<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/CEI2TEI/master/tei_cei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="charter_900024">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. MM. 24</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="DY">
               <resp when="1931">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>N. Denholm-Young</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TA">
               <resp when="2020">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Tuija Ainonen</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Bodleian Libraries</publisher>
            <address>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <street>Weston Library, Broad Street</street>
               <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>
               <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <!--Availability statement will be added here-->
            <idno type="msID">MS_D_D_Ch_Ch_MM_24</idno>
            <idno type="collection">D. D. Ch. Ch. (Deposited Deeds Christ Church)</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_D_D_Ch_Ch_MM_24" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <collection key="collection_100009">D. D. Ch. Ch. (Deposited Deeds Christ Church)</collection>
                  <!--change if a Bodleian document-->
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. MM. 24</idno>
               <idno type="ieArk">ark:29072/x02f75r9151c</idno><idno type="crArk">ark:29072/x02b88qd31q5</idno><altIdentifier><idno type="orderableItem">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. c. 39</idno></altIdentifier></msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="en">English</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <p>
                         
                        
                        Good <persName>Mr. <surname>Deane</surname>
                        </persName>, least I should seeme forgetfulle of
                        my good frends to whom I ame for many causes undeservedly behoulden, I have
                        at the last sent you myne opinion of the lease of <placeName type="manor" key="place_108239">Churche-Cowley</placeName> whereof you
                        delivered mee a coppie. ‘In which I note three things fitt to be considered.
                        First, what the case is: Secondly, what the lawe is: and thirdly, what
                        manour of proceedings are fittest to be used against the tennaunt. 
                        
                        1. What the case is. 
                        For the firste I finde it as harde to searche out the truth of the case, as beinge
                        searched oute to determine the points of lawe, but consideringe the coppye
                        of the lease with other Writings which I have receaved sithence of my Cosin,
                        <persName>Mr. <forename>Doctor</forename> 
                           <surname>Thornton</surname>
                        </persName>, 
                        I finde your case to be this. 
                        
                        <origDate notAfter="1536" notBefore="1535">Hen 8. an° 27.</origDate>
                        <persName>R. K. <surname>Abbott</surname>
                        </persName> by reccomendacion, 
                        but not by election of
                        the <orgName key="org_109067">Monastery of O<supplied>seney</supplied>
                        </orgName>: in the 
                        Countie of Oxon’ by Indenture bearinge date 15
                        Martii an°. 27°. H. 8. with the assent of the Covent demiseth unto H. R. and
                        L. his wife the mannour of Church-Cowley in the said countie of Oxon’, and
                        divers other lands. Habend to the said H., K. his wyfe, F. and L. theire
                        daughters and to the longest liver of them immediately after and as soone as
                        a certaine lease graunted to Jo: of … and Isa: his wyfe of Cowley aforesaid
                        is fully ended and expyred, by death, forfaiture surrender or otherwise,
                        unto the ende and terme of 31 yeares. 
                        
                        An°. 29°. In December an° 29° H. 8. a Conge deslier or licence to elect an Abbot to
                        the saied Monastery is graunted, the said R. L. is elected, the Kinge in
                        Januarie followinge assenteth to the election, and in Februarye the
                        temporalities are restored. 
                        
                        R. K.  now Abbot by election by Indenture bearinge date 14 Aprilis eodem an° H. 8.
                        viz: 29° with the assent of the Covent recitinge the former lease confirmeth
                        the same, and doeth farther by the same Indenture geive, demise and graunte
                        unto the saied H. and K. his wyfe, F. and L. theire daughters (but sheweth
                        not what hee doth geive or demise) habend’ to them and every of them for the
                        terme of the saied [sic] yeeres (with a space) after the forme and effecte
                        in the saied former Indentures specified and declared. The said Abbot and
                        Covent doe further by the same Indenture demise graunt and to ferme let unto
                        the saied H. R. the saied Mannour of Church Cowley and the saied other lands
                        Habend’ to him the saied H. and his assignes immediately and as soone as the
                        said lease made unto the saied H. and K. his wife for the terme of 31 yeeres
                        dated 15 Martii an° 27 H. 8. shall happen <pb n="190"/> to expire and ende,
                        unto the ende and terme of 68 yeeres yeildinge rent. 
                        
                        an°. 31°.
                        The saied Abbot in an° 31. H. 8. by the name of R. K. Reoven Episcopi commendatorie
                        of the Abbey of our blessed Ladye of O. in the countie of Oxon’ with the assent of the
                        Covent by deede under theire common scale doth surrender the Abbey and all
                        the lands there unto belonginge unto the Kinge; which is confirmed by
                        statute of 31 H. 8. 
                        
                        <supplied>f. 1d.</supplied> After, the Kinge by his letters patent graunteth the
                        Mannour of Church-Cowley inter alia to the <orgName key="org_101005">Deane and Chapter of the Cathedral Churche of Christ in Oxon</orgName>’ and to theire successors. 
                        
                        Thus far goethe your Case. 
                        
                        2. what the lawe is.
                        The pointe where you desire to be resolved is,
                        whether this Lease of the 14th of Aprille an° 29°. H. 8. bee a good lease
                        against the Deane and Chapter or not. To which I answere shortly, that it is
                        a voyed Lease in all: or not good for any more then Seaven yeares to come in
                        Apriell next. Whether it bee voied in all or no, I stand doubtfulle, but
                        that it can not bee good for any more then Seaven yeeres in Aprille next, I
                        ame resolute. 
                         For the pointe which hath carried awaye your
                        conceipt, I take yt it will not helpe you, or I finde that at the makinge of
                        the lease in 29° he was an Abbot by election and not by commendacion: as ys
                        conceaved: and whether he weare then Episco: Reoven’ 
                        (Whether it be materiall in common law, to make him onelie a
                            commandatorie Abbot, though he were elect, because he was at that tyme
                            also Episc. Revens’.) or not, I thinck in our Law it will not be
                        greately materialle. But the pointe whereupon I finde helpe for you is this.
                        The first Lease made by R. K. in Marche an° 27°. H. 8. for 31 yeeres in
                        revercion: was a meere voyed Lease bycause hee was then but a Commendatory
                        and had no power to make such a Lease. And when hee after in 29°. H. 8.
                        beinge a perfitt Abbot doeth confirme this Lease, that confirmacion is
                        likewise voied for that a voyed Lease can never bee made good by
                        confirmation. And when hee goeth on and saieth that he doeth geive demise
                        and graunt, these bee good Woords to have made a new demise, yf he had
                        expressed, what he did geive, demise, and graunte. And when he saieth
                        Habendum for the terme of the said <gap/> Yeeres (with a space) after the
                        forme and effect in the saied former Indenture specified and declared: I
                        thinke that the terme should have beene expressed in certaine, and that the
                        reference to the former Indenture is cleerely nought. Then the Lease for 31
                        yeeres beinge voyed, this is your Case. 
                        <pb n="191"/> 
                        A Lease is made for 68
                        yeeres to beginne uppon the expiracion of a voied lease: when this shall
                        beginne that is your pointe. The grounde of Lawe is, that yf a lease for
                        <gap/> yeeres have not a certaine tyme when it shall beginne and when it
                        shall ende, then it is voyed. The meaning was that this Lease should
                        beginne, when the voyed Lease by effluxion of tyme shoulde have ended, but
                        by Law this can not bee, for that a voyed Lease hath no tyme to beginne nor
                        no tyme to ende. Then the second Lease must either bee voied, or else the
                        Lawe must appoint a tyme when it shall beginne. Also the Lawe then, when it
                        shall beginne, and the answere is plaine: yf it shall beginne at all, it
                        must beginne from the makinge. And then from the 14 of Apriell an° 29° H. 8.
                        which was in the yeare 1537 to the 14th of Apriell an° 39 Eliz. in the yeere
                        1597, are iuste three-score yeeres and so of this Lease in Apriell next are
                        seaven yeeres to come. 
                        
                        3. What maner of proceeding is fittest to be used against the tenent.
                        Now for your proceedinge against the Tennaunt, yf you
                        shall resolve to attempt suite, then I have formerly directed a course yf
                        you thinke good to deale with the tennaunt by waye of mediatis, then you can
                        better advise yourselfe, then I can direct: if you would have mee to confer
                        with any other, I can like verie well of it. The coppie of the lease which I
                        receaved of you togeather with the other writings which I received of my
                        cosin <persName>
                           <surname>Thornton</surname>
                        </persName> I have sent you by this bearer. I have likewise sent you the
                        court Rolle of <placeName key="place_108012">Daventree</placeName>: which I wishe should bee kept amongst your
                        evidences of Daventree, that you maye have recourse to your Rolles as you
                        shall have occasion. 
                         
                        4. Whither our leete at Daventrie be loste by non use, or no. 
                        For the court Leete at Daventree I would bee glad
                        to keepe it when I maye bee assisted by your selfe or by somme of the
                        Chapter. You see how much wee have beene resisted when we have doen no more
                        than we have good authoritie in Lawe to doe: what shall I looke for them, yf
                        I goe alone to doe that which I knowe I can not instefie; I doubt that in
                        extremitie of Lawe, you have lost your Leete by not usinge it, and therefore
                        I would wishe that Mr. Attorney weare first made acquainted with it, and
                        that at Easter you should keepe bothe a leete and a courte Baron. And thus
                        havinge troubled you over longe, I hartely wishe you all comfortable
                        happinesse in Christ Jesus. 
                        <orgName role="date" key="org_105021">Grayes Inne</orgName> this of <origDate when="1597-10">October 1597°</origDate>. 
                        Your Wor’ assuredly
                        in what he can. </p>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="sheet">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <provenance>Archive of Cardinal College.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <bibl>N. Denholm-Young, <title>Cartulary of the Mediaeval Archives of Christ Church</title>, Oxford Historical Society o.s. 92 (1931), p.
                                <citedRange unit="page" from="189" to="191">189-191</citedRange>
                           </bibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021-06">First online publication</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>