<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/GVogeler/CEI2TEI/master/relax_ng_compact/tei_cei.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="charter_900059">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. MM. 58</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="DY">
               <resp when="1931">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>N. Denholm-Young</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TA">
               <resp when="2020">Encoding</resp>
               <persName>Tuija Ainonen</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Bodleian Libraries</publisher>
            <address>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <street>Weston Library, Broad Street</street>
               <settlement key="place_7011931">Oxford</settlement>
               <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <!--Availability statement will be added here-->
            <idno type="msID">MS_D_D_Ch_Ch_MM_58</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Deposited Deeds Christ Church</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_D_D_Ch_Ch_MM_58" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <collection>Deposited Deeds Christ Church</collection>
                  <!--change if a Bodleian document-->
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. MM. 58</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem>
                     <p>
                        
                        <hi rend="smallcap">The case truly stated betwixt the <orgName key="org_101005">dean and chapter of Christs Church in Oxford</orgName>, and <persName>
                              <forename>William</forename> 
                              <surname>Adkins</surname> butcher</persName>, concerning <placeName type="minor">Frideswides Medow</placeName> near <placeName key="place_105449">Oxford</placeName>.</hi> 
                         
                        The Dean and Chapter of Christs Church in Oxford were seised in fee, in right of
                        their Church, of a certain Medow called <pb n="198"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Frideswides</hi> Medow, lying
                        near unto <hi rend="italic">Oxford</hi>, and the
                        said Medow lying near unto <hi rend="italic">Oxford</hi> was, during the time that
                        <hi rend="italic">Oxford</hi> was a Garrison for
                        the late King, very much turfed and digged, and had several Bulworks made
                        upon it, and the Rivers of <hi rend="italic">
                           <placeName type="minor">Charwell</placeName>
                        </hi> and <hi rend="italic">
                           <placeName type="minor">Thames</placeName>
                        </hi>
                        were by His Majesties souldiers turned in upon it, and lay all over it
                        during the late wars, the better to keep the enemy from the Garrison; by
                        reason of which digging, turfing and floating, and the long lying of the
                        waters upon it, the same was almost altogether spoiled, and did bear nothing
                        but Flags and Sedge, and did become marshy ground, so that after the wars
                        the same was very little worth. Whereupon <persName>Dr. <hi rend="italic">
                              <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                           </hi> (now Lord Bishop of <hi rend="italic">
                              <placeName type="diocese" role="bishop" key="place_101090">Norwich</placeName>
                           </hi>) the Dean</persName>,
                        and the then Chapter of the said Church, conceiving that they were not enabled
                        by any Charter of Grant to hold the said Medow in their own hands, and to
                        their own uses, but that according to their trust they were obliged to let
                        the same at an improved rent in Com for the benefit of the whole Society,
                        which consists of a 100 Students and divers other Scholars, and being
                        desirous that the said Medow should be improved and made good again for the
                        benefit of themselves and their successors, did by their Indenture under
                        their Common Seal, bearing date the 20 day of Feb. in the year of our Lord
                        <origDate when="1649">1649</origDate>. demise the same unto the said <hi rend="italic">
                           <persName>
                              <forename>Will</forename>. <surname>Adkins</surname>
                           </persName>
                        </hi> for 21 years
                        thence next ensuing, at and under an improved rent in Money and Corn,
                        according to the Statute of the 18 <hi rend="italic">Eliz.</hi> and also finding by
                        old rent rolls and records, that the old rent of the said Medow was £10. 6s.
                            <hi rend="italic">per an.</hi> or thereabouts,
                        they did improve the same in Money and Com, which now usually amounts <hi rend="italic">Communibus annis</hi> to £35 <hi rend="italic">per an.</hi> which hath been
                        since paid and employed for the benefit of the whole Society, according to
                        the intent of the founder, and the said <hi rend="italic">Will. Adkins</hi> did also then
                        pay to the said Dean and Chapter for a fine for the said Lease the summe of £560. 
                        
                        That afterwards the said <hi rend="italic">Will Adkins</hi> was at very great 
                        charges for several years together,
                        in throwing down the Bulworks which were upon it, in dreining, scouring and
                        trenching the Rivers and Ditches, in laying soil and Compost upon the same,
                        and in planting many trees thereupon, and in other good husbandry, which
                        cost the said <hi rend="italic">Will. Adkins</hi>
                        at least £800 in so much that he did thereby improve the said Medow to be
                        worth yearly as much more as it was worth when the said 
                        <hi rend="italic">Will. Adkins</hi> did first enter upon it. 
                        
                        That after this the said <hi rend="italic">Will Adkins</hi> did renew the
                        Lease from the Dean and Chapter again, who by their Indenture under their
                        Common Seal, bearing date the 10 day of March <origDate when="1654">1654</origDate>. did demise <pb n="199"/>
                        unto the said <hi rend="italic">Will. Adkins</hi>
                        for 21 years thence next ensuing, at and under the said former improved rent
                        in Money and Com, for which said new Lease <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> did pay unto 
                        them the summe of £300. for a Fine whereby it appears that the said Adkins did
                        disburse in Fines and the said other Charges for improving the said
                        Premisses, the sume of £1600 at the least. 
                        
                        That the said Medow after all his said Charges upon it, not being worth above £100
                        <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> the Profits
                        thereof hitherto have not near satisfied unto him the yearly Interest of his
                        money, and the Colledge yearly Rents and Taxes, that he hath paid for the
                        same. 
                        
                        And yet notwithstanding, after the Restitution of his Majesty, 
                        <persName>Dr. <hi rend="italic">
                              <surname>Fell</surname>
                           </hi>
                        </persName> being made
                        Dean of Christ Church, he and the present Chapter being desirous to have the said
                        Medow to their own uses again, and pretending that the said <hi rend="italic">Adkin’s</hi> Lease was void in
                        Law, in regard that the said Medow had not formerly been demised, did
                        without allowing any satisfaction to the said <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> about two 
                        years since Commence an action of Ejectment in the name of one 
                        <hi rend="italic">
                           <persName>
                              <forename>Thomas</forename> 
                              <surname>Hudson</surname>
                           </persName>
                        </hi> Gentleman, as
                        their Lessee for the term of five years, to recover the possession of the
                        same from <hi rend="italic">Adkins,</hi> and the
                        said Cause coming to tryal at the same Assizes for the County of <hi rend="italic">Oxford,</hi> 
                        in the year <origDate when="1661">1661</origDate> the said Defendant <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi>
                        did then make proof of all the matters of fact, and the Jury were then ready
                        to have given a Verdict for <hi rend="italic">Adkins,</hi> but 
                        Dr. <hi rend="italic">Fell</hi> the Dean, and 
                        <persName>Dr. <hi rend="italic">
                              <surname>Dolben</surname>
                           </hi> the Treasurer</persName> of the said Colledge, being both present in
                        the Court, perceiving the same, did move the Judge that the matters in
                        difference betwixt the said parties should be referred to the determination
                        and award of an Arbitrator of their own choosing, and thereupon it was
                        ordered at the said Assizes, that a Verdict by consent should be found for
                        the Plaintiffs, and that all the differences betwixt the parties should be
                        referred to the said Arbitrator, and that the <hi rend="italic">Postea</hi>
                        should remain in the hands of the Clerk of the Assizes, untill 
                        <persName>Mr. Justice <hi rend="italic">
                              <surname>Windham</surname>
                           </hi>
                        </persName>
                        should give order to the contrary, as by that order may appear. 
                        
                        Upon which reference the said
                        arbitrator did take much pains to settle the differences betwixt them, but
                        could not; and did therefore at last (to prevent the ruin of the said
                        <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> and his family) on
                        his own award in writing, bearing date on the 28. day of October, <origDate when="1661">1661</origDate>.
                        betwixt the said parties, award that the said Dean and Chapter should pay to
                        the said <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi>, towards the
                        satisfaction of all his Monies and Costs, the summe of £600 at our Lady-day
                        then next following; and that in case the said Monies should be then paid,
                        that then the said <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi>
                        should surrender up his possession <pb n="200"/> and Lease to them; but in
                        case that the Monies should not be then paid, that then the said <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> or his Assignes
                        should hold and enjoy the said Medow for the term of 7 years only then next
                        ensuing, and that at the end of the term of 7 years deliver up his Lease and
                        possession to the said Dean and Chapter, as by the Award may appear. 
                        
                        And although the said Arbitrator did not award unto <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> one 
                        half of the Monies due to him, or that in case the said Monies should not be paid to
                        him, did award to him but one half of the term, he having 14. years to come
                        in his term at the time of the said Award; yet the said Dean and Chapter did
                        refuse to stand to the Award made by the said Arbitrator of their own
                        choosing; and yet notwithstanding all the said premisses, the said Dean and
                        Chapter did in the last Mich, term commence a new action of Ejectment in the
                        name of the said <hi rend="italic">
                           <persName>
                              <forename>Thomas</forename> 
                              <surname>Hudson</surname>
                           </persName>
                        </hi> 
                        their former Lessee, against the said <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> for the recovering
                        the possession of the said Medow from him, and the Cause did come to tryal
                        this last Assizes at <hi rend="italic">Oxford,</hi>
                        and a Jury did appear, which were returned by the Prothonotary the last term
                        by order of the <orgName key="org_108015">Court of Common-pleas</orgName>. 
                        
                        And the Defendant <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> having made full
                        proof of all the Monies disbursed by him for the benefit of the Inheritance
                        of the said Colledge, and all the said before mentioned matters of fact, the
                        Jury after a long and full evidence given on both sides, did find their
                        Verdict for the Defendant <hi rend="italic">Adkins.</hi> 
                        
                        And yet notwithstanding it is endeavoured that a Proviso be
                        added unto the Act for confirming of Colledge Leases, that the said Act
                        shall not extend to confirm any Leases made of any Lands which were not let
                        or dimised for eleven years or more before the year of our Lord 1640, which
                        Proviso, if it should passe, would destroy the said Lease of <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi>, 
                        and many more Leases, which this Dean <hi rend="italic">Fell,</hi> and the present
                        Chapter of Christs Church have confirmed of Lands never let before in Lease, 
                        till Bishop <hi rend="italic">Reynolds</hi> let them at that
                        time when <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> took his
                        Lease of him. 
                        
                        And likewise at <orgName key="org_108011">All-souls Colledge</orgName> in <hi rend="italic">Oxon</hi>
                        they have renewed
                        severall Leases of Lands that were never put in Lease, till much about the
                        time that <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> took his Lease of 
                        Bishop <hi rend="italic">Reynolds</hi>, and at <orgName key="org_109038">New Colledge</orgName> in
                        Oxford they have renewed with many Tenants with in
                        this year and a half, and confirmed their Leases of Lands that were never
                        put in Lease before about twelve years ago by those that were then
                        Governours in that place. 
                        
                        And yet <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi> doubts not but to
                        prove and make it appear that the said Medow hath been in ancient times
                        demised at an old <pb n="201"/> Rent, and the said Lease is good by the Laws
                        of this Land, if it be not avoided by the said Provise. 
                        
                        And it is manifestly known that Dr. <hi rend="italic">Fell</hi> who lays
                        claim to half this Medow for himself, as he is now Dean of Christs Church,
                        was never formerly invested in any part of it, nor those five Canons
                        likewise who seek to take the other from <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi>, and the 
                        improved Rent from the Students, which likewise were not formerly invested in these
                        Lands. And the other two old Canons are those that were there when 
                        Bishop <hi rend="italic">Reynolds</hi> let the Lease to 
                        <hi rend="italic">Adkins</hi>, and took their Fines, and remain established
                        Canons there still. 
                        
                        <hi rend="italic">The premisses considered, it is
                            humbly submitted to judgment what these Leases can he worth to those
                            Tenants who have paid great Fines, and have renewed their Leases within
                            these two years, with these Governours, if they he called away, and
                            other Governours put in their places.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">And therefore the said</hi>
                        Adkins <hi rend="italic">humbly prays and hopes
                            that the said Proviso shall not passe, but that his Lease may be
                            confirmed as well as other Colledge Leases, and that the Law may
                            determine the Title of the same betwixt him and the said Dean and
                            Chapter.</hi>
                        <!--TODO - language?-->
                    </p>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="sheet">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>parchment</support>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <provenance>Archive of Cardinal College.</provenance>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <bibl>N. Denholm-Young, <title>Cartulary of the Mediaeval Archives of Christ Church</title>, Oxford Historical Society 92 (1931), p.
                                <citedRange unit="page" from="197" to="201">197-201</citedRange>
                           </bibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021-06">First online publication</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
