<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/CEI2TEI/master/tei_cei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="collection_100058">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>D. D. Ewelme Honour</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="BOD">
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Bodleian Libraries</publisher>
            <address>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <street>Weston Library, Broad Street</street>
               <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
               <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="msID">D. D. Ewelme Honour</idno>
            <idno type="collection">D. D. Ewelme Honour</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-05">First online publication</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Documents concerning views of frankpledge of the Honour of Ewelme between 1712 and 1720, relating to Ardington, Hinton and Purley or Tidmarsh
            in Berks., High Wycombe, Quainton, Shabbington and Wingrave in Bucks., Cherrington and Little Rissington in Gloucs., Allington and Sutton Scotney in
            Hants, Uxbridge in Middlesex, Aston Rowant, Bicester, Binfield, Chalgrove,
            Checkendon, Chinnor, Clanfield, Ewelme, Great Haseley, Horspath, Lewknor and Thrupp in Oxfordshire. </p><p>"The papers are now arranged in three boxes referenced MSS. D.D. Ewelme honour d. 1-3 and comprise thirteen bundles. Each bundle contains a series of packets made
               up ofloose papers relating to a single view of frankpledge . The last leaf of each packet
               is the view itself. This is headed by the names of the place and steward, and the date.
               Then follows a list of the tithings with the names of the constables and tithingmen
               and their successors in case of a change. Then comes a list of the jurors. The
               presentments sometimes follow and sometimes are on a different piece of paper.
               Most of the other pieces in each packet contain, on separate scraps of paper, the lists
               of male inhabitants submitted by the tithingmen or constables. Each scrap has
               been given a separate reference number, consisting of bundle number, packet
               number and item number separated by strokes." (W. O. Hassall, 'Ewelme Honour Court Leets, 1712-1720', Oxoniensia 15 (1950), 114-117 [<ref target="https://www.oxoniensia.org/volumes/1950/notes.pdf#page=11">pdf</ref>])</p>
         <p>Belonged to Richard Carter of Chilton, steward of the Honour c. 1715, and descended by inheritance to Sir John Aubrey, Bt., of Boarstall and Dorton; transferred from the Buckinghamshire Archaeological Society (Aubrey Fletcher estate documents) to the Bodleian Library .</p>
         <p><ref target="https://charters.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/?f%5Bms_collection_s%5D%5B%5D=D.+D.+Ewelme+Honour&amp;f%5Btype%5D%5B%5D=charter">Browse this collection.</ref></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
