<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/CEI2TEI/master/tei_cei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="collection_100009">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>D. D. Ch. Ch. (Deposited Deeds Christ Church)</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="BOD">
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Bodleian Libraries</publisher>
            <address>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <street>Weston Library, Broad Street</street>
               <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
               <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="msID">D. D. Ch. Ch. (Deposited Deeds Christ Church)</idno>
            <idno type="collection">D. D. Ch. Ch. (Deposited Deeds Christ Church)</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-05">First online publication</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Medieval archives of Christ Church Oxford, principally relating to the religious houses used to endow Cardinal College and later Christ Church: St Frideswide's, Osney, Thame, and Littlemore, Oxfordshire; Tickford, Bradwell, Notley, and Ravenstone, Buckinghamshire; Daventry, Northamptonshire; Canwell and Sandwell, Staffordshire; Tunbridge and Lesnes, Kent; Beigham and 'De calceto', Sussex; Wix, Tiptree, Blackmore, Stanesgate, Horkesley, and Thoby, Essex; Poghly and Wallingford, Berkshire; Dodnash and Snape, Suffolk. According to Anthony Wood, Christ Church had cared for only a part of the archive and neglected the remainder. It seems to have been this remainder that Wood acquired and later bequeathed to the Ashmolean Museum from where they were transferred to the Bodleian in 1860. Wood's charters are now divided among the various county series in Bodleian's MSS. Ch. and MSS. Rolls collections. The present collection remained at Christ Church until 1927 when it was placed on deposit in the Bodleian.</p>
         <p>The arrangement is as follows:
            <list>
               <item>D. D. Ch. Ch. D.: Daventry Priory, arranged partly by tenement, partly alphabetically by parish.</item>
               <item>D. D. Ch. Ch. F.: St Frideswide's Oxford, arranged to follow the order of items as printed in  Robert Wigram, <title>The cartulary of the Monastery of St. Frideswide at Oxford</title>, 2 vols. (1895-6) </item>
               <item>D. D. Ch. Ch. M.: other religious houses, arranged by institution (M. 1-36, Wallingford Priory; M. 37-44, St Leonard's Clattercote; M. 45-55, Ravenstone Priory; M. 56-84A, Tewkesbury Abbey; M. 85-101, Eynsham Abbey; M. 102-110, Thame Abbey; M. 111-126, Bolton Priory; M. 126-9, Priory of Holy Trinity York; M. 130-4, St Wulftan's hospital Worcester).</item>
               <item>D. D. Ch. Ch. MM.: records of Cardinal College and Christ Church, arranged alphabetically by county.</item>
               <item>D. D. Ch. Ch. O.: Osney Abbey, arranged to follow the order of items as printed in  H. E. Salter, <title>Cartulary of Oseney Abbey</title>, 6 vols. (1929-1936).</item>
            </list></p>
         <p><ref target="https://charters.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/?f%5Bms_collection_s%5D%5B%5D=D.+D.+Ch.+Ch.+%28Deposited+Deeds+Christ+Church%29&amp;f%5Btype%5D%5B%5D=charter">Browse this collection.</ref></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
