<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/CEI2TEI/master/tei_cei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="collection_100053">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Yorks. (Yorkshire)</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="BOD">
               <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Matthew Holford</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Bodleian Libraries</publisher>
            <address>
               <orgName type="department">Special Collections</orgName>
               <orgName type="unit">Bodleian Libraries</orgName>
               <orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
               <street>Weston Library, Broad Street</street>
               <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
               <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="msID">Yorks. (Yorkshire)</idno>
            <idno type="collection">Yorks. (Yorkshire)</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Western</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-05">First online publication</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>As with other series shelfmarked MS. Ch. and MS. Rolls, this is an artificial collection created from a range of archival sources, and the provenance of individual items is not always known.</p>
         <p>The collection catalogued in 1878 comprised MSS. Ch. Yorks. 1-344 and MSS. Rolls Yorks. 1-19. The bulk seems to have formed the collection of the Yorkshire antiquarian Ralph Thoresby, briefly described in his <title>Ducatus Leodiensis</title> (1715). This collection passed to Thoresby’s nephew, Thomas Wilson (schoolmaster of Leeds and antiquarian), was acquired from him by Richard Rawlinson, and was given by Rawlinson to the Bodleian. </p><p>
            It is not always possible to identify the provenance of individual items, and Rawlinson also obtained charters from the collections of Thomas Hearne and Peter le Neve. <!--(see Enright, p. 290 and n., 302 (citing 8o Rawl. 707, pp. 96, 261), and app. D p. iii).--> B. J. Enright, 'Richard Rawlinson: collector, antiquary, and topographer' (DPhil thesis, Oxford, 1957), appendix D, lists charters in all the Bodleian collections then identifiable as Rawlinson’s; a few others can be added from Thomas Wilson’s papers and a transcript of some of Wilson’s papers (MS. Top. Yorks. e. 2). </p><p>
            The main later accessions are as follows:
            <list><item>Ch. 358-365: papers of the Hussey family (see the collection overview for Lincolnshire), presented in 1920-5 by the trustees of the Marquis of Waterford’s estate (see also New Summary Catalogue nos. 54418-503 and cf. Bodleian Quarterly Record vol. 3 p. 5).</item><item>
            Ch. 367-516: part of the collection given by Miss M. Miss Peacock, 1921 (see the collection overview for Lincolnshire)</item><item>
            Ch. 549-573: bought from  Miss J. Ratcliffe, 1968</item></list>
         </p>
         <p><ref target="https://charters.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/?f%5Bms_collection_s%5D%5B%5D=Yorks.+%28Yorkshire%29&amp;f%5Btype%5D%5B%5D=charter">Browse this collection.</ref></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
