<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="county">
            <head>BEDFORDSHIRE </head>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <placeName>BEDFORD</placeName>, Grey Friers at. Indenture, 20 June, <date>30 Hen.
                     VIII</date>. <persName><forename>Thomas</forename> <surname>Mender</surname></persName>, the warden, and convent of the Grey Friers,
                  Bedford, lease to <persName><forename>William</forename> <surname>Clark</surname></persName> of Renhale a close called ' Bishop's Close ' for
                  twenty years, at an annual rent of 205. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Beds. 1</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <placeName>CALDWELL</placeName>, Priory of. Proceedings in a suit between the
                  abbot and convent of Oseney of the one part, and Hugh, the prior, and convent of
                  Caldwell of the other, concerning the payment to Oseney of an annual pension of 12
                  marks. [<date notBefore="1322">1322-1323</date>.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MSS. Ch. Beds. 2-19</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <placeName>HARWOLD</placeName>, Priory of. An acknowledgment from <persName><forename>Elizabeth</forename> <surname>Chilton</surname></persName>, the prioress, and convent of Harwold that they have received from sir
                  <persName><forename>Henry</forename> <surname>Brounflete</surname></persName>, kt., lord Vescy, 465. 8d., being arrears of a certain annual
                  rent of 6s. 8d. Dated 6 May, <date>4 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Beds. 
                     20</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <placeName>LITTON</placeName>. <persName><forename>Agnes</forename> <surname>Kypping</surname></persName>, late wife of <persName><forename>William</forename> <surname>Kypping</surname></persName>
                  deceased, and <persName><forename>John</forename> <surname>Kypping</surname></persName>, son and heir of the said William, grant to <persName><forename>Valentine</forename> <surname>Bailis</surname></persName> and others 2 acres of land in a field called 'Blacwaterfeld' of Luton.
                  Dated at Luton, 20 Dec., <date>i Hen. V</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Beds. 
                     21</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> <persName><forename>Thomas</forename> <surname>Bray</surname></persName>, senior, of Cadington, co. Herts., husbandman, sells to <persName><forename>William</forename> <surname>Deyne</surname></persName>
                  of Luton, yeoman, a messuage situated in Churche Streete. Dated 6 March, <date>4
                     Ed. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Beds.  22</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Power of attorney given by Lodowicke, duke of Lennox, earl of Richmond, to sir
                  <persName><forename>Robert</forename> <surname>Napier</surname></persName> of Luton Hooe, co. Bedf., kt. and bart., to compound touching
                  Kedwelley business, &amp;c. Dated 30 March, <date when="1616">1616</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Beds. 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <placeName>RENHALE</placeName>. William, son of Richard de . . . . grants to
                  Godefr' de Aldeholt a meadow in Renhale which is of the honor of Boulogne at an
                  annual rent of Sd. For this donation the said Godefr' paid 85. (<date when="1200"
                     precision="low">c. 1200</date>.) [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Beds. 
                        24</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="2"/>
                  <placeName>WOTTON</placeName>. Memorandum from Stephen Estwicke of Wotton, that he
                  has received from <persName><forename>William</forename> <surname>Dernier</surname></persName> or Dormer of London a deed dated 23 April,
                  <date>3 Eliz.</date>, concerning lands at Wotton. Dated 3 Feb., <date>20
                     Eliz.</date>
                  <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Beds.  25</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <placeName>CALDWELL</placeName>, Priory of. Copy of a process before the abbot of
                  Eynesham, judge, between the abbot and convent of Oseney of the one part, and the
                  prior and convent of Caldwell of the other part, concerning a right to an annual
                  pension. A. 0.<date when="1322">1322</date>. [Mutilated.] Bedfordshire <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Rolls Beds. 1</bibl> . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <placeName>HIGHAM GOBIAN</placeName>. Court Rolls for the manor of Higham Gobian,
                  with its members Streteley and Sharpenho, from the Friday after the feast of the
                  Ascension <date>29 Hen. VI</date>, to the Monday before the feast of All Saints
                  <date>30 Hen. VI</date>. [Four courts. Philip Botiller, esq., lord of the
                  manor.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Rolls Beds. 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Rental, made <date>31 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 3</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         
         <div type="county">
            <head>CHESHIRE</head>
            
            <div type="charter">
               <p> . "Writ from King George the First addressed to <persName><forename>John</forename> <surname>Hannam</surname></persName>, Isaac Knight and
                  "<persName><forename>William</forename> <surname>Salmon</surname></persName>, to receive the oaths of <persName><forename>Henry</forename> <surname>Delves</surname> , esq.</persName>, upon appointment as
                  justice of the peace for the county of Chester. Dated 1 6 Dec., i oth of his
                  reign. Cheshire Charters, 6. The oath upon being appointed justice of the peace
                  for Cheshire. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Form of oath of abjuration for a justice of peace. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHESTER (Abbey of St. Werburgh's). Confirmation by King Henry V of the donations,
                  concessions, liberties and muniments belonging to the abbey of St. Werburgh,
                  Chester. Dated at Winchester, 19 April, 2nd of his reign. <persName><forename>Richard</forename> de <surname>Cleymundestowe</surname></persName> notary. [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire 13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHESTER (Bishoprick of). Letters for deacon's orders from Nicholas, bishop of
                  Chester, to Jonathan Wilkinson. Dated 20 May, <date when="1695">1695</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Certificate of subscription to articles by Jonathan Wilkinson, upon being
                  admitted priest. Dated 23 Sept., <date when="1695">1695</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Certificate of subscription to the articles upon the admission of <persName><forename>Edmund</forename> <surname>Pughe</surname></persName> to
                  the office of priest, by Nicholas, bishop of Chester. Dated n June, <date
                     when="1704">1704</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CONGLETON. <persName><forename>Henry</forename> de <surname>Lacy</surname></persName>, earl of Lincoln, grants to Benedict, son of <persName><forename>Walter</forename> de <surname>Stanleg</surname></persName>', four acres of land with appurtenances of the waste in the territory of
                  his town of Congleton, at an annual rent for each acre of 6d. [With seal] Ch. i.
                  <pb n="46"/> CHESHIRE. HATTON near DERESBURY. <persName><forename>John</forename> <surname>Hatton</surname></persName>, Stephen Sompnor of
                  Leigh near Acton Brygge, and <persName><forename>Hugh</forename> <surname>Colstanehok</surname> , clerk</persName>, grant to <persName><forename>Peter</forename> <surname>Hatton</surname></persName> of
                  Hatton their capital messuage in Hatton near Deresbury with all other messuages
                  &amp;c. in the village and territory of Hatton, to hold the same to him for his
                  life with remainder to his sons. Also they appoint <persName><forename>Henry</forename> <surname>Grymesdych</surname></persName> near Norcoot
                  and <persName><forename>Thomas</forename> <surname>Hatton</surname></persName> of Crooton to give seisin of the same. Dated at Hatton, 9 Dec.,
                  <date>2 Hen. VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> KIRKHAM, LANCASHIRE. An acquittance of John, bishop of Chester, for 6 1 35. 4^.
                  for half a year's pension going out of the church of Kirkham, by the hands of
                  master <persName><forename>Richard</forename> <surname>Anderton</surname></persName>, receiver of Ch. Ch., Oxon. [Mutilated.] Temp. Hen. VIII.
                  <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PICKMERE. Will of <persName><forename>John</forename> <surname>Arderne</surname></persName> of Pickmere, co. Chester, gentleman, made <date
                  when="1698">1698</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire  9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ROTHESTORN. Receipt given by <persName><forename>Richard</forename> <surname>Smyth</surname></persName>, archdeacon of Chester, for 2 is. Sd.,
                  last day of Oct., <date when="1542">1542</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire 
                     10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WIBBUNBURY. The master of the fraternity of the chapel and hospital of St. Cross
                  and St. George of Wibbymbury grants to <persName><forename>John</forename> <surname>Fenton</surname></persName> and Agnes his wife
                  participation in all the masses celebrated in the said chapel and all other works
                  of charity in life and in death. Dated at Wibbymbury, 4 July, <date when="1464"
                     >1464</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cheshire 11</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         
         <div type="county">
            <head>CORNWALL</head>
            
            <div type="charter">
               <p>TAMERTON (North). An exemplification of a suit in Avowry and of the fine, from
                  <persName><forename>Thomas</forename> <surname>French</surname></persName>, gentleman, to <persName><forename>John</forename> <surname>Moore</surname></persName>, gentleman, of and concerning 3 messuages,
                  3 gardens, 60 acres of land, 20 of meadow, 100 of pasture, 100 of furze and
                  brushwood, and 40 acres of maze, in Allistonwaye and Tamerton, and common of
                  pasture in Tamerton More. Tested at Westminster, 1 7 June, 1 <date>1 James
                     I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cornwall 1</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An exemplification of a recovery by <persName><forename>John</forename> <surname>French</surname></persName> and Alice his wife against
                  Thomasine Crewkerne, widow, and <persName><forename>John</forename> <surname>Trewene</surname></persName> upon an assize, of a tenement in
                  Aliston in the parish of Tamerton. Dated <date>7 Elizabeth</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cornwall 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="county">
            <head>CUMBERLAND</head>
            
            <div type="charter">
               <p> . Henry, son of Rocelle of Cornay, grants to God, the blessed Mary and St. John,
                  and to the hospital of Jerusalem, and the brethren of the same house, the whole of
                  his land of ' Bracchane thait,' namely to these divisions, from the gate which is
                  upon the bank of ' Kirkeslecbec ' and as far as to the ditch towards the moat, and
                  from the chief ditch by the hedge which extends itself beyond Starcimes towards
                  Blasich, and just as Blasich falls into Bracamethaccbec and by that river
                  descending to the ditch on the south part of Brachamechacc and by the ditch to
                  Kirkesletboc and by Kirkesletbec ascending to the foresaid bridge. To hold the
                  same in free alms for the health of his soul, &amp;c. (<date when="1200"
                     precision="low">c. 1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cumb. 1.</bibl></p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="47"/> CUMBERLAND. LANCASTER (Hospital of St. Leonard's). Henry, duke of
                  Lancaster, earl of Derby, &amp;c., empowers sir <persName><forename>Henry</forename> de <surname>Heydock</surname></persName>, chancellor of
                  Lancaster, to confirm to the prioress and convent of Seton the hospital of St.
                  Leonard of Lancaster to them and their successors. Dated at the castle of
                  Lancaster, 27 March, <date>30 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Cumb. 2</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         
         <div type="county">
            <head>DERBYSHIRE</head>
            
            <div type="charter">
               <p> . CODNOB, HAYNOB, LOSCOE, LANGLEY, and MILNEHAY. Indenture made 2 Feb., n Charles
                  I, being the settlement upon the marriage of sir <persName><forename>Paul</forename> <surname>Neile</surname></persName>, knight, son of the
                  lord archbishop of York, to <persName><forename>Elizabeth</forename> <surname>Place</surname></persName>, one of the daughters and heires of
                  <persName><forename>William</forename> <surname>Place</surname> , gent.</persName>, deceased, by which certain lands in the above villages are
                  settled to the use of the said Paul and Elizabeth. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >MS. Ch. Derbs. 1 </bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> DERBY. Indenture made i Oct., <date>30 Hen. VIII</date>, by which Thomas, the
                  abbot, and convent of St. Mary's, Darley, demise to <persName><forename>Richard</forename> <surname>Hey</surname></persName> of Derby ten acres
                  of land and two acres of meadow in Derby for 80 years at an annual rent of us.
                  [With sealJ] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs. 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> KALFDON. Bertram, son of William, son of Ralph, grants to Nicholas the clerk, son
                  of Geoffrey the clerk of Esseburn, and his heirs, eight bovates of land in Kalfdon
                  and three tofts with three .... paying annually for the same los. For this
                  concession the said Nicholas gave two marks of silver, (<date when="1200"
                     precision="low">c. 1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs. 12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LE DALE, or * De parco Stanley.' Copy of a charter by which Richard, son of <persName><forename>Peter</forename> de <surname>Sandiacre</surname></persName>, confirms to the church and the canons of St. Mary of Stanley Park in
                  frankalmoigne the whole of his wood of Drisco, with the land of the same ; also he
                  quit-claims all his right in the wood which is called Blithgare, with the whole of
                  the land from the rivulet of * Bromesbroc' between the park of Chirchehalla, and
                  the park of Stanley as far as ' in Wacellum ' near the park of Chirchehalla, and
                  from thence the whole wood with the land from the aforesaid ' Wacellum ' on the
                  west part of the old way which is nearest to the wood of Chirchehala, as far as
                  the way which divided the wood of Chirchehala and the wood of Westhala. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs.  11</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MEASHAM. Indenture made 20 Oct., <date>33 Elizabeth</date>, by which the right
                  honourable Henry, earl of Huntingdon, &amp;c., in consideration of a sum of money
                  paid to him by sir <persName><forename>George</forename> <surname>Hastings</surname></persName> of Copishill, co. Leicester, grants all the
                  tithes, glebe land, &amp;c. in Messam, co. Derby, belonging to the rectory of
                  Repingdon in the said county. [Seal and signature of H. Huntingdon.'] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs.  3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Counterpart of the deed, dated 20 Oct., 33 Queen Elizabeth. [Seal and signature
                  of sir <persName><forename>George</forename> <surname>Hastings</surname></persName>.^ <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs.  4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 14 June, i James I, by which George, earl of Huntingdon, &amp;c.,
                  in consideration of the receipt of 25, demises to <persName><forename>Nicholas</forename> <surname>Taylor</surname></persName> of Measham
                  certain land in Measham for 99 years, at an annual rent of 2os. and two capons.
                  <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs.  5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture dated i April, 1 <date>6 James I</date>, by which the right honourable
                  <pb n="48"/> DERBY. Henry, earl of Huntingdon, &amp;c., in consideration of the
                  good services of <persName><forename>Edward</forename> <surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>, servant of the said earl, have granted to him
                  for his life and three years after, a messuage and tenement standing upon part of
                  the parsonage of Mesam, co. Derby, for an annual rent of 2os. [Seal and signature
                  of the said earl.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs.  6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 7 Nov., <date>8 Charles I</date>, by which Henry, earl of
                  Huntingdon, in consideration of the receipt of 1580, sells to William "Wollaston
                  of Shenton, co. Leicester, esq., the rectory or parsonage of Measam in the county
                  of Derby. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs.  7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> REPINGDON. Indenture dated 9 May, 34 Queen Elizabeth, by which Henry, earl of
                  Huntingdon, &amp;c. and sir <persName><forename>George</forename> <surname>Hastings</surname></persName>, kt., for the sum of 550 paid to the
                  said sir George, sells to the right honourable sirEdmonde Sheffeyld, kt., lord
                  Sheffeylde, the glebe lands, tithes of corn and hay, &amp;c. in Messam,
                  Parkington, Okthorpe and Denisthorpe, cos. of Darbie and Leicester, belonging to
                  the rectory of Repingdon. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs.  8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> "WINSTEB. Indenture witnessing that <persName><forename>William</forename> de <surname>Birchover</surname></persName> demises to <persName><forename>Richard</forename> <surname>Gerard</surname></persName> and Agnes his wife 3 messuages, half a bovate of land, 3 acres of land,
                  with a meadow adjoining in Winster, paying annually for the same 17d. of silver.
                  Dated at Winster the Thursday next after the feast of the beheading of St. John
                  the baptist, <date>8 Ed. III</date>. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs. 
                     9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> <persName><forename>Richard</forename> <surname>Gerard</surname></persName> grants to <persName><forename>William</forename> de <surname>Birchovere</surname></persName> three messuages, the half of one
                  bovate and three acres of land in Wynster. Also he gave the same William all his
                  goods moveable and immoveable in the same tenement at the time of the making of
                  this charter. Dated at Wynster the Monday on the feast of the beheading of St.
                  John the baptist, <date>8 Ed. III</date>. [ With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Derbs. 
                     10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
