<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="county">
            <head>BUCKINGHAMSHIRE</head>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ADDINGTON, BOTTLE CLEYDON, and BAMPTON, Oxon. Fine made at Westminster on the
                  morrow of the Purification B.V.M., <date>7 Hen. VII</date>, between Thomas
                  Kebeell, sergeant at law, Robert Monie, clerk, Thomas Entwesill, William Strode,
                  John Lolle, and Thomas Jakes, querents, and sir Edward Hastynges of Hastynges,
                  kt., and Mary his wife, deforciarits of the manor of Adyngton, 15 messuages, 500
                  acres of land, 200 acres of meadow, 300 acres of pasture, 4 acres of brushwood, 20
                  acres of marsh, loos, rent, and the rents of lib. pepper and lib. cummin with
                  appurtenances in Adyngton, and Botelcleydon, co. Bucks. ; and of the manor of
                  Bampton, with appurtenances, and of 4 messuages, 400 acres of land, 100 acres of
                  meadow, 60 acres of pasture, 3 acres of wood, 5 acres of brushwood, 20 acres of
                  marsh, and loos, rent in Bampton, co. Oxon, which said manors, etc. are
                  acknowledged to be the right of the said Thomas Kebeel and others, they paying to
                  the said Edward and,. Mary 600 marks of silver. Buckinghamshire Charters, 61.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> AG-ECOTE. Sir Walter de Hyda grants to sir Roger de Mulent, bp. Cov. and Lich.,
                  the whole of his land which he has in a tenement of Agecote, with messuages,
                  rents, and services, to hold the same for ever of John de Englefeld and his heirs,
                  paying annually to the said John and his heirs one clove ; for which concession
                  the said Roger gave 20 marks sterling, (<date notBefore="1272" notAfter="1273"
                     precision="low">c. 1272-3</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 66</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BITTLESDEN, Abbey of. Memorandum that Wednesday after the feast of St. Ambrose
                  the bishop, a citation was issued by H., Prior of Lenton, and conservator of the
                  privileges and indulgences of the Cistercian order in the province of Canterbury,
                  to the sub-prior of Esseby and the rector of Codesford, to admonish Ralph, vicar
                  of Tornebr' (Thornborough), in the deanery of Bucks., and the prior and convent of
                  Luffeld to abstain from all molestation towards the abbot and convent of
                  Bittlesden, failing obedience to which monition to cite <pb n="24"/> them to
                  appear in the church of St. Mary the virgin, Nottingham, on Monday next after the
                  Ascension of our Lord. [ With sedl.~] Dated at Lenton, <date when="1251"
                     >1251</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 91</bibl> . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>BRADWELL, Priory of. Charter setting forth the grant of the priory of Bradwell to
                  William Holgyll, clerk, Thomas Stanley, esq., John Gostwyke and Thomas Cromwell by
                  sir John Longueville, kt. (by heirship, founder of the same), to the use of Thomas
                  Wolsey, archbishop of York, with a recital of their concession to the said
                  archbishop. [Much mutilated.'] Dated . . . . <date>16 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 63</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CLIFTON, EMBERTON, and PETTESHO. John Bartelmen of Emberton grants to sir Henry
                  le Chaumberleyn, rector of the church of Cumberworth, the whole of his capital
                  messuage in Emberton, i6%d. and % of annual rent and certain parcels of land in
                  Clifton, Emberton, and Pettesho, together with the reversion of 3 roods of land
                  upon Kersewelle furlang after the decease of Roger Gerebray, paying to the chief
                  lord the accustomed service, and to the fraternity of St. John of Jerusalem
                  annually id. Dated at Pettesho the Sunday next before the feast of St. Bar-
                  tholomew the apostle, <date>10 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                  67</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HADDENHAM. Proceedings in the bishop of Lincoln's court against Henry de
                  Swanebourn, vicar of Hadenham, for non-residence and dilapidations of his house
                  and chancel of the church, and for demising the fruits and oblations of his
                  vicarage to Alan Arches a laick to farm, with examination of witnesses concerning
                  the same. [An. <date when="1316">1316</date>.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     68</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> 68*. HANSLAPE. Simon le Veel of Hamslape grants to Joan Roger of the same place a
                  messuage in Hamslape. Dated at Hamslape the Monday next before the feast of St.
                  Augustine, <date>36 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 69</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Joane Rogger of Hampslape grants to Simon le Veel of the same place, and Joane
                  his wife, the whole of that tenement and land which she has in the village of
                  Hampslap of the gift of Simon, formerly father of the said Simon, paying annually
                  2d. to the chaplain of the parish church of Hamslape for 2 masses. Dated at
                  Hampslap the Tuesday in the feast of the Assumption B.V.M., <date>37 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 70</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard Veel of Hamslap grants to Simon Veel of the same place, his brother, and
                  Joane his wife, one curtilage and garden situate in Longestret in the same
                  village. [Mutilated.] Dated <date>6 Rich. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     71</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HOGSTON. William de Bermingham grants to Richard de Egebaston, son of sir Richard
                  de Egebaston, kt., one messuage in the village of Hoggeston which William Dragun
                  formerly held, and 6 acres of land in the fields of the same village, paying
                  annually for the same 35. of silver. Dated at Dorton the Monday next after the
                  feast of the Annunciation B.V.M., <date>3 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >MS. Ch. Bucks. 72</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="25"/> BUCKS. IVINGHOE, Priory of. Letter of Thomas a Becket, archbishop of
                  Canterbury, confirming to the religious of the wood of Ivinghou all their
                  possessions which they had by the gift of William, bishop of Winchester, and
                  confirmed by Henry his successor, as well as the gifts of Milo Neiremut and
                  William de Pichenestorre and all their other possessions, (<date when="1166"
                     precision="low">c. 1166</date>.) [Printed in the Monasticon, iv. p. 269.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 73-</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LOUGHTON (Great). William, son of John de Loughton, rector of the church of Great
                  Loughton, grants to Ivo de Loughton his brother, and Cecilia, daughter of Robert
                  de Stoke Hammond, the principal messuage, land, rents, etc., which he had by the
                  gift and concession of the said Ivo in the village and territory of Great
                  Loughton. Dated at Loughton the Tuesday next after the Purification of the B.V.M.,
                     <date>22 Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 74</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MISSENDEN (Great). Sentence in the ecclesiastical court for the validity of the
                  will of Edmund Hampden, esq., late of Great Missenden, and for the revocation of
                  letters of administration previously granted. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                  75</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NETHESCHEVIL. Agnes, relict of William le Frankeleyn of Netheschevil, quit-claims
                  to Adam the clerk, son of William Tork of Muresley, all her right in 2 roods of
                  land lying in the fields of Netheschevil, in a certain culture called Mereforlong.
                  Dated at Netheschevil the Sunday next before the feast of St. Lawrence, <date>21
                     Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 76</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NEWPORT PAGNELL. Robert le Somme demises to Simon de in Newport Pagnel, Matilda
                  his wife, and a messuage with a curtilage adjacent in Newport Pagnel. [Mutilated.]
                  Dated there the Monday in the feast of St. Barnabas, 2 <date>1 Ed. III</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 75*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> QUAINTCXN". Jordan, brother of the house of St. John of Aylesbury, and the
                  brethren and sisters of the same place, acknowledge to have received half a
                  virgate of land with a meadow in the fields of Quenton of William, son of Robert
                  Lambert of Aylesbury, paying annually to the said William and his heirs 75., with
                  a clause for payment of a relief on the death of the principal brother of the
                  house for the same land. (<date when="1240" precision="low">c. 1240</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 62</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SATTNDERTON. Alice, relict of Richard le Chapman of Santerdon, widow, grants to
                  John her son her whole dowry in 2 crofts which were formerly Reginald le
                  Syvekere's in Santerdon. (c. 1280.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 77</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SIPPENHAM (Manor of). Indenture made n Nov., <date>21 Elizabeth</date>, <date
                     when="1579">1579</date>, between Henry, earl of Huntingdon, etc., of the one
                  part, and Wolstane Dixe, citizen and alderman of London, of the other part, that
                  in consideration of a sum of .1500 the said earl demises to the said Wolstane the
                  manor of Sippenham als. Sipnam for 200 years with power of redemption. Ch.'jS. <pb
                     n="26"/> BUCKS. STEWKLEY (Little). List of free tenants and natives of Little
                  Stewkley. Temp. Ed. I. Court of Ralph de Styvecle held there the Monday next
                  before the feast of St. Hillary, n Ed. III. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 80</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The will of Alice Depes, widow, of Little Stukeley. Dated <date when="1454"
                     >1454</date>. Proved 3rd September, 1454. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 81</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STOKE GOLDINGTON. Fragment of a charter relating to the grant of lands, etc., in
                  Stoke Goldington. Dated at Stoke Goldington the Monday in the feast of the An-
                  nunciation B.V.M. ... Ed. III. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 79</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TWYPOKD. Public instrument under the hands of John Lechamsted, clerk, notary
                  public, dated Feb. 13, <date when="1396">1396</date>, concerning an exchange
                  between John de Buckyngham, rector of Carleton near Buckingham, Line. dioc. (sic),
                  and master Richard Cloop, rector of Twyford near Buckingham. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 65</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> VACHE. Release given by Anthony Restwold de le Vache, co. Bucks., to Michael
                  Hawtry, gent., of all kinds of actions, suits, etc., from the beginning of the
                  world to the date of the present writing. Dated 2 1 May, 2 and 3 Philip and Mary.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 64</bibl> . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WADDESDON. Declaration of Robert Bennet, clerk, as to the holding the first
                  portion of the rectory of Waddesdon. Dated 22 Deer., <date when="1660"
                  >1660</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 83</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Presentation of Robert Bennet to the second portion of the rectory of Waddesdon
                  by Philip, lord Wharton, the patron. Dated 22 Feb., <date when="1660">1660</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 84</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WHADDON Manor als. Giffards. Deed reciting that Philip, lord Wharton, and Jane
                  his wife claim to them and their heirs the moiety of the manor of Whaddon als.
                  Giffards and ofEatori als. Watereaton, together with the moieties of other lands
                  in the county of Bucks., and praying that the same may be inrolled on record. As
                  witness their hands 28 Nov. <date when="1651">1651</date>. Inrolled in the Common
                  Pleas, Michaelmas term. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 82</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WLNCHENDON (Over). Presentation of Mr. Richard Bryan to the vicarage of Over
                  Winchendon, Bucks., by Philip, lord Wharton, etc., and lady Jane Wharton his wife.
                  Dated 2fth Sept., <date when="1654">1654</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     88</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WINSLOW. Memorandum from the Winslow court roll, <date>19 Hen. VI</date>. William
                  Thomelyn of Shepton surrenders certain land to the use of William Smyth and his
                  heirs. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 85</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Memorandum from the Winslow court roll, <date>19 Ed. IV</date>. Thomas Power
                  surrendered into the hands of the lord a toft with 2 acres of land to the use of
                  Walter Palmer and Elizabeth his wife. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 86</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Release from Richard Graunte of London, salter, to Walter Palmer of Winslow, co.
                  Bucks., chapman, of all kinds of actions from the beginning of the world to this
                  present date. Dated at London, 16 Oct., <date>8 Hen. VII</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 87</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WOBUBN. Indenture made 3 May, <date>37 Hen. VIII</date>, between <pb n="27"/>
                  BUCKS. Margaret Thomson of Hurste, co. Berks., widow, and Thomas Hyde of Hurste of
                  the one part, and Edmund Rydyng of Chalfont St. Giles of the other part, being a
                  lease of a field called ' Gaysefyld,' in the parish of Wooburn, for 21 years, at a
                  yearly rent of 85. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 89</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Joan Gaunt and Alice her sister, daughters of Thomas Gaunt of Wouborne,
                  quit-claim to John Edmound of Beknesfeld all their right in a croft called ' Beast
                  Norchardyn,' in the parish of Wouborne, together with a common lane leading from
                  Beknesfeld to Maydenheth. Dated at Beknesfeld, <date>13 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 90</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HADDENHAM. The account of Stephen, servant of the manor of Hadenham, from the
                  Thursday next after the feast of St. Dunstan, <date>27 Ed. I</date>, to the Sunday
                  on the morrow of St. Peter ad Vine, following. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Rolls. Bucks. 1</bibl></p></div>
            <div type="charter"><p> PITSTON.
                  View of frankpledge for the manor of Pytleyston, <date>9 Rich. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Rolls Bucks. 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ABBEY OF NOTTLEY. CAVERSHAM, Oxon. Indenture made 23 Dec., <date>27 Hen.
                     VIII</date>, between Richard Ridge, the abbot, and convent of Notteley on the
                  one part, and William Rolte, sergeant at arms, of the other, being a lease of the
                  church and parsonage of Caversham, co. Oxon, for 66 years, at an annual rent of 8.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 41</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHARDESLEY, Bucks. Indenture made 6 Oct., <date>27 Hen. VIII</date>, between
                  Richard Ridge, the abbot, and convent of Notley on the one part, and Rowlond
                  Lymell, clerk, of the other, being a covenant to serve the parish church of
                  Chardesley in Bucks., and administer the sacraments, in consideration of an
                  annuity of ,5 13s. ^d. } going out of the manor of Nether Winchenden, during his
                  life. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 40</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BURTON, Bucks. Indenture made 20 May, .... Hen. VIII, between Richard Ridge, the
                  abbot, and convent of Notteley of the one part, and Nycolas Bothom of Asshendon,
                  yeoman, of the other part, reciting a lease of the 3oth of Sept., 2 <date>1 Hen.
                     VIII</date>, of the rectory and parsonage of Durton, co. Bucks., to William
                  Scryvener, at a yearly rent of 14 13s. 4^., and transferring the same to Nycolas
                  Botham. [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 42</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MAYDEN BRADLEY, Wilts. Indenture made 6 Feb., <date>26 Hen. VIII</date>, by which
                  Richard Rydge, the abbot, and convent of Notteley lease to William Radisshe of
                  Maydenbradley, co. Wilts., and his two sons, the parsonage of Mayden Bradley, with
                  appurtenances and tithes, fruits, and offerings from the feast of St. John the
                  Baptist, for 4 1 years next ensuing, at an annual rent of 16. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 38</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SHYRITTGHAM, Worf. Indenture made 23 June, <date>30 Hen. VIII</date>, between
                  Richard Ridge, the abbot, and convent of Notteley of the one part, and Henry
                  Baldwyn of Crendon of the other part, reciting a lease dated 8 July, 2 <date>2
                     Hen. VIII</date>, of the rectory of Shyryngham, co. Norfolk, to William
                  Phillippys and Hugh Bethome for 40 years, at a rent of <pb n="28"/> 16 annually,
                  and granting the remainder of such lease to Henry Baldwyn upon the same
                  conditions. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 43</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STOKE LISLE, Oxon. Indenture made between John, the abbot, and convent of
                  Notteley of the one part, and Edward Lowe of Stokelyle of the other, being a lease
                  of the church of Stoke Lyle, co. Oxon, with appurtenances from the feast of the
                  Annunciation B.V.M. 1525, for 6 1 years, at an annual rent of 6 los. Dated at
                  Notteley, 6 March, <date>17 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     38*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SWELL (Nether), Glouc. Indenture made 1 1 Oct., <date>26 Hen. VIII</date>,
                  between Richard Ridge, the abbot, and convent of Notteley of the one part, and
                  William Scryvener als. William Harvy of Canons Assheby, co. Northampton, of the
                  other part, being a lease of the parsonage and rectory of Nether Swell for ...
                  years, at an annual rent of 6 1 35. 4^. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 39</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PRIORY OF RAVENSTONE. RAVENSTONE. John de Basingham, lord of Wahull, grants to
                  "William the clerk, for his homage and service, one messuage near the cemetery,
                  and three acres of land in Ravenston, paying annually for the same 3$. sterling,
                     (<date when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     1</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter of Henry, bishop of Lincoln, assenting to the foundation of the priory of
                  Ravenstone of the order of St. Augustine by King Henry III, for the souls of Peter
                  Chaceporck and Hugh de Vynon, his uncle, in Ravenstone, reserving the rights of
                  the see of Lincoln, and those of Ralph de Clifford then rector of the mother
                  church of Ravenstone. Dated at Bickeleswad, 4 Nones Nov., <date when="1255"
                     >1255</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Agnes, daughter of Walter the cook, grants to sir William, the prior of
                  Ravenstun, and his successors in frankalmoigne, i 1/2 acre of land lying in the
                  assart which was formerly Richard Tonge's, for ever, at an annual rent of 3 pence.
                  For this donation the said prior gave to her i6s. 8d. (<date when="1260"
                     precision="low">c. 1260</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Agnes, daughter of Walter the cook, grants to sir William, the prior of
                  Ravenston, and his successors, in frankalmoigne, i| acre of land, at an annual
                  rent of %d. For this donation the said prior gave her 245. 8d. (<date when="1260"
                     precision="low">c. 1260</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard Tonge of Ravenston grants to Walter the cook, for his homage and service,
                  and for 305. of silver, 2\ acres of land with a ditch and live hedge, at an annual
                  rent of ^d. (<date when="1260" precision="low">c. 1260</date>.) [Mutilated.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 5</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, son of Richard Tonge of Ravenston, grants to the church of St. Mary of
                  Ravenston and the canons there in frankalmoigne all his right in a ditch with a
                  live hedge which Walter the cook formerly bought of Richard his father, lying
                  between the assart of the said John on the one part, and the assart of the heirs
                  of the said Walter on the other, (<date when="1260" precision="low">c.
                  1260</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard de Clifford, rector of Ravenston, grants to William de <pb n="29"/>
                  BUCKS. Ravenston and Christiana his wife that messuage with appurtenances which
                  Edmund formerly held of the fee of the church of Ravenston. (<date when="1260"
                     precision="low">c. 1260</date>.) [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     6*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Elizabeth, daughter of William de Ravenston, grants to the prior and canons of
                  Ravenston all right and claim in 7 acres of land in Ravenston which were formerly
                  Walter and lye near the great park. (<date when="1270" precision="low">c.
                     1270</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Elizabeth, daughter of William de Ravenston, grants to the prior and canons of
                  St. Mary of Ravenston in frankalmoigne 7 acres of land in the fields of Ravenston
                  near the great park. (<date when="1270" precision="low">c. 1270</date> ) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Nicholas, son of Richard Thonge of Ravenston, quit-claims to the prior and canons
                  of Ravenston the whole of that tenement he held of them, namely, one messuage with
                  a croft adjoining in Ravenston, and the whole of the land which he has in the
                  assart called Thongestocking, also he gives to them various rents for lands held
                  of him in the same assart, (<date when="1270" precision="low">c. 1270</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Bateman (I) of Ravenston and Helen his wife grant to master John Kynebelle
                  of Filgrave the whole of their land which lies by divers parcels in a certain
                  place which is called Aylewardesriche le croft. Dated at the Wednesday next after
                  the feast of St. Gregory, <date>3 Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter by which .... of Ravenston grants to ... [Fragment.] Ch. ii. John Gyffe
                  of Ravenston grants to William de . . . one messuage in the village of Ravenston
                  with a curtilage and appurtenances, namely, that messuage which is situated
                  between a messuage of Thomas le Creton and the messuage formerly Philip de
                  Gahurst's. Dated at Ravenston. [Undated] (<date when="1280" precision="low">c.
                     1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Ravenston grants to Beatrice his daughter, for her homage and service,
                  the whole of that assart with hedges and ditches which he bought of Hugh, son of
                  the provost, paying annually for the same 2S. o\d. (<date when="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Convention (indented) between R. . . . the prior, and convent of Ravenston of the
                  one part, and Simon de Ravenston, chaplain, of the other part, by which the said
                  prior and convent demise to the said Simon . . . assart and appurtenances which
                  they had from Nicholas Tonge of Ravenston, in the meadow of Ravenston, which Hugh
                  Ode held ; to hold the same for 12 years from the feast of St. Clement, <date>9
                     Ed. I</date>, paying annually gs. for the same. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     14</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry de Castro of Raveneston demises to Hugh Ode of the same place and'Isabella
                  his wife lying a t Pertronwelle between the land of Henry Randolf and the land of
                  William Cok, to hold the same for their lives at an annual rent of 6s. 6d.
                  [Mutilated] Dated at Ravenston the Sunday next after the feast of St. Michael,
                     <date>19 Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 15.</bibl></p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Edith, daughter of William Aylward, quit-claims to the prior and <pb n="30"/>
                  convent of Ravenston 1/2 acre of land lying in a place which is called Dated at
                  Ravenston the Thursday next before the feast of St. Margaret the virgin, <date>25
                     Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 16.</bibl></p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letters patent of King Edward II, dated at Berwick-upon-Tweed, ist March, 4th of
                  his reign, being a licence of alienation to John de Ravenston to enable him to
                  grant to the prior and convent of Ravenston certain land in exchange for other
                  land in the same village. [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 17</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Amyoun and Agnes his wife grant to Roger, the prior, and convent of
                  Ravenston 2 acres and 3 roods of land with appurtenances in the territory of
                  Ravenston for ever. Dated at Ravenston, in the feast of St. Valentine the martyr,
                     <date>6 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 18</bibl> .</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letters patent of King Edward II, dated at Westminster, 27 March, 7th of his
                  reign, being a licence to assign to the prior and convent of Ravenston by Philip
                  Alfrich one messuage and 20 acres of land in Ravenston, in exchange for a messuage
                  and 20 acres of land in the same village. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 19</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letters patent of King Edward II, dated at Northampton, 4 July, [roth of his
                  reign], being a licence to Drogo de Bararityn that he may be able to assign to the
                  prior and convent of Ravenston twenty acres of brushwood with appurtenances in
                  Ravenston. [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 20</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Thomas de Lyford and Joane his wife grant to Philip Tone of Ravenston and Matilda
                  his wife, all their lands, tenements, &amp;c. which they have in Ravenston, to
                  hold the same to them and their heirs for ever. Dated at Ravenston <date>9 Ed.
                     II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 21</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Bull of pope John XXII, dated 14 Kl. Jan., 2nd year of his episcopate [<date
                     when="1318">1318</date>], confirming the gift of the church of Ravenstone with
                  certain other lands and possessions in the same place, by King Henry III, to the
                  prior and convent of Ravenston. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 22</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alice, relict of John de Ravenston, grants to Philip Tone of Ravenston and Alice
                  his wife 2 acres i \ rood of land in Ravenston for ever. Dated at Ravenston the
                  Wednesday next after the feast of St. Luke the evangelist, <date>14 Ed. II</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 23</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry de Warewik and Christiana his wife grant to Walter Wydmot of Ravenston and
                  Beatrice his wife and Joane their daughter, one rood of arable land in the field
                  of Ravenston for ever. Dated at Ravenston the Sunday next after the feast of St.
                  James the apostle, <date>18 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 24</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry de Warewyk in Ravenston and Christiana his wife grant to Ely de Weston in
                  Ravenston six acres of land in the fields there. Dated at Ravenston the Wednesday
                  next before the feast of St. Laurence the martyr, <date>18 Ed. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 25</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> <pb n="31"/> Henry de Mulsho of Ravenston grants to sir
                  Richard de Ravenston, chaplain, one acre and one rood of arable land and 2 roods
                  of meadow in the field of one acre of land in Scyttho near the land which William
                  Gyle holds of sir William de Mokelstone, kt. [Mutilated.'] Dated <date>4 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 26</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alice grants to sir Robert, the prior, and convent of Ravenston 3 1/2 acres of
                  land lying in the fields and meadows of to hold the same for the term of her life,
                  after her decease the said land to revert to Nicholas her husband, and after his
                  decease to remain to the said prior and convent for ever. [Mutilated.] Dated at
                  Ravenston the Thursday after the feast of St. Matthew the apostle, <date>7 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 27</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Joane Adecok, who was the wife of Roger Ingelberd of Northhampton, grants to John
                  le Masun of Ravenston, clerk, one acre of arable land .... "Weston at ' Le
                  Smalehegges,' near the land of the abbot of Lavenden. [Mutilated.] Dated at
                  Ravenston, All Saints, n Ed. III. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 28</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Joane Adecok, who was the wife of Roger Ingelberd of Northhampton, binds herself
                  in a bond to John le' Masun of Ravenston, clerk, to pay to him or his attorney in
                  the church of Ravenston 305. at the feast of Epiphany following. Dated at
                  Ravenston the Wednesday next after the feast of All Souls, i<date>1 Ed.
                  III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 29</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter by which of Ravenston grants to his messuage in Ravenston with the houses
                  built thereon, with a curtilage, garden [Mutilated] Dated at Ravenston the Sunday
                  in , <date>15 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 31</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry, son of William de Castro, grants to Hugh Ode of Ravenston one rood of
                  arable land lying at le Peretrewelle. Dated at Ravenston .... next after the
                  translation of St. Hugh the bishop, <date>15 Ed. III</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 32</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Pykenham appoints John Lacy and Walter Botayne, his attornies, to deliver
                  seisin to William Trussel, esq., of his manor of Ravenston with appurtenances,
                  according to the form and effect of a certain charter. Dated at London, 2 Feb., .
                  . Rich. II. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 35</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letters patent of King Richard II, dated at Westminster, 26 Feb., 2nd of his
                  reign, granting licence to the sub-prior and brethren of Ravenston to elect a
                  prior in room of Eustachius Bernard who had resigned. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     36</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The prior and convent of Ravenston, as appropriators of the church of Ravenston,
                  agree with William, the vicar, to augment the stipend .3 145. annually from 2
                  farms pertaining to the priory, viz. one in Stoke called ' Bery ferme,' and
                  another in Ravenston called ' Wotteny ferme.' Dated in the feast of the Invention
                  of the Cross, <date>5 Ed. IV</date>, 1465- <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 37-</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="32"/> BUCKS. STOKE GOLDINGTON. John Norman of Stoke Goldington grants to
                  sir William , clerk, half an acre of arable land lying in the north field of Stoke
                  aforesaid in a certain place called Bradeleye. [Mutilated.'] Dated after St.
                  Hilary the bishop, <date>18 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 33</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STOKE GOLDINGTON, IKLEE, PIDDINGTON, and WESTON. William de Haregrave of Stoke
                  Goldington, chaplain, grants to the prior of the church of Ravenston all his
                  tenements in the villages and fields of Stoke, Ikelee, Pyddington, and Weston,
                  which fall to him by heirship, with one messuage and thirty acres of land which he
                  had by the gift and feoffment of a certain Nich. the smith of Ravenston, &amp;c.
                  Dated at Stoke Goldington the Sunday in the vigil of the Assumption, <date>24 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 34</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WESTON. Richard de Haregrave of Stoke Goldington grants to John Lambard of
                  Weston, Joan his wife, and their heirs, i6s. 6d. rent from 6 acres of land and one
                  acre of meadow which the said John, and Joan, and their daughters hold in Weston
                  for their lives. [Mutilated.] Dated Ed. III. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 30</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PRIORY OF TICKFORD. ASTON, near Birmingham. Proceedings in a cause relating to
                  the chapel of Yerdele, against Simon and Henry, priests, and certain others of
                  Worcester and Coventry dioceses, on the relation of William, rector of the church
                  of Eston, by which it is decided that the chapel of Yerdele is appurtenant to the
                  mother church of Eston. Done at Langford, n July, <date when="1237">1237</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 45</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Fragments of charter reciting proceedings in a cause relating to the chapel of
                  Yerdele. (Proceedings as set out in document no. 45. q. v.) <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >MS. Ch. Bucks. 43 &amp; 44</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Giles de Erdinton grants to Thomas de la Hurne, for his homage and service, his
                  capital messuage in Eston near the church, and the whole meadow and moor in that
                  part called Stockedemedue with their appurtenances, and 24 acres of land in the
                  same village, for which the said Thprnas gave in exchange a tenement in the
                  village of Erdington and a rent of 2d. Excepting the moor under the mill of Wytton
                  which the said Thomas holds of Nicholas Saleman, paying annually to the said Giles
                  and his heirs 40$. sterling, (<date when="1270" precision="low">c. 1270</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 46</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard, son of Nicholas de Fonte, grants to William, son of Geoffrey Wodard, for
                  his service and 105., one half acre of arable land in the parish of Eston, namely,
                  that which he has in ' Wodeweyeforlonge ' and which Hugh de la Liche sometime
                  held, paying annually one clove at Easter for all services, (<date when="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 47</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Garys, the prior, and convent of Tykeford near Newport <pb n="33"/>
                  BUCKS. Paynel, have demised to Hugh de Hopewas, canon of Lichfield, and John de
                  Aston, chaplain, the church of Aston near Birmingham, and their parsonage of the
                  said church, with the tithes of corn of Aston, Wythton, Dodeton, Necheles, and
                  Erdington, for five years, paying annually 16 marks sterling. Dated at Tykeford
                  the Sunday on the feast of the Purification, <date>28 Ed. I</date>ll, <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 54</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, the prior, and the canons of Tykeford authorise Hugh de Hopewas, canon of
                  Lichfield, and John de Aston, to pay to the chapter of Lichfield 80 marks, owing
                  to the said chapter by the prior and canons, by name of a certain annual pension,
                  saving the allowance of 68s. as is expressed in an indenture. Dated at Tykeford
                  the Monday next after the feast of the Annunciation, <date when="1354"
                  >1354</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 53</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHICHELEY. John, the prior, and convent of Tykeford grant to Richard Smyth of
                  Chechele and Emma his wife a messuage and five acres of arable land in the village
                  and fields of Chechele. [Mutilated] Dated at Tykeford the Friday in Ed. III. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 52</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 26 July, <date>5 Hen. VIII</date>, between Thomas Broke, the
                  prior, and convent of Tickford, of the one part, and Richard Glover of Chich . . .
                  , being a lease of a messuage with appurtenances in to hold the same for 60 years
                  at an annual rent of 415. [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 60</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 5 Jan., n Hen. VIII, between Thomas Broke, the prior, and convent
                  of Tykford nye Newport Paynel of the one part, and Christopher Davese of
                  Battyllesdon, co. Beds., yeoman, of the other part, witnessetli that the said
                  prior and convent have received of the said Christopher .32, and have demised to
                  him all their tithe cornes in the parish of Checheley, excepting the tithe of the
                  manor of Thytcthorne, for 13 years ; paying for the 3 first years one peppercorn,
                  for the 4th year .8, and for the remainder 10 annually. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks.
                     57</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NEWPORT PAGNELL. Amice, formerly wife of Richard de Marisco of Newport, grants to
                  Thomas, son of Amice, of Newport, and Alice his wife, three acres of arable land
                  in the fields of Newport, paying annually for the same 50?. (<date when="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 48</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TICKFORD. John de Roden, in Newport Paynel, grants to John de Craule, jun., and
                  Agnes his wife, one half acre of land in the fields of Tykeford, upon a culture
                  called ' Vorul,' near the land of William de Emberton of the one part, and that of
                  John de Craule, sen., of the other. Dated at Newport Paynel the Tuesday next after
                  the feast of St. Peter ad Vincula, <date>17 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >MS. Ch. Bucks. 49</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, son of Peter Chapman, of Newport Paynel, grants to John de Crawel, jun.,
                  and Agnes his wife, one half acre of arable land in the field of Tykeford upon '
                  Le Dytchfurlong,' Dated at Tykeford, <date>18 Ed. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 50</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letters patent of King Richard II, dated at Westminster 1 2 Dec., 6th of his
                  reign ; being an exemplification of a bull of Pope Alexander IV, <pb n="34"/>
                  dated at Viterbo, 6 Ides Nov., 3rd year of his pontificate, and confirmed by King
                  Edward I, of exemption from episcopal jurisdiction of the priory of Tykeford, a
                  cell of the abbey of St. Martin at Tours. <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 58</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letter from Guy, abbot of the monastery of Marmonstier, Tours, appointing
                  Humphrey Lytelton, priest, late monk of St. Peter's, Westminster (on the
                  recommendation of John, abbot of Westminster), prior of the priory of Tickford, in
                  the room of William Pemberton, deceased. [Mutilated.] Dated (i39 2 )<bibl
                     type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 59</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Fragment concerning an ecclesiastical suit. (<date when="1440" precision="low">c.
                     1440</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 56</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> "WTLLEN. Citation from the dean of arches to John, vicar of fctoke, William
                  Wytheberd and Richard Grey, parishioners of Wylien, to appear before the said dean
                  or his commissary in the church of the B. V. M. of arches, London, the 3rd law day
                  after the feast of St. John ante porta Lateran, in an appeal on the part of the
                  prior and convent of Tickford, in a cause for providing the ornaments for the
                  altar of the church of Wylien. Dated 9 Kl. April, <date when="1353">1353</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks. 51</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
