<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="county">
            <head>DURHAM</head>
            
            <div type="charter">
               <p> E <pb n="50"/> . DUKHAM. EVENWOOD. John Haunsard, lord of Evenwood, eldest son of
                  Gilbert Haunsard, grants to Thomas Haunsard of Toftes and Joan his wife, the whole
                  of the land with messuages, &amp;c., which the aforesaid Gilbert his father had
                  granted to them for the term of their lives, paying annually three arrows for all
                  service. And they may grind the third part of the whole of their corn growing in
                  the aforesaid tenements in his mill of Evenwode. Also he grants pannage for 10
                  pigs in his woods of Evenwode. Dated the Monday on the feast of St. Peter 'in
                  cathedra,' <date when="1293">1293</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Durham Charters
                     1</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WOTTON, ESCOUMB, and STANHOPE. Anthony Becke, bishop of Durham, grants to "Walter
                  de Bermeton a toft and 127 acres of land of the waste in the fields of Wotton,
                  Escoumb, and Stanhope, to hold the same for an annual rent of 625. $d. (<date
                     when="1300" precision="low">c. 1300</date>.) [With seal.] <bibl
                        type="shelfmark">Ch. 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
           <div type="county">
            <head>GLOUCESTERSHIRE</head>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> . ALVRYNTON. William de ShareslmU and William de Gersyndon appoint John Lucy and
                  William Genet, their attorneys, to accept seisin in their name of all messuages,
                  lands, etc. which Robert Scovile held in Alvrynton. Dated at Alvrynton the
                  Saturday in the feast of the Nativity of St. John the Baptist, <date>37 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Gloucestershire Charters, i</bibl>,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ARLINGHAM. King Henry II grants in frankalmoigne to the church of St. Leonard of
                  Stanley, the church of Arlingham with all the tithes of the same village, and one
                  virgate of land at Maismore which Roger de Berchelaio gave to the said church in
                  frankalmoigne, Besides he granted to the same church 6os. per annum, namely,
                  Hardacr' de Berchelaio, which the same Roger gave them of his rents, as the
                  charter of Henry his grandfather witnesseth. At Dover, in transitu regis. (<date
                     when="1160" precision="low">c. 1160</date>.) . <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     20</bibl>. </p>
            </div>





            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="81"/> . BOTINTON. The will of sir John de Bures of Botinton, kt., dated the
                  Sunday next before the feast of St. Lucy the virgin, 1350. Probate dated 2 Jan.
                     <date when="1350">1350</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRISTOL (Bishop of). Letters patent of King Charles II, dated at Westminster,
                  36th of his reign, for the translation of John Lake, bishop of Sodor and Man, to
                  the bishoprick of Bristol. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> COBERLEY. Ordination made by William, bishop of Worcester, for settling the
                  controversy between the abbot and convent of St. Peter's, Gloucester, the prior
                  and monks of Stanley and William de Berkeley, concerning the right to the advowson
                  of the church of ' Cudberleia,' and a pension of 55. (<date when="1188"
                     precision="low">c. 1188</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 21</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Confirmation by Baldwin, archbishop of Canterbury, of the charter of William,
                  bishop of Worcester, for settling the controversy between the abbot and convent of
                  St. Peter's, Gloucester, the prior and convent of Stanley and William de Berkeley,
                  as to the right of the advowson of ' Cuthbertleia.' (<date when="1188"
                     precision="low">c. 1188</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 22</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Thomas, the abbot, and convent of St. Peter's, Gloucester, grant to Robert the
                  clerk, nephew of Peter de Lech, archdeacon of Worcester, the half of the tithes of
                  the lordship of William de Berkeley, in ' Cudberle,' which pertains to the church
                  of St. Leonard of Stanley. (<date when="1190" precision="low">c. 1190</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 23</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> COLESWORD. Writ of King Stephen to Roger, bishop of Salisbury, the sheriff of
                  Wilts, and others, granting to the monks of Gloucester a wood and 2 assarts with
                  fields adjacent in his manor of Celesword in frankalmoigne, in the same manner as
                  William his uncle, as is witnessed by the charter of King Henry. Dated, R.
                  chancellor, at Buref. (<date when="1135" precision="low">c. 1135</date>.) [With
                  seal broken.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 5</bibl> . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ED G WORTH. License of alienation granted to Jerome Jefieryes and Mary his wife,
                  to enable them to assign to William Jones alias Lewes a messuage, garden, 20 acres
                  of land, and 4 acres of wood, with appurtenances at Edgworth, co. Gloucester, held
                  of the King in capite. Dated at Westminster, 2 Dec., <date>14 Chas. I</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> EWELEGH. Final concord made at Canterbury on the morrow of the octave of SS.
                  Peter and Paul, <date>6 Hen. III</date>, by which Peter de Eulegh remits and
                  quit-claims to Henry, the abbot of Gloucester and his successors, all his right in
                  the advowson of the church of Ewelegh. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GLOUCESTER (St. Peter's abbey). Grant from King Stephen to the abbot and monks of
                  St. Peter's of freedom from toll throughout the kingdom. (<date when="1135"
                     precision="low">c. 1135</date>.) [With seal broken.] Dated at Gloucester. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The confirmation of Magna Carta by King Henry III [2nd of his reign] with the
                  seals of the legate and earl Marshall. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Confirmation by King Henry III of Magna Carta and the Carta de Foresta. Dated at
                  Westminster, 28 Jan., 2 1 st of his reign. [ With great seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 10</bibl>, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="82"/> GLOUCESTER. Confirmation of the Magna Carta and the Carta de Foresta
                  of King Henry III, by King Edward I. Dated at Lincoln, 14 Eeb., <date>29 Ed.
                     I</date>. [ With great seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 26</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Agreement between Gilbert, lord Talbot of Castell Godrich, of the one part, and
                  Walter, the abbot, and convent of St. Peter's, Gloucester, of the other, by which
                  the said Gilbert grants to the said abbot and convent the lasher-pool and fishery
                  of ' Fromelod ' and the soil adjacent called l Coliescroft.' Dated at London, 18
                  Feb., <date>9 Hen. IV</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 10*</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GLOUCESTER (City of). Indenture made 25 Feb., <date>21 Ed. IV</date>, by which
                  Thomas Saundres of Brystowe, gent., gives to Thomas Morgan and Thomas Kyngescote a
                  tenement in Smythestrete in the town of Gloucester. ' <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     11</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> . Arthur Cole, clerk, grants to an annual rent or annuity from a tenement in the
                  town of Gloucester for the term of his life. [Mutilated] Dated 20 August ....
                     <date>24 Hen. VII</date> (?). <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Grant of arms to the city of Gloucester by Christopher Barker, garter, <date>30
                     Hen. VIII</date>. [Original, with seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 13</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TEMPLE-GUYTING. Indenture by which sir William "Weston, kt., prior of the
                  hospital of St. John of Jerusalem, and the knights of the same, demise unto John
                  Stradford of their tithe of Temple Guyttyng for 40 years, at an annual rent of 20.
                  Dated 27 June, <date when="1533">1533</date>, 25 King Henry VIII. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 17</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> KINSTANLEY. Institution by Godfrey, bishop of Gloucester, of James Chadwicke,
                  clerk, M.A., to the rectory of Kinstanley. Dated at le Wyneard near the city of
                  Gloucester, 17 May, <date when="1630">1630</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     4*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LONGENEYE. Stephen, son and heir of Robert Agu of Longeneye, with the consent of
                  his father, acknowledges to have endowed Agnes, daughter of William Saundres of
                  Longeneye, his wife, at the church door of Longeneye, on Wednesday next after the
                  feast of St. Barnabas the apostle, <date>5 Ed. I</date>ll, being the day he
                  espoused her, with the third part of a messuage and one virgate of land in
                  Longeneye. [TFi^A seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 14</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PYRTON, AYLEBERTON, ST. BREOVALL'S, CLOWER-WALL, STAUNTON, HOUSOM, BYKNOR,
                  HUNTLEY, WHICCLEVE, BREME, and COLFORD. Henry Parcye of Colford, in performance of
                  an indenture bearing date 18 Oct., <date>30 Hen. VIII</date>, grants to William
                  Parcye his son and heir apparent all his messuages, lands, etc. in the above
                  places, and appoints Edmund Barowe his attorney to give seisin of the same. Dated
                  19 January, <date>30 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 15</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STANEDIS. Final concord made at Gloucester, <date>30 Hen. II</date>, 5 March, by
                  which Odierna, wife of William, son of William the provost, acknowledges the right
                  of the abbot and convent of Gloucester <pb n="83"/> GLOUCESTER. to 20 acres of
                  land in Stanedis. Tor this agreement the said abbot and convent granted to the
                  said Odierna and her heirs for ever, one half virgate of land in Stanedis which
                  William her husband held. Ok* STOW on the WOLD. Fine dated at "Westminster, Hilary
                  Term, 5 Geo. I, by which John Chamberlayne and Joan his wife quit-claim, etc. to
                  Anne Freeman, widow, their right in a messuage, garden, orchard, and land in the
                  parish of Stowe on the Wold, for which the said Anne paid to the said John and
                  Joan 200 sterling. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 24</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Duplicate of no. 24. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 25</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TAINTON (Great). Matilda, formerly wife of John Clerk of threat Teynton,
                  quit-claims to John Coli all right, etc. to lands and tenements in Great Teynton.
                  Dated at Kempeley the Sunday next before the feast of St. Mark, evangelist, 15 Ed.
                  III. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 16</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TEWKESBTTRY (Abbey B.V.M. at). Randle Finegal, for the health of his soul, and
                  his heir, Reginald Finegal, and of Margaret his wife, with the consent of the said
                  Reginald, grants to the church of the B.V.M. of Tewkesbury in frankalmoigne the
                  whole of that land which is called Neuland. (<date when="1200" precision="low">c.
                     1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 18</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John L .... of Tewkesbury grants to John Whythe of the same place a burgage which
                  he lately acquired by the feoffment of Agnes de Cryckelade in the village of
                  Tewkesbury. Dated at Tewkesbury the Thursday next after the feast of St. Michael
                  'in monte tumba,' <date>5 Rich. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 19</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>

         <div type="county">
            <head>HAMPSHIRE</head>

            <div type="charter">
               <p> . BASINGSTOKE. Mandate from King Charles I to John, lord Finch, keeper of the
                  great seal, to issue letters patent containing an Inspeximus of the grant of the
                  house of the brotherhood in Basingstoke, 3 and 4 Philip and Mary. Dated 30 May, 16
                  Chas. I. Hampshire Charters, 2. BEREFORD. John Stoford, son and heir of Joan
                  Prikemere, grants to William Peracourt the whole of a messuage in the village of
                  Bereford St. Martin's. Dated at Bereford aforesaid the Sunday on the feast of St.
                  Michael, <date>16 Rich. II</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ELNETHAM, HANTS., and LAURENCE LYDYRARD, and SHIPTON BEATICHAMP, co. SOMERS. Sir
                  William Hody, kt., and others, appoint Henry Rawe and others their attornies to
                  receive in their name of sir John Seymour of Wolfale, co. Wilts, kt., possession
                  of the manor of Elnetham in county of Southampton, and the manors of Laurence
                  Lydyrard and Shipton Beauchamp, co. Somerset. Dated 4 Nov., <date>20 Hen.
                     VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> G 2 <pb n="84"/> EXBURY, FAWLY, BWOKENHURST, etc. Final concord dated Michaelmas,
                  8 Q. Anne, by which John Gretnam and Joane his wife, Daniel Edwards and Elizabeth
                  his wife, and John Burton, acknowledge the right of Joseph Sheppard to a common of
                  pasture and a common of turbary in Exbury, Fawly, Bwokenhurst, and the New Forest,
                  for which he gave 60 sterling. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> FREMANTELL. Roll of expenses for the king's park of Fremantell, <date>4 Hen.
                     VII</date>. [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Mutilated roll indorsed, ' <date>18 Hen. VII</date>. Compotus Johannis "Waller
                  vicecomitis co. Southampton de diversis custibus et expensis, etc., pro parco de
                  Fremantell/ <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GUERNSEY (Island of). Letters patent of George, bishop of "Winton, confirming to
                  John Saumarez, clerk, dean of Guernsey, all the rights and ecclesiastical
                  jurisdiction belonging to his office as dean. Dated 14 July, <date when="1664"
                     >1664</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 14</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HANTS. Memorandum of the descent of the family of De Quincy, earls of Winchester,
                  from Robert, earl of Mellent, showing their right (inter alia) to the manor of
                  Buckeby, co. Northampton, (<date when="1440" precision="low">c. 1440</date>.) Ch.
                  i. Roll of accounts of "William Uvedale, sheriff of Southampton, <date>3 Hen.
                     VII</date>. [Mutilated.] Ch. n. LAURENCE WOOTTON. Admission by the
                  commissioners for approbation of public preachers of Mr. William Manning, clerk,
                  to the church of Laurence Wootton in the county of Southampton on the presentation
                  of William Withers, esq., the patron. Dated at Whitehall, 25 June, <date
                     when="1656">1656</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LEMYNGTON. A certificate of the appointment of Robard Osborne by George Kent,
                  mayor of New Lerayngton, and other burgesses, to collect and receive alms for the
                  building of a bridge at Bolder in the said parish. Dated there, 19 Feb., 16 Ed.
                  IV. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LINKENHOLT. Certificate of the institution of Richard Spicer, M.A., to the
                  rectory of Linkenholt, co. Southampton, by George, bishop of Winchester. Dated 4
                  May, <date when="1683">1683</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 16</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MOTLESTON. Indenture made 20 September, <date>10 Chas. I</date>, by which Robert
                  Dillington of Knighton in the Isle of Wight, baronet, grants to Barnabas Leigh of
                  Shortwell, Isle of Wight, esquire, the manors of Motleston and Knighton in the
                  parish of Newchurch, together with other lands for the term of 28 days. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STOKBRIDGE. William de Gamel of Stockbridge grants to William the miller and his
                  heirs three deals of meadow in the meadows of &lt; Benetleus ' p Bentley] which
                  Osbert Bust held of him. (<date notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low"
                     >c. 1230-40</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SWATHLYNG and HERTELE. Portion of a manor court roll for the manors of Swatlyne
                  and Hertele held the morrow of St. Nicholas, <date>10 Rich. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WOODHAY (East). Adam, bishop of Winchester, grants to <pb n="85"/> Walter Zele his chamberlain certain land in the parish of Wydehay. (<date
                     when="1340" precision="low">c. 1340</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     15</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ALVERSTOKE and GOSPORT. The account of John Browne, bailiff of Alverstoke, from
                  the loth to the nth of Charles I and the 3rd year of Walter Curie, bishop of
                  Winchester, and the account of James Bell, bailiff of Gosport, for the same year.
                  Hampshire Rolls, i. ASSHEMERSWORTH. The account of Arthur Wescote, farmer, and of
                  John Thurman, collector of the rents there, for one year to Michaelmas, <date>12
                     Elizabeth</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHILBOLTON. The bailiff's account for the manor of Chilbolton in the county of
                  Southampton for the year <date when="1365">1365</date> and the 4th of sir Hugh,
                  prior of Winchester. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MANYDOWNE MANOR. The account of Thomas Baff, farmer, and Eichard Jamblevey,
                  collector of the rents of the manor of Manydowne in <date when="1484">1484</date>,
                  and i5th year of Thomas Hunton, prior of Winchester. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     22</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WALTHAM (North). The accounts of the bailiffs of the bishops of Winchester for
                  the manor of North Waltham from <date>15 Hen. VI</date> to . . Eliz. (18 rolls),
                  viz. : (1) John Cole, <date when="1435">1435</date>-6. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (2) The same, <date when="1445">1445</date>-6. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (3) The same, <date when="1446">1446</date>-7. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (4) Geoffrey Baker, <date when="1468">1468</date>-9. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (5) Nicholas Lamvale, <date notBefore="1484">1484-5</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (6) The same, <date notBefore="1489">1489-90</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (7) The same, 1*490-1. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (8) The same, <date notBefore="1491">1491-2</date>. Rolls, n. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>(9) Duplicate, <date when="1491">1491</date>-2. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (10) The same, <date notBefore="1494"><date notBefore="1494"
                  >1494-5</date></date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (n) The same, <date notBefore="1495">1495-6</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     14</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (12) The same, <date notBefore="1496">1496-7</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 15</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (13) The same, <date notBefore="1498">1498-9</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 16</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (14) The same, <date notBefore="1501">1501-2</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 17</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (15) The same, <date notBefore="1519">1519-20</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 18</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (16) James Eumbold, <date notBefore="1570">1570-1</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 19</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (17) The same, <date notBefore="1573">1573-4</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 20</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> (18) James Yates (undated). <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 21</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WHITCHURCHE, EVYNGAR, and HUSSEBORNE. Portmote held at Whitchurch, <date
                     when="1391">1391</date>. Hundred court of Evingar held at Whitchurch same year.
                  Court held at Husseborne the Saturday 4 November, <date when="1391">1391</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 23</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="86"/> WHITCHURCH and EVYNGAR. View of frankpledge with portmote, held at
                  Whitchurch, 3 Nov. <date when="1496">1496</date>, and I 497- View of frankpledge
                  with hundred, held at Evyngar same day and year as Whitchurch. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 24</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="county">
            <head>HEREFORDSHIRE</head>


            <div type="charter">
               <p> . BILLINGHAM. Certificate by Eobert le Wright, justice of the peace for
                  Middlesex, of the marriage of sir John Scudamore, late of Billingham, co.
                  Hereford, bart., and the lady Margaret, daughter of sir George Crymes of Peckham,
                  co. Surrey, kt. Dated 24 July, <date when="1656">1656</date>. Herefordshire
                  Charters, 2. CLIFFORD (Priory of). Gilbert Hannyeys, the prior, and convent of
                  Clifford, grant to Howel ap . . . . a messuage and certain parcels of land under
                  le Harewode. (<date when="1420" precision="low">c. 1420</date>.) [Mutilated.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> DAGLINGWORTH. A convention between Bartholomew Erchumband of Cirencester and
                  Richard de Beenham concerning the dowry of Constance, wife of the said Richard, in
                  the village of Daglingworth. Dated <date>1 Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> EGLETON. Court roll held 14 May, <date>9 Henry VII</date>, before John Breynton,
                  seneschal. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HEREFORD. Licence from Thomas [Spofford], bishop of Hereford, to sir Walter
                  Devereux, kt., and Elizabeth his wife, for the celebration of mass in any place
                  within the diocese of Hereford, without prejudice to the mother churches, for
                  three years. Dated in the house of the rector of Ross, 15 April, <date when="1445"
                     >1445</date>. [With seal.] Ch. i.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard de Medymor, son of Walter de Medymor, quit-claims to the church of St.
                  Mary and St. Ethelbert, and the dean and chapter there, all right in the lands and
                  rents of four of his men, for which they gave the said Richard z\ marks of silver,
                     (<date when="1270" precision="low">c. 1270</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Extract from the book called ' Nomina Villarum ' in the exchequer concerning the
                  city of Hereford. (<date when="1500" precision="low">c. 1500</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The whole tax of the city of Hereford, amounting to 46 145. id. [On the reverse
                  is a vegetable prescription.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ' The canons' fee in Hereford by John Shepenhams dayes, being mere sessyd for
                  payment of parlament sylver.' (<date when="1560" precision="low">c. 1560</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 20 March, <date>4 Chas. I</date>, by which Francis Phillpotts of
                  the city of Hereford quit-claims to John Best, D.D., and Francis Kerry, D.D., his
                  right to certain houses in the city of Hereford. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     14</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 5 Feb., n James I, by which Robert, bishop of Hereford, leases to
                  Anne Doughtie and others the mansion, canon house in Hereford, to hold the same
                  during the life of the said parties at an annual rent of six shillings and
                  eightpence. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 15</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="87"/> HEREFORD. Receipts signed by Francis [Godwin], bishop of Hereford,
                  for various sums for the subsidy of i June, <date when="1631">1631</date>, from
                  the dean and chapter of Hereford, &amp;c. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 16</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Two receipts, dated 8 Oct., <date when="1641">1641</date>, signed by George Leak
                  for rent due to the king in Hereford. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 17</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> . Appointment of Francis Kerie, S.T.P., as proctor of Jonathan Browne, dean of
                  Hereford, for the admission of Henry Rogers, S.T.P., to the prebend of Pratum
                  major. Dated 24 Feb., <date when="1641">1641</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     18</bibl>, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letters patent of King Charles II, granting to George Benson', clerk, the office
                  of archdeacon of Hereford. Dated at Westminster, 19 July, <date>12 Chas.
                  II</date>. Ch, 19. LYDNEY. Bond given by Thomas Gethinge alias Marbull of
                  Hereford, yeoman, to the dean and chapter of Hereford, in a sum of 40 marks to
                  keep the condition of certain indentures concerning a lease of the parsonage of
                  Lydney. Dated 15 January, <date>38 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 1.5 January, <date>38 Hen. VIII</date>, by which the dean and
                  chapter of Hereford demise to Thomas Gethinge, otherwise Merbull, of Hereford,
                  their parsonage of Ledeney and chapel of St. Brevell, for 29 years, at an annual
                  rent of ,16 6s. Sd. Ch. n. Indenture made 18 Dec., <date>3 Elizabeth</date>, by
                  which the dean and chapter of Hereford, in consideration of the sum of 10, demise
                  unto Roger Brougham their parsonage of Lydney and the chapel of St. Brevell's for
                  60 years, paying annually Xi6 6s. Sd. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TADYNTOK". Mutilated roll of tenants of a manor commencing, ' E. Waltero Terwarth
                  Vica/rio de Tadynton qui tenet secundum cons' manerii per copiam Cur 1 unum Mes'
                  cum j Glaus' adjac nuper in tenur' Hugonis Taillor e. r. p. a. 1 <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 20</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WHOLHOPE. An exemplification of documents filed in the court of the marches of
                  Wales in a cause between Henry Lane of Wholhope, plaintiff, and sir Nicholas
                  Walwin, master of St. Ethelbert's almshousea, Hereford, defendant, concerning a
                  lease of lands in Buckenhill, delivered to Richard Cam upon his petition. Dated at
                  Gloucester, 5 August, 36 Q. Eliz. \_With seal^\ <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     22</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WILTON. Indenture made 18 Feb., <date>41 Elizabeth</date>, by which lord Grey of
                  Wilton demises to Charles Wake of London, a close called the ' ould orchard ' in
                  the lordship of Wilton, and six acres of land in Wilton field, six acres in
                  Peterslome field, and a cottage and garden at the Poole myll, &amp;c., for five
                  hundred years, at a yearly rent of a peppercorn. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     21</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WORCESTER. Stephen, called abbot of Dore, and the convent of the same, confirm to
                  Adam de Stratford, skinner, of Worcester, all their land in Worcester which was
                  Christiana Godefray's, at an annual rent to themselves of one pound of cummin, and
                  to the prior and convent of Worcester 6d. (<date when="1230" precision="low">c.
                     1230</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="88"/> HEREFORD. EGLETON, CLEHUNGRE, HAMME, and HARDEN. Court rolls of the
                  above manors (part of the possessions of the dean and chapter of Hereford) from
                  1274 to 1405. (35 rolls.) Herefordshire <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 1-34</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>HEREFORD (Bishoprick of). The accounts of all and singular the bailiffs, provosts,
                  and other ministers of the rt. rev. John, bishop of Hereford, from Michaelmas,
                     <date>37 Hen. VIII</date>, to the same feast, <date>38 Hen. VIII</date>. [Fine
                  roll of 21 membranes.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 35</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HEREFORD. An agreement between the dean and chapter of Hereford and the mayor and
                  citizens of Hereford, to show certain documents to substantiate the right of the
                  dean and chapter to jurisdiction within the city of Hereford, with the replies of
                  the mayor, &amp;c. to the documents produced. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     36</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> A paper roll (heading gone) of rents issuing out of various parishes in the city
                  of Hereford and elsewhere, belonging to the dean and chapter of Hereford. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 37</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Rental of the canons within the city of Hereford. (Temp. Hen. VII.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 38</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LEDBURY (Hospital of). The account of Francis Kerie, S.T.P., keeper of the
                  hospital of Ledbury, from Michaelmas, 1640, to 1641. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     39</bibl>. </p>
            </div>


         </div>

         <div type="county">
            <head>HERTFORDSHIRE</head>

            <div type="charter">
               <p> . BAYFORD. William Hykman alias Barbour of Hertford appoints Gilbert att Hill of
                  Bayford his attorney to give seisin to Henry Coke and Gilbert Foster of lands,
                  &amp;c. in Bayford. Dated the Sunday next after the feast of St. John the Baptist,
                     <date>4 Ed. IV</date>. Hertfordshire Charters, i. Thomas atte Wode, late of
                  Bayford, gentleman, quit-claims to Henry Coke of Bayford all his right to and in
                  certain lands in the county of Hertford which he, the said Thomas, lately had in
                  conjunction with others by the gift and concession of Philip Clement, late of
                  Bayford, deceased. Dated 24 Nov., <date>7 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Walter Hanham of Chesthunte grants to Agnes, formerly wife of Philip atte Hell of
                  Little Berkhampstead, and John their son of Beyford, all those lands, &amp;c.
                  which were Thomas atte Grene's in Beyford and elsewhere in the county of Hertford.
                  Dated at Beyford on the feast of All Saints, <date>7 Hen. VI</date>. [With seal]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 2*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter (indented), being the award of William Langford, Thomas Birch of
                  Hertford, William Clerke otherwise Sutton, and William Roe of Hoddisdon,
                  arbitrators chosen to settle a dispute between John Wightman of Hertford of one
                  part and Richard Hill of Hoddison of the other part, concerning the title and
                  right to certain land in Bayford. Dated 10 June, <date>3 Hen. VII</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sir William Say, kt., and John Foster, clerk, quit-claim to Robert <pb n="89"/>
                  HERTFORD. Wyghtman, son and heir of John Wightman of Bayford, all their right in
                  certain lands and tenements in Bayford, formerly Walter Hanham's, late of
                  Cheshunt. Dated 7 July, <date>21 Hen. VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Horrdwood, brother and heir of Benedict Horrdwood, grants to William Humfrey
                  of Bayford and others, a messuage and 14 acres of land in the village and fields
                  of Bayford. Dated at Bayford, i March, 1 <date>1 Hen. VIII</date>. , <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Benet and William Coke, at the instance of Agnes Umfrey, widow, Robert
                  Longe, and Robert Gaunt, executors of William Umfrey, deceased, demise to Timothy
                  Knyghton, Joan his wife, and John his son, a tenement of the said William Umfreys
                  in Bayford. Dated at Bayford, 23 Feb., <date>14 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BERKHAMPSTEAD. Convention (indented) made the Saturday next after the feast of
                  the Assumption of the B.V.M., <date>40 Hen. I</date>ll, by which Bernard
                  fitz-Ralph lets to farm to John, son of Adam Gossalmer, the whole of his capital
                  messuage, mill, &amp;c., which were Osbert le Ster's in Berchamstede, at an annual
                  rent of 285. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRODWATER and WICCHE (Hundreds of). Peter .... is bound to sir John Carbonel,
                  sheriff of Essex and Hertford, in a sum of for the custody of the hundreds of
                  Brodwater and "Wicche from Easter, <date>20 Ed. I</date>, to the feast of the
                  nativity of the B.V.M. [Illegible, with seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     7*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHESHUNT. Copy of the will of William Tutty of Cheshunt, co. Hertford, made 15
                  Feb., 17 Geo. II. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HERTFORDSHIRE. Receipt given by Toresmus le Pape, merchant of Florence, to John
                  Carbonel, sheriff of Hertfordshire, for 15 of silver from the lands and goods of
                  John de Balliol, in part payment of 8 1 13s. \d. Dated the Saturday next after the
                  octave of St. Michael, <date>20 Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 9</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Appointment of sir John Gore as deputy lieutenant of the county of Hertford, by
                  Lawrence, earl of Rochester, and lord lieutenant of the said county. Signed and
                  dated 5 January, <date when="1687">1687</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MYMS (North). Bond given by Philip Conyngesbye of Twigmore, co. Lincoln, to sir
                  Ralph Conyngesbye of North Myms, co. Hertford, kt., to secure payment of .40.
                  Dated 18 June, <date>8 Jas. I</date>. [With seals] Ch. n. ROYSTON (Priory of). An
                  acknowledgment that Richard Higham, prior of Royston, has received the sum of six
                  marks from John Chapman, his farmer in Coddenham, co. Suffolk. Dated 6 February,
                     <date>17 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SACOMBE. John de Holt and Alice his wife attorn and in their places appoint
                  Robert Bray to receive seisin of the manor of Savecomp, with the advowson of the
                  church, which were Elizabeth's, the wife of Roger de Elmerugge, in Staundon and
                  Epcoiup. Dated at Northampton the Monday next after the feast of the Annunciation
                  B. V. M.. <date>50 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="90"/> HERTFORD. Extract from the manor court roll of Savecomp held the
                  Tuesday next after St. Nicholas, bishop, <date>28 Hen. VI</date>. Agnes, late wife
                  of John Upherst, sen., and John his son surrender to the use of John Taylor and
                  Katherine his wife a tenement and land in Elmedell. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     14</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Memorandum that at a view of frankpledge for Sacombe, of Philip and Mary, held 22
                  April, 3 and 4 of their reign, by reason of the minority of William Plompton,
                  cousin and heir of Isabella Plompton, widow, cousin and heir of Ralph Babthorpe,
                  kt., Edward Snell surrenders into the lord's hands certain lands, to the use of
                  Elizabeth Snell and John Snell. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 15</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SAWBRIDG-EWORTH. "Will of John Enever of Sawbridgworth, co. Hertford, grocer,
                  dated 6 December, <date>28 Chas. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 16</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STICHEHACH. Margery, daughter of Ralph de Gavele, grants to William, son of Simon
                  de Thicheburst, for his homage and service, one virgate of land in the village of
                  Stichehach which is called Reinhulle ; paying annually to the cook of St. Alban's
                  ios., and to the said Margery and her heirs one pair of white gloves or one
                  halfpenny ; for this charter the said William gave 10 marks, (c. 1 2 30.) [ With
                  seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 16*</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STORTFORD. John and Edward Willay grant to Richard Bedewell of Stortford one acre
                  of land in Stortford. Dated 9 Dec., i and 2 Philip and Mary. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 17</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 2 June, <date>8 Hen. VIII</date>, by which Thomas Grace of
                  Stortford, tanner, sells to John Wylley, citizen and grocer of London, one croft
                  of land containing 8 acres, which will descend to the said Thomas after the death
                  of John Grace his father. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 17*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ST. ALBAN'S (Monastery of). A public instrument attested by John Vernon, notary
                  public, by which John Buckmaster, vicar of Shepale, belonging to an exempt
                  jurisdiction of the abbey of St. Alban's, resigns the said vicarage. Dated <date
                     when="1492">1492</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 18</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WARE. Indenture made 10 April, <date>16 Elizabeth</date>, by which the lady
                  Katherine, countess, and the now earl of Huntingdon, in consideration of the
                  receipt of 205., sell to Robert Maryott the park of "Ware in the county of Herts.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 19</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made between Katherine, countess of Huntingdon, late wife of Francis,
                  earl of Huntingdon, deceased, and Thomas Ffanshawe, esq., by which she the said
                  Katherine grants to the said Thomas the whole of the lordship and manor of Ware to
                  hold the same for ever at an annual rent of &lt;8o. Dated 21 June, 18 Q.
                  Elizabeth. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 20</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An exemplification at the request of sir George Hastings, kt., concerning the
                  manor of Ware, co. Hertford, being the depositions on <pb n="91"/> HERTFORD. the
                  behalf of the younger children of Katherine, countess of Huntingdon, against
                  Thomas Fanshawe. Dated, 18 April, <date>23 Elizabeth</date>. [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 21</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WESTON. John, duke of Norfolk, &amp;c., grants to John Mowbray, earl Warren and
                  Surrey, and Elizabeth his wife, daughter of John, earl of Shrewsbury, the manor of
                  Weston near Baldok in the county of Hertford, and all and singular those lands and
                  tenements, rents and services, in Chygwell and Gynge Margarete, in the county of
                  Essex, formerly belonging to Elizabeth his grandmother, deceased. Dated, 30 June,
                     <date>29 Hen. VI</date>. [/Signed.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 21*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WIDFORD. Walter Smyth, Thomas Bedell, and John Plomer, of Great Hadham, demise to
                  John Scot, rector of Widford, and others, all the lands, tenements, &amp;c., which
                  they had by the gift of William Okholt and John Mundes, lying in different parcels
                  in the fields of Wydeford. Dated at Wydeford the Thursday after the Epiphany,
                     <date>9 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 22</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Scot, rector of Wydeford, John Leventhorp, esq., and others grant to John
                  Elyot of Wydeford one toft and half an acre of land in Wydeford. Dated at
                  Wydeford, 10 January, <date>16 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     23</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Leventhorp, jun., and others demise to Robert atte Mille, jun., and others
                  all lands, &amp;c., which they had by the gift of Walter Smyth, Thomas Bedell, and
                  John Plomer, in Wydeford. Dated, 27 July, <date>25 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 24</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Porys of Wydford grants to Thomas Wheler and others certain lands, &amp;c.,
                  in Widford. Dated at Wydford, 9 October, <date>20 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 25</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, son and heir of John Eliott of Wydeford, husbandman, grants to Philip
                  Conwey and others all his lands and tenements in Wydeford. Dated at Wydford, 22
                  May, <date>i Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 26</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Mellys and Thomas Ellyott de Wydford, co. Hertford, demise and confirm to
                  Thomas Mellys and others all their lands lying in divers parcels in the village
                  and fields of Wydford. Dated at Wydford, 12 June, <date>29 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 27</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WINDERICHE. Indenture made 6 September, <date>4 Ed. VI</date>, by which Edmond
                  Foster, gent., in consideration of the receipt of 116, sells to Raynold Carte,
                  gent., all his term of years in the site and capitall mansion of Wynderiche
                  granted to him from the crown by letters patent bearing date 26 May, <date>3 Ed.
                     VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 28</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WELLING. Licence for solemnizing matrimony between Nicholas Bonfoy of Welling,
                  co. Herts., and Elizabeth Hale of Little Ayot, Herts., at the chapel of Gray's
                  Inn. Dated, 17 October, <date when="1701">1701</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     29</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="92"/> HERTFORD. HERTS. Exchequer Constat, being the account of sir John
                  Gore, ki, sheriff of the county of Hertford for the year <date when="1654"
                     >1654</date>. Hertfordshire Rolls, i. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>Roll, dated <date when="1663">1663</date>, containing a list of rectors, &amp;c.,
                  within the various deaneries of Hertfordshire who have not paid the tithes due to
                  the king. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SACOMBE. Copies of evidences delivered by William Plompton, esq., to sir Philip
                  Boteler, kt., after the sale of the manor of Sauccompe, co. Hertford. Dated <date
                     when="1513">1513</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TEMPLE-CHELSYN. View of frankpledge with court baron of sir Ralph Saddeleyr, kt.,
                  for the manor of Temple Chelsyn from 3 Dec., 3 Ed. YI, to 3 June, <date>6 Ed.
                     VI</date>. (6 membranes.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The same, from 21 June, <date>2 Elizabeth</date>, to 29 Nov., <date>7
                     Elizabeth</date>, (i membrane.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The same, held 19 June and 24 Sept., <date>8 Eliz.</date> (i membrane) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The same, from 20 April, <date>13 Eliz.</date>, to 8 June, <date>24 Eliz.</date>
                  (i membrane.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The same, for i April, <date>25 Eliz.</date> (i membrane.) <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> View of frankpledge with court baron of Henry Sadleir, esq., from i June,
                     <date>30 Eliz.</date>, to 28 Dec., <date>31 Eliz.</date> (i memtoane.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Court baron of sir Philip Boteler, kt., held 21 June, 37 Q. Eliz. View of
                  frankpledge with court baron, held 9 March, 38 Q. Eliz. (2 membranes.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> View of frankpledge and court baron of sir Philip Boteler, kt., held 9 March,
                     <date>41 Elizabeth</date>, (i membrane.) Rolls, n. Court baron of sir Philip
                  Boteler, kt., held 29 July, <date>42 Elizabeth</date>, (i membrane.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The same, from 3 April, <date>42 Eliz.</date>, to 9 April, <date>44 Eliz.</date>
                  (3 membranes.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The same, from 27 April, i Jas. I, to n April, <date>3 Jas. I</date>. (3
                  membranes.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 14</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> View of frankpledge with court baron of the lady Jane Botiler, widow, dated <date
                     when="1608">1608</date>. (i membrane.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 15</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The same for 16 Sept., n Jas. I. (i membrane.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     16</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The same for 22 Jan., <date>16 Jas. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     17</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Court baron of the lady Jane Boteler, widow, held n October, <date>19 Jas.
                     I</date>, and 5 July, <date>20 Jas. I</date>. (i membrane) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 18</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WATTON ATTE STONE. Rental of Philip Botiller, esq., there taken, 6 October,
                     <date>6 Hen. V</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 19</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>

         <div type="county">
            <head>HUNTINGDONSHIRE</head>

            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="93"/> . ALCMUNDEBURY. William, son of Robert the smith of Alcmundebyri,
                  grants to Robert, son of Ralph of Little Stivecle, 4 selions of land in the fields
                  of Alcmundebyri; for this grant the said William paid one mark sterling, (<date
                     when="1260" precision="low">c. 1260</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Huntingdonshire Charters, i</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WANBRYGGH (Forest of). The metes and bounds of the forest of Wanbryggh as set out
                  in an inquisition taken <date>28 Ed. I</date>. [Copy.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Commission from Thomas Bruce, earl of Ailesbury, &amp;c., lieutenant of the
                  county of Huntingdon, appointing Samuel Pepys, esq., a deputy lieutenant for the
                  above county. Dated 17 March, <date when="1685">1685</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HUNTINGDON. Licence of alienation from Oliver Williams alias Cromwell, kt.,
                  Elizabeth Williams alias Cromwell, widow of Oliver Williams alias Cromwell, esq.,
                  and Elizabeth his wife, to Richard Oakley, esq., and Richard Owen, gent., of a
                  capital messuage called 'le Augustyne ffryers' alias 'Austine ffryers/ within the
                  town of Huntingdon, with all messuages, houses, &amp;c., late in the occupation of
                  Elizabeth Williams alias Cromwell, widow. Dated at Westminster, 20 May, <date>7
                     Chas. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Citation from William, bishop of Lincoln, to the archdeacon of Huntingdon, to
                  appear with two proctors of his archdeaconry at a convocation of the province of
                  Canterbury in the church of St. Paul on Thursday, 8 July, <date when="1708"
                     >1708</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ST. NEOT'S. Simon Bret of St. Neot's grants to John Cros his cousin the whole of
                  that messuage which he had by the gift of Robert West in the village of St.
                  Neot's, excepting one chamber. Dated at St. Neot's the Thursday next after the
                  feast of St. Dunstan, 3 <date>7 Ed. III</date>. [ With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 6</bibl> . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Portion of the hundred roll for the county of Huntingdon, taken 6 (?) Ed. I.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Huntingdon Rolls, i</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>

         <div type="county">
            <head>KENT</head>


            <div type="charter">
               <p> BARHAM. Decision of Walter, archbishop of Canterbury, in a dispute between John
                  de Ros, rector of the church of Bisshoppesbourne and chapel of Bereham, and the
                  convent of St. Gregory, Canterbury, concerning the great and little tithes of the
                  demesne lands of Henry de Bereham, decreeing that the said John and his successors
                  should take all the said tithes, and pay annually to the said convent six marks.
                  Dated at Lambeth, 2 Ides Aug., <date when="1315">1315</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Kent Charters, 149</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BONTTON-MALHERBE. John Childeston of Bontton-Malherbe grants to Richard Tayllour
                  and his heirs of Lenham, a certain <pb n="94"/> KENT. annual rent of 6s. 8d. from
                  eight acres of land in the parish of Bontton-Malherbe. Dated there the Tuesday in
                  Whitsun week, <date>37 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 143</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BORDEN. William Wysinden and John atte Melle grant to Stephen Baker two pieces of
                  land, one called Knobhold, the other Broc, in the parish of Bodrisden. Dated at
                  Bodrisden the Saturday next after the feast of the Conversion of St. Paul, 40 Ed.
                  III. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 142</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRABORN. The will of John Ramsey, priest, vicar of Braborn. Dated 26 July,
                     <date>3 Hen. VIII</date>. Probate attached, dated 10 Aug., <date when="1512"
                     >1512</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 144</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRADSTEAD. Thomas Holeweye and John Benet, son of Thomas Benet of Snodeland,
                  grant to Thomas Geffrei of Bradestede one messuage called ' le Esthous ' with a
                  garden adjacent in the village of Bradestede. Dated at Snodeland the Tuesday next
                  after the feast of St. Michael, <date>41 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 145</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRIDGE. Grant of a pardon by King Charles the Second to Arnold Beames of Bridge
                  in the county of Kent. Dated 7 June, <date when="1660">1660</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 146</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BROMLEY. Andrew Shotte, late of Bromley, grants to Richard Violet one messuage
                  with houses, gardens, &amp;c. in the village of Bromley. Dated at Bromley 20
                  Sept., ist Ric. III. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 147</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sir Nicholas de Hondesaker, chaplain, grants to John Mol of Bromlegh and Isolda
                  his wife the whole of a messuage in Bromleg' for the term of their lives. Dated
                  the Monday next after the feast of the exaltation of the Cross, 35 Ed. HI. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 148</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CANTERBURY. Thomas Bac of St. Dunstan's near Canterbury grants to William Kyng of
                  Canterbury a tenement in the parish of St. Mary of Northgate, Canterbury. Dated
                  there the last day of Feb., <date>i Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     150</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Bourne of the parish of St. Mary's, Northgate, Canterbury, grants to John
                  Redy, clerk, and John Cheest of Canterbury, one tenement in the parish of St.
                  Mary's, Northgate. Dated at Canterbury, 27 Oct., <date>7 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 151</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Gervase Clifton, esq., grants to John Shotte, esq., and Roger Downe of Brabourne,
                  an aldermanry (' aldermanriam ') of H . . . . in Canterbury, with rents, view of
                  frankpledge, custom reliefs, &amp;c., together with the whole of a rent called '
                  Chicchesrente ' within the liberties of the city of Canterbury. Dated at
                  Canterbury 26 of May, <date>27 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     152</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Bond of 40 marks given by Richard Metford of Nonyngton to William Colman, for
                  securing possession of a tenement in the parish of St. Mary's, Northgate. Dated 3
                  June, <date>i Hen. VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 205</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Thomas Bowsar of the city of Canterbury, cook, grants to John <pb n="95"/> KENT.
                  Harryson of the same city, pewterer, a messuage and garden in the parish of St.
                  Mary's, Northgate, in the said city. Dated 2 May, <date>4 Ed. VI</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 153</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CANTERBURY (Friars minor of). Blank form for the admission of persons of the
                  third degree to the privileges of the order of St. Francis, written <date
                     when="1479">1479</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 153</bibl>*</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Bond given by Robert Frusdon of Canterbury, vintner, and "William Frusdon,
                  yeoman, to William Langley, esq. in 300 sterling, for merchandise bought of him
                  payable at Michaelmas following the date of this bond. Dated at Canterbury, n
                  Dec., <date>15 Ed. IV</date>. [3 seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 154</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard Metford of Nonyngton and Alice his wife quit-claim to William Colman,
                  master John Colman, and others, all their right in a tenement in the parish of St.
                  Mary of Northgate, Canterbury. Dated 3 Oct., <date>i Hen. VII</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 155</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CANTERBURY (Ch. Ch. priory). Indenture made 20 April, 1 <date>6 Hen. VIII</date>,
                  between Thomas, the prior, and the convent of Ch. Ch., Canterbury, of the one
                  part, and Edward Ryngeley of Knolton co. Kent, and Jane his wife, of the other
                  part, witnesseth that the said prior and convent demise to the said Edward and
                  Jane all houses, land, meadows, marshes, and pastures, of their manor of
                  Lyddecourte in Kent ; with certain reservations to hold the same for 2 1 years at
                  an annual rent of 36 13s. 4^., with clauses for re-entry in case of death, and
                  regulations as to the store conceded to them by the prior and convent for the
                  time. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 155*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHARRING, PETTE and WESTWELL. Hewe at Hatche, gent., grants to Laurence Caldocke
                  and others all his lands, &amp;c. in Charring, Pette and Westwell. Dated 22 May,
                     <date>8 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 158</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> List of lands of the manor of Petts out of which Hewe at Hatche hath sold a
                  yearly rent of 3 to Stephen Draver of Cranbroke, <date>8 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 157</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 22nd day of May, <date>8 Hen. VI</date>H, by which Hewe at Hatche
                  of Charyng co. Kent, gent., and others charge certain lands in the co. of Kent
                  with an annual payment of .3 to Stephen Draver of Cranbroke. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 159</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 8 March, <date>9 Henry VIII</date>, by which Hewe at Hatche of
                  Charryng, in consideration of the receipt of &lt;8o, sells to Stephen Draver of
                  Cranbroke one yearly rent of 4. issuing out of the manor called Pettesplace, and
                  six score acres of land in the parishes of Charryng, Pette and Westwell. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 160</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 1 5 March, 1 <date>6 Hen. VIII</date>, by which Stephen Draver of
                  Crainbrook sells to the lord archbishop of Canterbury all his messuages, lands and
                  tenements, called Pett or Pett-place, in the parishes of Charyng, Pett and
                  Westwell. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 161</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 2 March, <date>25 Hen. VIII</date>, by which John Lauraunce <pb
                     n="96"/> KENT. of Charryng, husbandman, sells to Thomas Cherrell, citizen and
                  haberdasher of London, two pieces of land in the parish of Charryng. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 162</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Decree of the privy counsell in a cause between John Harrys and Jone his wife as
                  in the righte of the said Jone, Thomasyn Fowler, Thomas Bateman and Alice his
                  wife, as in the right of the said Alice and Robert Savage and Jone his wife, as in
                  the right of the said Jone, Rauffe Lawreaunce and Richard Lawrence, cossyns and
                  next heyres to Richard Tubbe, parties complainants against William Johnson, party
                  defendant, concerning 2 messuages and lands in Charyng, Westwell, Little Chart,
                  Staweffeld and Pevyngton co. Kent. Dated Michaelmas, <date>36 Hen. VIII</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 162*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letters patent dated at Westminster 28 June, <date>4 James I</date>, granting to
                  Robert Hunnywood, esq. the whole of the wood, underwood and wood land called
                  Downewood, containing 95 acres lying within the manor of Charring, to hold the
                  same for 3 1 years, at an annual rent of 9 6s. [With the great seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 163</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHEPSTED. "Walter le Mareschal de Chepstede grants to Henry de Brentone a
                  messuage situated near the house of Henry Pikeruth in Chepstede. Dated at
                  Chivenigge the Saturday next before the feast of St. Martin, <date>27 Ed.
                  I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 163*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHIDDINGSTONE. Indenture made 5 March, <date>32 Charles II</date>, by which
                  Robert Streatfield, citizen and grocer of London, demises to Edward Medhurst of
                  Chiddingstone, Kent, yeoman, six pieces of land lying in Chiddingstone together
                  with other lands in the same parish for n years, at an annual payment of 21 IDS.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 164</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHILHAM. Robert Sandum of Chylham grants to Walter Culpepur of the parish of
                  Conch erst, and Thomas Amyte and Hamon his son of Dreklegh, and Geoffrey Baker of
                  Scheldwych, all his lands and tenements lying in the village of Chylham. Dated at
                  Chylham, 27 June, <date>21 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 165</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CHISTELET, HEBNE, and RECULVERS. John Lovell, clerk, and others grant a lease of
                  houses, lands, &amp;c., in the parishes of Chistelet, Herne and Reculvers for ten
                  years, to Robert Clifford, esq. after the death of his wife Joan, the said houses
                  &amp;c. being held by Robert and Joan during the life of Joan ; on condition of a
                  payment being made to John Hunt. Dated at Welle in the feast of St. George,
                     <date>6 Hen. V</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 166</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CINQUE PORTS (The). Inrollment of five writs relating to the liberties of the
                  Cinque Ports, &amp;c., <date>26 Ed. II</date> to <date>18 Ed. III</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 167</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Extract from the red book of the Exchequer of the services due to the crown from
                  the Cinque Ports and their members. [Mutilated.] Dated the octaves of St. Hilary,
                     <date>21 Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 168</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> DEPTPORD. Indenture dated 7 October, 8 Geo. II, by which Matthew Cunstable of
                  Woolwich, baker, leases to "William Williams of Deptford, pavier, a brick messuage
                  in Deptford for 7 years, at an annual rent of 8. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     169</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> EGEBTON. Robert Tournor of Whitstapull quit-claims to John Pyers of Egerton,
                  sen., all right of action, demand, &amp;c., against him to the date of this
                  charter. Dated 6 May, <date>6 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     170</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 10 July, <date>24 Hen. VIII</date>, by which John Carpinter of
                  Egerton sells to Stephen Draver a piece of land called the wood in the said parish
                  of Egerton. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 171</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ELHAM. An agreement reciting that whereas certain lands,-tenements, rents,
                  &amp;c., in Elham, were granted to Henry, formerly the abbot, and convent of St.
                  Radegund's, near Dover, by William, the prior, and convent of St. Andrew's,
                  Rochester, for an annual payment of 10 marks, this chirograph witnesses that, in
                  consequence of the said lands not being worth the said rent, the prior and convent
                  agree to fix the annual rent at 8 marks, 6s. 8d. for the future. Dated 4 August,
                     <date when="1293">1293</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     214</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> EBHETHE. Richard Bokeloud, citizen and fishmonger of London, and others, demise
                  to William Segood a certain tenement lately Robert Foulere's in Erhethe in the
                  parish of Lesnes. Dated at Erhethe, 6 June, <date>9 Hen. V</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 196</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> EWELL. Inventory of the goods and chattels of Allen Hoord, late of Ewell, gent.,
                  deceased, taken 6 May, <date when="1603">1603</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     172</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> FABLEIGH. John Cok, son and heir of Robert Cok, grants to Gybe and Joan his wife
                  of Farleigh a tenement in Farleigh and certain land. [Mutilated.] Dated at
                  Farleigh ... St. John ante port. Lat., <date>4 Hen. IV</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 173</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> FAVEBSHAM. Will of Elizabeth Culleu of Faversham, Kent, dated 3 October, <date
                     when="1692">1692</date>. Probate dated 18 October, <date when="1697"
                     >1697</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 174</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GODMEBSHAM. Robert Coleman of Saham antegawy, and Petronilla, daughter of Simon
                  le Riche, grant to John de Boketon one curtilage in the parish of Godmersham.
                  Dated at after the feast of St. Augustine, <date>10 Ed. I</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 176*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GODNESTON. The will of John Brooke, dated at Godneston in the feast of St.
                  Lawrence the martyr, 27 Hen. [VI.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 175</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GBETINEBSE. Fragment of a grant to William, son of Thomas de Faucham, of a
                  meadow, &amp;c., in Gretinerse [Greenhithe]. (<date when="1260" precision="low">c.
                     1260</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 177</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HADLOW. William atte Longesfrith grants to sir Henry de Shipton, clerk, a certain
                  field called Risse containing five acres of arable land lying in the parish of
                  Hadlo. Dated St. Martins day, <date>15 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     178</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HABBING and SELLING. William Billyngton grants to John Jernegan, Isabella his
                  wife, and others, the manors of Harry iig H <pb n="98"/> KENT. and Selling in
                  Kent, together with all other manors and lands in the same county. Dated 2 April,
                     <date>i Hen. VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 156</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Jernegan, esq., and Isabella his wife, demise to "William Billyngton their
                  manors of Harrenge and Sellynge in co. Kent. Dated at Harrenge, 26 March, i Hen.
                  VII. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 179</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HAB-TLIP. Ralph Canut grants to William Scurlag the land of Hertlacheope, paying
                  annually for the same 35. (<date when="1180" precision="low">c. 1180</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 180</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HOWMARSHE near ROCHESTER. Robert Freke, gent., John Walter, and Henry Goldefynche
                  alias Fynche, for certain considerations, quit-claim to Thomas Fane of Buston, co.
                  Kent, all right in a marsh, lands, tenements, &amp;c., in Howmarshe near
                  Rochester. Dated 12 October, 5 Q. Eliz. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 181</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert Freke, gent., and John Walker of London, sell to Richard Goldefynche alias
                  Fynche of Feversham and Robert Giles of the Middle Temple the whole of a marsh
                  called Howmarsh with all that belongs to it, situated and known as Howmarsh near
                  Rochester. Dated 15 February, 6 Q. Eliz. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 182</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ICKHAM and WICKHAM. Indenture made 12 July, <date>19 Elizabeth</date>, between
                  Richard Rogers, suffragan bishop of Dover, and executor of the last will of Edward
                  Isaak, late of Canterbury, esq., of the one part, and Henry Palmer of the said
                  city, John Jermy of Ipswich, and Thomas Apelton of Waldingfeld, of the other part,
                  witnesseth that a grant is made to the said second parties to this indenture of a
                  messuage or tenement with appurtenances in Ickham and Wickham, co. Kent, for ever.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 183</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> IVECHURCH. Robert Pondherst of Ivechurch grants to Thomas Hanyfeld 19$. of annual
                  rent in Ivechurch. Dated 20 January, <date>20 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 184</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, servant of Hugh of the manor, quit-claims to Geoffrey the mercer, six
                  acres of land which William his brother sold to him, which acres his father gave
                  to his said brother. For this concession the said Geoffrey gave 205. (<date
                     when="1230" precision="low">c. 1230</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     176</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard With, with the consent of Agnes his wife, grants to William, his son and
                  heir, free liberty to marry whenever it shall please him, and that he will not
                  sell or alienate his lands, &amp;c., unless under great necessity or with the
                  consent of the said William during the term of his life. [0.<date when="1270"
                     >1270</date>-80.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 185</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Fragment of a grant by which Richard Curtone grants to .... Beatrice his wife,
                  Francis and Roger their sons, lying in the parish of Dated <date>26 Ed. I</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 186</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Receipt given by Henry, duke, marquis, and earl of Kent, to Peter Burrell,
                  sheriff of Kent, for the sum of 20 due to the said Henry, for the honor of Kent,
                  granted by King Edward IV, by letters patent bearing date 29 May, 5th of his
                  reign, to Edward, earl of Kent, and his heirs male lawfully begotten. Dated
                  Michaelmas, 9 Geo. I. [ With autograph signature.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     187</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> KINGESDON. Michael, son of Arnulf de Kingesdon, grants to <pb n="99"/> KENT.
                  Ralph de Chimbeham a rent of 2i\d. which John Joseph was accustomed annually to
                  pay to him for land which lies between the field called Northfeld and the land of
                  William Clodham's ; also $d. annual rent in the same village which William, son of
                  Felicia de Brankeshecche, paid at an annual rent of one halfpenny for all services
                  and demands. For this grant the said Ralph gave i6s. sterling, (<date when="1210"
                     precision="low">c. 1210</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 188</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LAMBERHURST. Agnes Toly, late wife of William Toly, grants to William Wyse and
                  William H . . . . one tenement, two crofts, and one rood of land in the parish of
                  Lamberhurst. Dated at Lamberhurst, 16 June, <date>1 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 189</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LEDES (Priory of). Adam Yvori and Richard, son of Richard Trochor, grant to the
                  church of St. Mary and St. Nicholas of Ledes in frankalmoigne certain land at an
                  annual rent of one penny, (<date when="1280" precision="low">c. 1280</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 190</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LEIGH. Indenture made 30 April, <date>17 Hen. VIII</date>, being the marriage
                  settlement agreed upon by Humfrey Lewkenore of Legh, esq., father of Robert
                  Lewkenor, and Edmund Thwaytts of Ostynghanger, executor of the will of sir Edward
                  Ponyngs, kt., upon the marriage of the said Robert and Mary, daughter of sir
                  Edward. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 191</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LENHAM. Indenture made 1 6 October, 1 <date>7 Hen. VIII</date>, by which Markys
                  Downe of Lenham, husbandman, in consideration of the receipt of 16 35. 4^., sells
                  to Edward Wotton of Bocton Malherbe, esq., all his part of howsys, lands, &amp;c.,
                  called Downe court, in the parish of Lenham. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  192</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LESNES (Abbey of). William, the abbot, and convent of B.V.M. and St. Thomas of
                  Lesnes grant to John, bishop of Rochester, and others, a certain annual rent of
                  zoos., payable during the natural life of Henry Blakemore, late abbot of Lesnes.
                  Dated 9 March, <date when="1516">1516</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     200</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LIFDEN, WOTTON, ALKEHAM, SWENEFELD, and ROME'JST. James Frogenale, John Coumbe,
                  and Thomas Everyng quit-claim to William Lotrich the whole of their right to
                  certain lands in Lifden, Wotton, Alkeham, Swenefeld, and Romen, within the
                  liberties of the five ports. Dated at Swanton the Sunday next after the feast of
                  the Nativity B.V.M., <date>50 Ed. III</date>. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 201</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LODENHAM, OWRE, and SENSHAM. Indenture by which the abbot and convent of Lesnes
                  demise to sir John Norton, kt., 83 acres of marsh ground in the parishes of
                  Lodenham, Owre, and Sensham, co. Kent, paying yearly five marks. Dated 31 Jan.,
                     <date>12 Hen. VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 199</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MALLING (East). Robert French of West Mallyng grants to Simon Cheyrie of the same
                  the whole of a piece of land in East Mailing. Dated at West Mallyng the Sunday
                  next on the feast of St. Matthew the apostle, <date>4 Ric. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 202</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> H 2 <pb n="100"/> KENT. MARGATE. Bond to secure payment of zoos, given by Edward
                  Catelote of Margate to Thomas and John ate Stone of Westebroke. Dated 5 March, i
                  Hen. [VI q. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 203</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NONNINGTON and KATYNGTON. Christiana Masoun of "Waldwareshare grants to William
                  de Langele half an acre of land in the parishes of Nonynton and Katynton. Dated at
                  Knolton the Saturday next after the feast of St. Matthew, <date>26 Ed. III</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 204</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NORTHFLEET. Final concord, made at Westminster, <date>26 Eliz.</date>, before
                  Thomas Meade and others by which William Browne and Katherine his wife acknowledge
                  the right of Robert Childe to a messuage, garden, and 15 acres of land in
                  Northflete, for which the said Robert gave to the said William and Katherine 130
                  marks of silver. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 207</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> 3STORTHWAYE. Receipt given by Lambart Cooke of North way e, esq., for 50 to John
                  Wentworth of Somerleton, esq., his father-in-law. Dated 25 July, . . . James I.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 206</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> OSPRINGE. Indenture made 20 Feb., <date when="1650">1650</date>, by which sir
                  John Wollaston, knight, and others, commissioners for abolishing deans and
                  chapters &amp;c., bargain and sell to David Judd of London, gentleman, in
                  consideration of the receipt of .266 us., a barn and land in Ospringe co. Kent,
                  part of the lands of the cathedral church of Rochester. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     209</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PECKHAM (East). William Erkebould grants to Christian Renekyn two pieces of land
                  lying in East Peckham. Dated at East Peckham the Sunday next before the feast of
                  St. Michael, <date>19 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 210</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard Foxtone grants to Richard Renekyn of East Peckham a piece of land called
                  Crouchefeld in East Peckham. Dated at East Peckham the Monday next before the
                  feast of the Annunciation, <date>43 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     211</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Geoffrey "Welde of East Peckham quit-claims to Richard Roytone and Anne his wife
                  all right in a certain piece of land called Westfeld in East Peckham. Dated at
                  East Peckham, i April, <date>5 Hen. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     212</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ST. RADEGUND'S (Priory of). Charter by which William Gernun, with the consent of
                  Grisilia his wife, grants to the church of St. Mary and St. Radegund's, in
                  frarikalmoigne, the rent and service of Gerard Kalkston of Rochester, (<date
                     when="1230" precision="low">c. 1230</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     213</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> RAMSEY (Abbot of). Fragment of an acquittance. Dated <date when="1384"
                     >1384</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 215</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ROCHESTER. John, son of Simon Potyn of Rochester, grants to John, the prior, and
                  convent of Rochester, 3^ days' work of his lanp in the suburb of Rochester, in a
                  certain lane called Craulane. Dated at Rochester, 20 Feb., <date>20 Ed.
                  III</date>. [ With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 215*</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="101"/> KENT. "William Poteman of Eastgate, skinner, grants to John, son of
                  Simon Potyn of Rochester, id. annual rent which he was accustomed to pay to him
                  for 3^ ' deywerks ' of land in the suburb of Rochester. Dated at Rochester, 6
                  Dec., <date>20 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 217</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ROMNEY MARSH. Indenture made 21 Sept., <date>12 Hen. VIII</date>, by which John
                  Honywode of Newenton, in consideration of the receipt of 19, sells to Thomas
                  Pulton of Bataile, Sussex, a parcel of laud in the parish of St. Mary church in
                  Romeney Mersshe. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 218</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SANDWICH. William Upton of Sandwich grants to John Palmer and John Fyneux of
                  Sandwich all lands, tenements, rents, &amp;c., which come to him by heirship in
                  the village of Sandwich, or elsewhere in the county of Kent. Dated at Sandwich, 20
                  April, <date>31 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 219</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SIBBTTBNE. William de Putindene grants to Syward de . . . . his field which is
                  called Stounerio (?) in Syburne, at an annual rent of 2s. for all service. For
                  this grant the said Syward paid two marks, (<date when="1200" precision="low">c.
                     1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 208</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SPELDHUBST. Fragment of a charter by which William, son of grants to which he has
                  in ' La Hope ' in the parish of Speldhurst. (<date when="1300" precision="low">c.
                     1300</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 220</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SPELDHUBST and HABWABTON. Indenture made Christmas Day, <date>10 Hen.
                  VIII</date>, by which Richard Roston., LL.D., master, and the brethren of Corpus
                  Christi College, nigh the parish of St. Lawrence Poultney, London, demise unto
                  William Waller of Brownebrigge co. Kent their manors of Spelhurst and Harwarton
                  for 20 years, at an annual rent of 565. Sd. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 221</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STOCTELE. Commission from Hamo, bishop of Rochester, to Hugh de Forsham and John
                  de Foderyngheye, rectors of the churches of Sunderesham near Chytyngston and of
                  Stone near Dartford, to determine the right to the tithe of a certain piece of
                  land held by John de Suthwik at Stoctele, claimed by the prior and convent of
                  Rochester as appropriators of the church of St. Margaret, Rochester, on the one
                  side, and by the prior and convent of Ledes as appropriators of the church of
                  Chatham on the other. Dated at Trottesclyne, 10 kl. Dec., <date when="1320"
                     >1320</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 216</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> THANET (Isle of). The will of Thomas Smyth Philpotts, of the parish of St. John,
                  in the Isle of Thanet. Dated 12 June, <date when="1472">1472</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 222</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The will of Thomas Smyth Philpotts of St. John's parish, Isle of Thanet. Made 12
                  June, <date when="1472">1472</date>. Probate granted 29 Oct., <date when="1472"
                     >1472</date>. (See 222.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 223</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> THOBNEY (Manor of). Court roll of the manor of Thorney held there the Saturday
                  next after the feast of St. Michael, <date>50 Ed. III</date>. Also for the
                  Saturday after the feast of St. Faith the Virgin, <date>1 Rich. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 194</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Court roll containing proceedings of courts for the manor of Thorney held <pb
                     n="102"/> KENT, (i) The Thursday after the feast of St. John ant. port, lat.,
                     <date>4 Hen. IV</date>. 2) The Saturday in Easter week, <date>5 Hen. IV</date>.
                  3) in Whitsun week, <date>2 Hen. IV</date>. 4) The Wednesday in the feast of St.
                  Anne, <date>3 Hen. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 195</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Court roll for the manor of Thorney, <date>3 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 197</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Court roll of the abbot of Lesnes for the manor of Thorney, held the Thursday
                  next before the feast of St. Michael the Archangel, <date>16 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 198</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> THROWLEYE. The will, with probate, of Robarte Kynge of Throwleye, Kent, dated 22
                  May, <date when="1559">1559</date>. Probate dated 16 Dec., <date when="1560"
                     >1560</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 224</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TRAPHAM. Bond for 2200 given by Margaret Harflete of Trapham in the parish of
                  Wingham, co. Kent, widow to sir Edward Mouins of Waldershare, baronet, to secure
                  the payment of .1166 according to certain indentures. Dated 4 Feb., <date
                     when="1663">1663</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 225</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TTPCHURCHE. Thomas Elmeston of Raynham, co Kent, quitclaims to Thomas Butt of
                  Raynham all right to a garden and nine pieces or parcels of land in Upchurche,
                  Kent. Dated 6 Oct., 12 Queen Elizabeth. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 226</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WOODCHURCH, BRENSETT, BILSINGTON, MER,SHAM, MIDLY JOY CHURCH, OLD ROMNEY, and NEW
                  ROMNEY. An exemplification of a fine made in the court of common pleas, dated upon
                  the day of the three weeks of St. Michael, in the year of our Lord, 1659, by which
                  George, lord Eure, Horatio Eure, Sampson Eure, gent., Ralph Eure, gent., William
                  Kayes, clerk, and Elizabeth his wife, and John Pickering and Deborah his wife,
                  acknowledge certain messuages, gardens, and lands in the above villages to be the
                  right of Charles Lambert, gent., and Joshua Pordage, gent. Dated at Westminster,
                  24 Oct., <date when="1659">1659</date>. [With seal.} <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     227</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WITTENASS. Richard Kenteis grants to William, son of Agnes, for his homage and
                  service, two virgates of land in Wittenass in fee and heirship, namely that which
                  Margaret and Baldwin held, paying annually for the same 205. (<date when="1180"
                     precision="low">c. 1180</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 228</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WOODHURST. Thomas Hobynden grants to John Payn of Frythynden and others, a
                  messuage and land called Rokelynge, in the parish of Woodhurst. Dated at
                  Woodhurst, 23 Jan., <date>31 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  229</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WORTH, ESTRE, and ADDESHAM. Richard Bonde, clerk, and Hugh Parkys demise to
                  Richard Shore and Beatrice his wife, Geoffrey Downes, esq. and others, the manor,
                  of Felderland and no acres of land and 4 acres of wood in Worth, Estre, and
                  Addesham. Dated at Worth, 20 Nov., <date>9 Hen. VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 230</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WORTH. John Swanne, son and heir of John Swanne late of <pb n="103"/> KENT.
                  Canterbury, acknowledges to have received of sir Thomas Lovell, kt., 100 marks in
                  full payment of certain lands, &amp;c., called Upton in the parish of Worth. Dated
                  20 March, <date>20 Hen. VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 231</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WYLINGTON. Robert Haukere, son of "William Haukere of Wylington, constitutes
                  John, rector of Button atte Hone, his attorney, to give seizin to the abbot and
                  convent of Lesnes of six acres of land in the village of Wylington. Dated 15
                  April, <date>23 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 193</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YALDING- and BRENCHESLEY. Deed by which sir Thomas Scott, kt., Charles Scott,
                  Henry Scott, George Scott, gentlemen, brothers of the said Thomas and Reginald
                  Scott, son and heir of Richard Scott, esq., deceased, remit and quit-claim to
                  Robert Byng, esq. for ever all their right, &amp;c. in all those lands and
                  tenements, and other hereditaments in Yalding and Brenchesley in the county of
                  Kent, which the said Robert Byng lately acquired, i.e. 14 Aug., <date>19
                     Elizabeth</date>, as parcel of the tenements, &amp;c. of Winifrid Raynesford,
                  deceased, together with other lands by divers instruments of the dates of 20 Feb.,
                     <date>19 Elizabeth</date>, and the 4th of Dec., <date>20 Elizabeth</date>, in
                  Brenchesley and Horsmonden. To hold the same to him and his heirs for ever. Dated
                  28 Aug., <date>20 Elizabeth</date>. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     232</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CANTERBURY (Priory of). Inrollment of 52 charters pertaining to the villages of
                  Middleton, Booking, Monks-Illegh, Hadley, Depeham, Clyve, St. Botulph's, Esshe and
                  Exeter, of lands &amp;c. belonging to the priory of Christ Church, Canterbury,
                     (<date when="1310" precision="low">c. 1310</date>.) Kent Rolls, i. (a) John de
                  Walflet grants to the church of St. Mary and to sir John, the prior, and convent
                  of Christ Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne, a rent of 35. which he was
                  acccustomed to receive by the name of one Sparrowhawk, and all right and claim
                  that he has or can have in homages and services, reliefs and heriots, and all
                  other appurtenances, namely of the fee which was Robert Poyntel's in the village
                  of Middleton. (6) John de Walflet quit-claims to sir John, the prior, and convent
                  of Christ Church, Canterbury, all his right in the above rent of 35., and services
                  of the fee of Robert Poyntel's in Middleton. For this grant the prior and convent
                  gave to him 6os. sterling by the hands of John de Hereford then keeper of the
                  manor of Middleton. (c) William, son of Hugh, grants to the church of St. Mary and
                  the monks there in frankalmoigne, 1 2d. rent in the village of Middleton, namely
                  that which Samuel ' de campo ' used to pay for two acres of land in the same
                  village. Besides he granted and quitclaimed to the monks the homage of the said
                  Samuel and any other homage or rent that should fall to him. (d) Gilbert, son of
                  Henry, acknowledges that seven acres of land in the village of Bockinges to be the
                  right of the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, namely that seven
                  acres which Baldwin de Bunetone held, which lie between the wood of the said prior
                  and convent called ' Le Ho ' and the wood of Richard de Boveton. <pb n="104"/>
                  KENT. (e) Sahir de Bredeford grants to the prior and convent of Christ Church,
                  Canterbury, in frankalmoigne, the homage and service of Roger, son of Robert de
                  Branketre, and nd. annual rent which the same Roger was accustomed to pay for the
                  messuage which Roger le Drapier holds of him, and from a field called '
                  Melnefelde.' (/) Sir John de Bockyng, kt., quit-claims all right which he has or
                  can have in a meadow called ' Hopimedewe ' in Booking, to the prior and convent of
                  Christ Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne. Dated in the month of September,
                     <date>46 Hen. III</date>. (g) Gilbert, son of Adam de Turry, grants to the
                  prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, the whole of his meadow which Adam
                  de Turry his father held of the feoffment of Matilda de Efford in the meadow of '
                  Oppymed.' To hold the same in frankalmoigne, paying to the heirs of the said
                  Matilda Sd. annually ; for this donation the prior and convent received the said
                  Gilbert into the benefits of Christ Church, Canterbury. (h) Nicholas ' de camera'
                  and Isabella his wife, formerly wife of Adam de Turri, quit-claim all right which
                  they have by name of dowry after the death of Adam her husband in the meadow of '
                  Opimed ' to the prior and convent of Holy Trinity, Canterbury, for ever. (i)
                  Roger, son of Robert de Brauketr', grants to the prior and convent of Christ
                  Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne, a rent of i $d. in the village of Bockyng,
                  viz. 8d. from Robert Wysman for a certain croft called ' Bredecrofte/ and &amp;d.
                  from Roger le Vinger for land he held of Godfrey le Dieter. (&amp;) Turgis de
                  Illeghe recites a grant from the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury,
                  for his homage and service, of one virgate of land which he bought from "Walter
                  the marshal in the village of Booking, and one half virgate and one half 'forland'
                  which he bought of William Ruffus in the same village, to hold the same at an
                  annual rent of 255. sterling. (1) Roger the Parker and Alina his wife grant and
                  quit-claim to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, all their right
                  in the whole of that land with appurtenances lying in the village of Bockyng which
                  is called ' Hole-eye,' between the land of the prior and convent on either side.
                  For this grant &amp;c., recorded in the court of the prior and convent of Bockyng,
                     <date>33 Hen. I</date>ll, they gave to Roger and Alina 505. sterling. (m)
                  Simon, son of Alina de Bounton, quit-claims to the prior and convent of Christ
                  Church, Canterbury, all his right in the whole of that land which lies in the
                  village of Bockynge, in the lordship of the prior and convent on either side, and
                  is called ' Holeghe/ which land Alina his mother gave to the said prior and
                  convent. Sealed <date>33 Hen. III</date>. (n) Roger the Parker by this charter
                  binds himself and his heirs to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury,
                  to warrant to <pb n="105"/> KENT. them the tenement which he holds by right of
                  heirship in Bockyng, viz. the whole of that land called ' Holeghe ' in the same
                  village. Sealed <date>33 Hen. III</date>. (o.) Amicia, formerly wife of Robert
                  Byenden, quit-claims to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, all
                  right in a certain meadow called ' Opimed,' in the village of Bockyng ; for this
                  quitclaim the prior and convent gave by the hands of William de Cerring, then
                  keeper of the manor of Bockynge, 95. sterling. Sealed <date>3 Ed. I</date>. (p)
                  Convention made on the morrow of the nativity of St. John the Baptist, <date
                     when="1277">1277</date>, between sir Thomas, the prior of Christ Church,
                  Canterbury, of the one part, and sir "William called Folyot, vicar of Bockynge, of
                  the other part, by which the prior grants one croft of the lordship of Bockyng
                  lying under the messuage of the said viear, as it is inclosed, for the term of his
                  life, at an annual rent of 2s. (q) Roger, son of Gunilda, confirms to Gilbert, son
                  of Henry, 25. of rent and two men in the month of August, and one penny towards an
                  aid of 205., as the charter which Adam his son made to the said Gilbert testifies.
                  (r) Adam, son of Roger, son of Gunilda, grants to Gilbert, son of Henry, and his
                  heirs, 2S. of rent which Henry, son of Walter de Bockyng, was accustomed to pay
                  for certain land which lies in a field called ' Legha/ between land of Roger, son
                  of Gunilda, and land of Reginald Heyward ; and also two men in the month of August
                  which the said Henry was accustomed to find to reap his corn for one day; and
                  towards an aid of 205., one penny, and if more, then more ; for this grant he gave
                  165. sterling. (s) Godfrey, son of Geoffrey de Meerseye, grants to Christ Church,
                  Canterbury, in frank almoigne, 140?. of annual rent from Edward the dyer for 5^
                  acres of land granted to him and his heirs at the above rent. (t) Convention made
                  between the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, of the one part and
                  Ivo de Mereseye of the other, by which the said prior and convent grant 3 acres of
                  land in Mereseye, which were formerly Mauwine de Mereseye's for the term of his
                  life, at an annual rent of 35. for all services. (u) Peter Bigge of Meldinges
                  quit-claims to sir John, the prior, and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, all
                  his right in 30 acres of land in the village of Yllegha; for this quit-claim the
                  prior and convent gave to him 3 marks sterling. (v) Thomas and William, sons of
                  Richard Sigar of Monks Illegh, grant to the prior and convent of Christ Church,
                  Canterbury, in frank-almoigne, the whole of their pasture in the common way
                  towards their manor of Illegh, and between a field of the prior and convent called
                  ' Binolde ' on the north, and an alder grove of the said prior called ' Schortfen
                  ' towards the south, and abuts in length upon the garden of William the priest
                  towards the west, and a pasture of sir Matthew de Meldinges towards the east. <pb
                     n="106"/> KENT. (w) Emma, formerly wife of Richard Sigar of Monks Illeghe,
                  quitclaims to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, all her right in
                  the pasture described as above (v). (x) Hugh, son of Ralph of Monks Illegh, grants
                  to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne, the
                  homage and service of Anselm Abot, ^d. annual rent which he was accustomed to pay
                  for 3 acres of land in Monks Illegh, in a field called ' Swdainesland/ the homage
                  and service of Adam, son of Hugh, 4$. of annual rent for a certain messuage held
                  in the same village between the king's way and the land of "Walter de la Mere, the
                  homage and service of Walter de la Mere, 5^. of annual rent for one acre of land
                  in the said village in a field called ' Havedland,' with all appurtenances. (y)
                  Anselm Abot and Agnes his wife of Monks Illegh grant to the prior and convent of
                  Christ Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne, the homage and service of Hubert
                  Montchensey, 6d. annual rent for 3 acres of land which he held in the village of
                  Monks Illegh, in a certain hamlet called ' Stacwode.' (z) Richard Dauney and
                  Claritia his wife of Monks Illegh grant to the church of Christ Church,
                  Canterbury, and the monks there, in frankalmoigne, all right, homage and service
                  which they have in iftd. annual rent which Richard de Lelleseye was accustomed to
                  pay to them for 3 roods of land, which Seman, son of Augustus, sometime held in
                  Monks Illegh. (aa) Nicholas de Lelleseye, son of Anselm de Lelleseye, quit-claims
                  to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, all his right in 2 1 acres
                  of wood in Monks Illegh, which lies in breadth alongside the wood of the said
                  prior and convent, called ' Manbey ' on the east, and the way which leads from
                  Meldinge towards Kerseye on the west, and abuts upon the land of sir Richard de
                  "Waterfeld, kt., which is called * Wodecroft ' on the north. For this quit-claim
                  the prior and convent gave by the hands of William de Cerring, then bailiff of the
                  manor of Illegh, IDS. sterling. Dated the Saturday after the feast of St. Faith
                  the virgin, <date>4 Ed. i</date>. (bb) Thomas de Lelleseye, son of Anselm de
                  Lelleseye, quit-claims to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, all
                  his right in the 2\ acres of wood described in (aa). Dated at the same time. (cc)
                  Henry de Lelleseye, son of Anselm de Lelleseye, quit-claims to the prior and
                  convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, all his right in the 2\ acres of wood
                  described in (aa). Dated at the same time. (dd) Robert Ster of Bradestrete and
                  Matilda his wife quit-claim to Christ Church, Canterbury, and the monks there, in
                  frankalmoigne, half an acre of land in Hadleghe in a field called ' Dalefeldes,'
                  between the demesne of the court of Hadleghe. (ee) Robert le Cornur and Alice his
                  wife quit-claim to Christ Church, <pb n="107"/> KENT. Canterbury, and the monks
                  there, in frankalmoigne, half an acre of land in Hadleghe in the field called '
                  Dalefeldes,' between the demesne of the court of Hadleghe. (ff) Katherine de
                  Audeham, formerly wife of Roger de Audeham, grants to the prior and convent of
                  Christ Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne, 3 acres of land in Hadleg' formerly
                  called ' le Stubbinge,' one head abutting upon the land of Ralph Eadrich, and
                  another upon her own land and the land of Matilda de Haudeham. (gg) Katherine,
                  formerly wife of Roger de Haudeham, in consideration of a loan of 40*. sterling
                  from Henry Sturdi, monk, of Christ Church, Canterbury, mortgages to him in the
                  name of his church 3 acres of land called ' le Stubbinge/ as above ; the said 405.
                  to be paid within 12 days of the feast day of the Nativity, <date>41 Hen.
                  I</date>ll, in default the said 3 acres to remain to the church in frank-almoigne.
                  (hh) John, son of Walter Eadrix of Hadlegh, grants to the prior and convent of
                  Christ Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne, one half acre of mowing land in the
                  village of Hadleg', in a meadow called ' Corsfordemed ' between the meadow of
                  "William de Gloucestr' and the bank running towards Prestesbregg, one head
                  abutting on the said bank and another on the wood of Humphrey de Denardeston. (ii)
                  Ralph, son of Richard the Marshal of Depeham, grants to the prior and convent of
                  Christ Church, Canterbury, his messuage with lands, rents, edifices and
                  appurtenances which he held of them in Depeham. (kk) Ralph, son of Richard the
                  Marshal of Depeham, quit-claims to the prior and convent of Christ Church,.
                  Canterbury, in frank-almoigne, his messuage, with rents, edifices and
                  appurtenances which he held in Depeham. (11} Basilia, daughter of Hugh Sturmi,
                  grants to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne,
                  one half acre of land in Depeham lying between the land of Richard del Hil towards
                  the west, and the land which was William A yl ward's towards the east, and abuts
                  upon the king's street towards the north, and the land of Stephen de la Grrene on
                  the south ; also one rood of land in ' Lefstanscroft/ lying between the land of
                  Richard del Hil towards the north, and the land which was William Aylward's
                  towards the south, and abuts upon the land of Reginald Crepyn's towards the east,
                  and the church way towards the west. (mm) Nigel Crunge of Depeham grants to the
                  prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, one acre of land which he held of
                  the fee of the church of Depeham lying in the field of Depeham in two places,
                  between the lands of Ralph Crunge and Adam de Westwelle. For this grant the prior
                  gave 125. of silver. (nn) Milo Elvine of Depeham grants to the prior and convent
                  of Christ Church, Canterbury, the whole of that piece of land which lies between
                  the land of Robert Chaun and the land which was Grifard Tholi's in the field of
                  Depeham. <pb n="108"/> KENT. (oo) Robert Scott of Depeham and Basil ia his wife
                  grant to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne, one
                  half acre and one rood of land in Depeham, described in (II). (pp) John, son of
                  Ralph Urry of Depeham, grants to the prior and convent of Christ Church,
                  Canterbury, in frankalmoigne, that mill which Ralph his father gave to him in the
                  tenement of Depeham, namely which is situated in ' Maydenho,' between the land of
                  Richard, son of Amicia, towards the west, and the land of David Ram towards the
                  east, and between the land of the said John towards the north and south. (qq)
                  Ralph Urry of Depeham confirms the above donation (pp). (rr) Ralph Urry of Depeham
                  undertakes not to sell or in any way appropriate the lands which William, son of
                  Urric le Breton, held of Henry de Eya by the service of 2s. in Depeham, unless
                  with the sanction of the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, who had
                  granted the same to him. (ss) William de Blomvile, son of Richard de Blomvile,
                  quit-claims to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, and their
                  successors, all right and claim in one acre of land in Depeham, which is called '
                  Schortacre,' lying between the land of Hamo the priest on the east, and the land
                  of William Boinbel on the west, and one head abuts upon the King's street which
                  leads towards Norwich on the south, which acre William de Blumvile, his
                  grandfather, formerly granted to the same church. (tt) Adam le Botiler quit-claims
                  to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, all his right by reason of
                  wardship in a meadow of the said monks in their manor of Clyve. (uu) Hugh Bardulf
                  grants to the church of St. Thomas and the monks there, 45. of annual rent which
                  Martin de Ho ought to pay in the feast of St. Thomas the apostle. (vv) Robert
                  Bardulf confirms the gift of Hugh his brother, of the annual rent of 45. from
                  Martin, son of Geoffrey Talebot of Ho, as above. (ww) William, son of Gilbert of
                  St. Botulph's, for the health of his soul and Cecilia his wife, grants to the
                  church of St. Thomas the martyr and the convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, in
                  frank-almoigne, one piece of land in the village of St. Botulph's on the east of
                  Barre-ditch near the land of Guy, son of Sigar. (xx) Guy de Esse, son of Walter de
                  Haffeld, grants to the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, in
                  frankalmoigne, for the souls of himself, his father, and Matilda his mother, one
                  acre of land in the village of Esse with the advowson of the church of Esse,
                  Norwich diocese, to hold the same for ever. Sealed on the morrow of the passion of
                  St. Thomas the martyr. (<date when="1259">1259</date>.) (yy) Henry, son of Henry
                  de la Pomeray, grants to the monks of Christ Church, Canterbury, in frankalmoigne,
                  an annual rent of <pb n="109"/> KENT. half a mark from a messuage which Richard
                  Bosketh and Beatrix his wife held in the city of Exeter at a rent of one mark.
                  (zz) Richard, son of Roger le Pruir of Monks Illegh, grants to the prior and
                  convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, an annual rent of one mark of silver in
                  frankalmoigne (for one pittance within the octave of the translation of St. Thomas
                  the martyr annually in their treasury at Canterbury for ever) from those who shall
                  hold the said lands after his decease, which lands were formerly William Pant's
                  and Henry his brother in the village of Monks Illegh. (aaa) John Pycot and Juliana
                  his wife bind themselves to pay to the prior and convent of Christ Church,
                  Canterbury, one mark of silver annual rent for one pittance within the octave of
                  the translation of St. Thomas the martyr in their treasury at Canterbury for ever,
                  for the lands and tenements which were formerly William Fant's and Hugh his
                  brother in the village of Monks Illegh. (bbb) Ralph Eadrich of Hadleghe grants to
                  the prior and convent of Christ Church, Canterbury, 7^ acres of his land which he
                  bought of Katherine, formerly wife of Roger de Haudeham, in the village of
                  Hadleghe, and which Augustus, son of the said Katherine, confirmed to him by his
                  charter, of which 2^ acres lie in 'Brunessclade/ near the land which was formerly
                  Seardus the provost of Haudeham, and 5 roods lie in the field called 'Eastfeld,'
                  and one head abuts upon the way called ' Melnestrete/ And 3^ acres lie in the same
                  field and abut on one side upon the land of Thomas de Muccesslo, and the other
                  upon a wood ; for this charter the prior and convent gave 8 marks of silver.
                  CINQUE PORTS (The). Commission for constituting a court of loadmanage within the
                  Cinque Ports. Temp. James II. [Not dated or signed.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> THORNEY LESONS, STIFF. Court rolls for the manor of Thorney Lesons from the
                  Wednesday next after the feast of St. James, apostle, <date>i Hen. VII</date>. to
                     <date>7 Hen. VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Customs of the manor of Thorney Lesons, co. Suffolk, &amp;c. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 4</bibl>. (a) Customs of the tenants of the manor,
                  whether free or native, concerning their tenures. (b) Anselm de Lucye grants to
                  the church of St. Thomas the martyr of Lesnes and the canons there, for the health
                  of his soul and for the souls of Richard de Luci his father and Richard Munfichet
                  his son, 405. of rent of his free marriage of Thorney. (c) Note of the
                  appropriation of the church of Rammesden Belhouse to the abbot and convent of
                  Lesnes. (d) Notes of annual rents in Clopton, 505. Pension of 265. 8$. from the
                  church of Rammesden Belhouse and 13s. ^d. from Steple Morden. {e) Walkeline de
                  Greinwyche grants to the abbot and convent of Lesnes one part of his land lying
                  between the church of St. Alphage, Greenwich, on the east, and one wall which
                  descends to the cemetery <pb n="110"/> in the way which extends to the Thames at
                  the gate of St. Alphage ; also one acre of land in Mulefelde between the land of
                  the prior of Southwarke and of Adam, son of Gunnora ; and 2 .... of land behind
                  the church of Greenwich.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WALLAND (Marsh of). The account of William Lambskyn of the expenditure for the
                  marsh of "Walland and other marshes adjacent, from the feast of the exaltation of
                  the Cross, <date>16 Ed. IV</date>, to Michaelmas, <date>17 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PRIORY OF TUNBRIDGE. BITTEBERGH. Richard and Edmund, sons of Eylnoth de
                  Bittebergh, grant to the prior and convent of Tunbridge all their right in certain
                  rents called ' Bullalosland,' and of a meadow called ' Standesmed ' in Bittebergh,
                  for which the said prior and convent gave 12 pence sterling, [Mutilated.] (<date
                     when="1280" precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     46</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Stonyna, daughter of William le Hoppere, grants to the prior and convent of
                  Tunbridge all her right and claim in all the lands, tenements, rents, and woods in
                  Dishfeld, which were formerly Bitteberghe. [Mutilated.] (<date when="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 69</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Kyngewode of Bytteberghe grants to John Edward of the same place and
                  Alice his wife one piece of land and a garden [Mutilated] Dated at Bytteberghe the
                  Sunday next after the feast of St. George, <date>13 Rich. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 126</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BODKESHAM. William le Mous of Swapham Bolebec grants to David, the prior, and
                  convent of Tunbridge for 20$. sterling in hand paid, one croft in Bodekesham ;
                  paying annually for the same 6d. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 24</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An indenture witnessing that the prior and convent of Tunbridge have demised to
                  John de Waldyngfeld and Isabella his daughter, for their lives, a certain tenement
                  at Bodekesham called ' Jeromes ' for 45. annual rent. Dated at Tunbridge, 3 April,
                     <date>43 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 115</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An indenture witnessing that John, prior of Tunbridge, demises to John Vaus and
                  William his son, for their lives, a certain croft at Bodekesham called '
                  Alwardescroft ' containing three roods in Wyneyard for 2S. 6d. annual rent. Dated
                  at Tunbridge, <date>46 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 115*</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture witnessing that Robert, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge have
                  demised to Richard Skynhale of Bodekesham and Letitia his wife, for the term of
                  their lives, one messuage and one croft containing one acre near the vicarage of
                  Bodekesham, formerly held by Richard Gardiner at an annual rent of 75. Dated at
                  Tunbridge on the feast of Saint Michael, <date>7 Rich. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 122*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture witnessing that Robert, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge demise to
                  Richard Cagge and William his brother of <pb n="111"/>
                  Bodekesham, for sixty years, a messuage, house, and a croft containing one acre
                  near the vicarage of Bodekesham, which Richard Skynhale formerly held of them ;
                  paying annually for the same 3$. ^d. Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of St.
                  Michael, <date>10 Rich. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 123</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture by which Robert, prior of Tunbridge, demises to John Boghead (?) of
                  Bodkesham and others certain land in Bodkesham. [Mutilated.] Dated at Tonbridge,
                  Michaelmas day, <date>20 Rich. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 129</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BOKINGFOLD. Bartholomew Chanu, son of William Chanu, grants to the prior and
                  convent of Tunbridge in frankalmoigne an annual rent of one mark of silver, viz. \
                  mark from land of Bokingfold and \ mark from Bartholomew le Herre and his heirs,
                  which they owed to him for the field of Odo. (<date when="1210" precision="low">c.
                     1210</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRENCHLEY. Elicia, daughter of Godard de Brenchesle, grants to Robert, son of
                  John de la Londe, half an acre of her land in the underwood (' Brueria ') which
                  extends from the land of ' La Lande ' in the way leading from Angele towards the
                  church of Brenchesle ; paying annually for the same one penny. For this charter
                  the said Robert gave 6d. sterling, (<date when="1210" precision="low">c.
                     1210</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Ralph de Bubherst grants to Goditha his sister the whole of the land which
                  Richard Ster held of Reginald of the church, which lies between the land belonging
                  to the vicar of Brenchesle and the land of Richard the smith, son of Robert the
                  smith ; paying annually to the said Ralph and his heirs one halfpenny. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 19</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert ate Londe, son of John ate Londe, grants to the prior and canons of
                  Tunbridge the whole of his land called ' La Londe ' in the parish of Brenchesle,
                  with appurtenances, which extends from the land of Thomas the vicar of Brenchesle,
                  which is of the same fee as far as Sheiselle towards the west, and from the land
                  of Godwine Cunelard, which is of the same fee as far as Stokeselle towards the
                  north, except one acre enclosed. Also he conceded an annual rent of 3\d. Also 2
                  acres of land with appurtenances which he held of Hugh ate Cherche ; and one acre
                  which he held of Viel, paying annually one penny. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     26</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Peter Cook, son of Symon Cook, grants to the prior and convent of Tunbridge the
                  whole of the land called 'La Londe,' in the parish of Brenchesle, namely that
                  which Robert la Londe formerly held of him; paying annually for the same 27 pence.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 27</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Reginald, son of Geoffrey de la Londe, quit-claims to Robert de la Londe 42 acres
                  of land in Brenchesle, paying annually for the same 2d. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     28</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Peter de la Mare grants to the prior and convent of Tunbridge half a pound of
                  pepper which they were accustomed annually to pay for certain land which is called
                  ' La Bonde/ in the parish of Brenchesle, in frankalmoigne. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 60</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard R . . . . grants to the prior and convent of Tunbridge forty pence of
                  annual rents from the land of Bond in Branchesle; <pb n="112"/> KENT. paying
                  annually for the same five grains of pepper at the priory of Tunbridge. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 73</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Geffecok de Brenchisle grants to master Henry de Grofherst, clerk, one
                  piece of land called ' Marlefeld ' and five acres of wood called ' Estbrocks '
                  lying in the parish of Brenchisle. Dated at Horsinyndenn the Wednesday on the
                  morrow of St. Laurence, martyr, <date>18 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 97</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture dated 3 December, <date>3 Henry VIII</date>, between Richard the prior
                  and convent of Tunbridge of the one part, and "William Borowe and William Geffrey,
                  clerks, William Barentyne, Edward Ferrers, and others, of the other part,
                  witnesseth that the prior and convent demise to William Borowe and others their
                  rectory of Brenchesley in co. Kent, for 60 years; paying annually 4 marks
                  sterling. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 137</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> DENEB-DISTAN. Sir Richard Appelgor, kt., of Denardistune, grants to the prior and
                  convent of Tunbridge, in frankalmoigne, 4 acres of his land lying in the field of
                  Denardistune. (c. 1 240.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 17</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sir Richard de Appelgard, kt., grants to the priory of Tunbridge in frankalmoigne
                  five roods of arable land lying in the fields of Denardistone. [Mutilated] (<date
                     when="1240" precision="low">c. 1240</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     20</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard .... grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalene of Tunbridge .... land in
                  Denardestun and one acre of meadow .... in frankalmoigne. [Mutilated] (<date
                     when="1270" precision="low">c. 1270</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     42</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalene of Tunbridge seven roods of land in
                  Denardestun in frankalmoigne. [Mutilated] (<date when="1260" precision="low">c.
                     1260</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 51</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard .... grants to the priory of Tunbridge . . acres and one rood of land in
                  Deuardestun in frankalmoigne. (<date when="1300" precision="low">c. 1300</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 68</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Convention between Roger de Frendesbery, rector of Stradeselle, and John, the
                  prior, and convent of Tunbridge, by which the prior and convent lease to the said
                  Roger their chapel of Denardeston, with their manor, tithes, &amp;c., for 12
                  years, at an annual payment of &lt;io. Dated <date when="1334">1334</date>, St.
                  Peter ad vine. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 94</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture witnessing that the prior and convent of Tunbridge on Michaelmas day,
                  loth of Henry IV, demised to farm to sir Gilbert Mylde, priest, their chapel of
                  Denardestone with their manor there, for 20 years. (Contains a list of cattle,
                  ornaments, &amp;c., belonging to the manor and chapel.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     131</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture between Richard Thomlyn, prior, and the convent of Tunbridge of the one
                  part, and Henry Everard of Denarston, Suffolk, of the other part, witnesseth that
                  the prior and convent demise to the said Henry their parsonage of Denarston for 28
                  years at an annual rent of four pounds, payable in the church porch of Bodkesham,
                  co. Cambridge. Dated 18 May, <date>12 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     139</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge demise to William Homyngton of
                  Denarston and Joan his wife, for 24 years, one croft called ' Fychcroft,' paying
                  annually 43. Dated at Tunbridge, 6 Sept., .... <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     120</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="113"/> KENT. DENNEMANNESBROKE. Richard de Clare, earl of Hertford, grants
                  to the prior and canons of Tunbridge in frankalmoigne certain land called '
                  Dennemannesbroch/ together with the rents of 1 35., to find a light in the said
                  church ; also the service of John de Ymewrth, viz. 10 pounds of incense, payable
                  at the feast of St. Michael, to incense his body, &amp;c. (<date when="1200"
                     precision="low">c. 1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 22</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> DODINGEBERY. Richard de Clare, earl of Hertford, grants land in Dodingeberi to
                  [Nearly obliterated.] (<date when="1180" precision="low">c. 1180</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert de Grethle grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalen of Tunbridge the
                  whole of his laud of Dodingeberi with appurtenances, which donation was made in
                  the presence and with the consent of Richard de Clare, earl of Hertford, to the
                  said church, &amp;c., in frankalmoigne. (<date when="1200" precision="low">c.
                     1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> .... Roule and Jordan his brother grant to the prior and canons of [Tunbridge]
                  the whole of their land which lies at Dudingebir', paying annually for the same
                  6d. (<date when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) [Mutilated.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 53</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ESSEDENN (East). William Sc'ileg' (?) grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalen,
                  Tunbridge, and the canons there, three acres of land in Eastessedenn ; for this
                  charter of concession the said prior and canons gave gs. sterling, (<date
                     when="1210" precision="low">c. 1210</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     25</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Giles de Hesedenne grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalen of Tunbridge frd.
                  rent, and one hen, and a horse-shoe (' ferrum equinum '), which was annually paid
                  to him by William de Boghinghurst and his heirs from certain land which he holds
                  of him in H esedenne ; for which donation the paid prior and convent gave him 35.
                  sterling, (<date when="1250" precision="low">c. 1250</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 34</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HADLOW. Atius de Piruriht grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalen of Tunbridge
                  and the canons there, in frankalmoigne, the whole of his land of Hadlo which Hugh,
                  brother of master Robert de Kent, held of him at an annual rent of one mark,
                  saving the services due to his lord, R., earl of Clare, viz. the tenth part of one
                  knight's fee. (c. 1 1 80.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HAISDEN and WICHERST. Henry, Gilbert, and Peter, sons of Clement, son of Martin,
                  grant to the prior and canons of Tunbridge, in frankalmoigne, one annual rent of
                  6d. from certain land in Haisden, and another of one penny from land in Wicherst.
                     (<date when="1230" precision="low">c. 1230</date>.) See Wicherst. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 30</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LANGPORT. Richard, son of Richard le Mus of Tunbridge, grants to the church of
                  St. Mary Magdalen of Tunbridge in frankalmoigne id. for ' forgabul ' which Joan de
                  Oxsted was accustomed to bring to him annually. Besides he remitted to the prior
                  and canons %d. of annual rent which they were accustomed to bring to him for a
                  curtilage in Langport called ' Pauecokkeshagh.' (<date when="1270" precision="low"
                     >c. 1270</date>.) [Mutilated.'] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 62</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, son of John ate Bourne of Tunbridge, quit-claims to the prior and convent
                  of Tunbridge all his right in a messuage and garden in Langporte which came to him
                  after the death of Sibilla his mother. Dated at Tunbridge the day of the
                  Assumption of the Blessed Virgin, <date>18 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 89</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> i <pb n="114"/> KENT. LEIGH. William, son of .... grants to the prior and convent
                  of Tunbridge .... annually received from William Pultebeam from land in the parish
                  of Lega. (<date when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) [Mutilated."] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 10</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of Reginald de Lega, grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge Sd.
                  of annual rents from the parish of Lega. (<date when="1230" precision="low">c.
                     1230</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 33</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Benedict Srobbe grants to the prior and canons of St. Mary Magdalen, Tunbridge,
                  in frankalmoigne, a certain part of his land and a messuage with a house thereon,
                  with a way belonging to the same, in the parish of Lega, of the fee of Eustace de
                  Wlkstede. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 35</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Benedict Srobbe grants to the prior and convent of Tunbridge his land in the
                  parish of Legh which is of the fee of Eustace de Walkestede. (<date when="1240"
                     precision="low">c. 1240</date>.) [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     36</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of Gilbert de Bugingherst, grants to the prior and canons of
                  Tunbridge the whole of his land at Bugingherst in the parish of Legh, to hold the
                  same in frankalmoigne. (<date when="1240" precision="low">c. 1240</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 43</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge a meadow in the parish of Leghe.
                     (<date when="1250" precision="low">c. 1250</date>.) [Mutilated.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 47</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> widow grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge all right and claim to lands,
                  tenements and rents in Witness Jordan, rector of Liga. (<date when="1250"
                     precision="low">c. 1250</date>.) [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     48</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> H son of Geoffrey de Putindenne, grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge 45.
                  6d. annual rent which he bought from John son of Gilbert de Curtone, payable at
                  the feast of St. Andrew, by the heirs of the said Geoffrey de Putindenne, for a
                  certain tenement which the said John held at Polle, in the parish of Lega. (<date
                     when="1260" precision="low">c. 1260</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     49-</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, son of Gilbert Brce of Hortune, in the parish of Ebesham, grants to the
                  prior and canons of Tunbridge lands in Edingherst, in the parish of Lega,
                  Rochester diocese, (<date when="1260" precision="low">c. 1260</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 56</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Benedict de Sroppeslond grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge for ever six
                  pence of annual rent, which Lucas called Heyward, and John de Cumbesell were
                  accustomed to pay for certain land held of him at Howeme in the parish of Legha.
                  Also he granted a certain wood [Brocum] with appurtenances, which he bought of
                  Eustace de Wulkestede in the parish of Legha, for ever, paying annually 3 grains
                  of pepper. (0,<date when="1240">1240</date>-50.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     61*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Proceedings in the court of the bishop of Rochester concerning the right to
                  present to the church of Leigh, to which Stephen de Pencestre, son of sir Laurence
                  de Cobeham, kt., had presented George Chanu ; decided in favour of John, the
                  prior, and canons of Tunbridge, who present Richard de Holdene, priest, to that
                  church, vacant by the death of Jordan de Sevenak late rector. Dated at Hallyng, 7
                  Id. Feb., <date when="1304">1304</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 79</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry de Schiptone, rector of Stradeselle, grants to sir Roger de Frendesbery,
                  rector of Leghe, two pieces of land lying in the parish of Leghe. Dated at
                  Tunbridge, 5 Aug., <date>15 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 96</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="115"/> KENT. Letter of Hamo, bishop of Rochester, to the archdeacon of
                  Rochester, dated <date when="1349">1349</date>, concerning the appropriation of
                  the church of Leghe to the prior and convent of Tunbridge. [Mutilated] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 100</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture witnessing that John Simon of Osprenge grants to the prior and convent
                  of Tunbridge two crofts of land which he acquired of sir Roger de Frendesbery in
                  the parish of Leghe for 30 years. Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of the
                  Purification, <date>23 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 103</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Simon of Osprenge grants to the prior and convent of Tunbridge and their
                  successors the whole of his right and claim in two crofts of land in the parish of
                  Leghe. Dated at Tunbridge, 3rd March, <date>23 Ed. III</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 105</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Simond of Osprenge grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge two crofts of
                  land which he acquired of sir Roger de Frendesbery in the parish of Leghe. Dated
                  at Tunbridge on the feast of St. Andrew the apostle, <date>28 Ed. III</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 113</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Appropriation of the church of Legh to the prior and convent of Tunbridge, by
                  John, bishop of Rochester, on account of the unfortunate burning down of their
                  buildings, &amp;c., together with the ordination of the vicarage. Dated at
                  Rochester, 25 Feb., <date when="1353">1353</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     123*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Grant by Robert, the prior of Tunbridge, to the perpetual vicar of the church of
                  Leghe, Rochester diocese, of a messuage and a certain piece of land for the use of
                  the vicar and his successors. Dated 20 Feb. <date when="1393">1393</date>,
                     <date>17 Ric. II</date>. [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 127</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MALLING ... Peltebem ... quit-claims to the prior and canons of Tunbridge, for
                  himself and heirs, their whole right in a tenement in the village of Mallinge,
                  Rochester diocese, (c. 1 2 20-30.) [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     37</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MEREDEN. William de Moriston of Mo ... ton grants to the church of St. Mary
                  Magdalen of Tunbridge, in frankalmoigne, a tenement in the parish of Mereden.
                     (<date when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) [Mutilated] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 14</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NORHERST. Convention between John, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge of the one
                  part, and Robert, William, and Laurence, sons of Laurence de la Holclene, of the
                  other part, viz. that the prior arid convent demise, during the lives of the said
                  Robert and others and one year beyond, 46 acres of land at Norherst lying near the
                  gate called ' Mesingeleghesgate/ for an annual rent of 8s. Sd. sterling. Dated at
                  Tunbridge on the vigil of St. Michael, <date>2 Ed. III</date>. Ch.yi. NORTHFELD.
                  Indenture witnessing that the prior and convent of Tunbridge have demised to
                  William Hervy, senior, and Thomas his son, of Bodesham, 6 acres of land in
                  Northfeld for 60 years, at an annual rent of 6s. Dated at Tunbridge on the morrow
                  of the feast of St. Michael, . . . Hen. VI. [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     135</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> I 2 <pb n="116"/> KENT. OXFORD. An indenture made the 2 yth of Nov., <date
                     when="1518">1518</date>, witnessing that John, the prior of Ellsyngspittel in
                  London, had received of Richard, the prior of Tunbridge, the sum of 18 in part
                  towards the building of St. Maries College in Oxford, according to the schedule
                  from my lord Cardinal. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 138</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SIBBURNE. Stephen fitz Richard fitz Simon of Sibburne grants to James de Vahad
                  the whole of his land in Sibburne, whether of the fee of sir Peter de Merwrthe or
                  of the fee of sir Richard de Vahad ; paying annually for the same 55. (<date
                     when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> . . . Pudindenn, widow, grants to the prior and convent of Tunbridge all her
                  right and claim which is in the parish of Siburne of the fee of Pudindenn, viz.
                  that which Alured her husband formerly held. Witness Richard Forestar, then
                  constable of Tun- bridge, (<date when="1230" precision="low">c. 1230</date>.)
                  [Mutilated^] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 31</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The prior and convent of Tunbridge have demised to John Colpeper and Geoffrey his
                  brother, sons of Walter Colpeper, a certain field in the parish of Schiborne
                  between ' Lakebreggesmed ' and the water running from the mill of Oxsnode towards
                  the mill of Horsgate called ( Baggemelle,' paying annually for the same %d. Dated
                  at Tunbridge on the feast of the nativity of John the Baptist, <date>27 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 112</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture dated 24th day of May, <date>16 Hen. VIII</date>, between Richard
                  Thomlyn, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge of the one part, and Thomas Cook of
                  the otlier, witnesseth that the prior and convent have sold to T. C. all their
                  wood and underwood lying and growyng in two parcels of land in Sheborn, called the
                  Hook and Capelbooth, for the sum of ,5 13s. ^d. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     140</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SNEYLESEL. Geoffrey de Appelgar grants to the church of Tunbridge, in
                  frankalmoigne, a piece of land in the field called 'Sneylesel.' (<date when="1230"
                     precision="low">c. 1230</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 32</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SPELDHURST. Sir Simon de Berhersse, knight, grants to the prior and canons of
                  Tunbridge in frankalmoigne the whole of his land in the parish of Speldhurst.
                     (<date when="1280" precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     59</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An inventory of goods, &amp;c. at the hall of Speldhurst. (<date when="1300"
                     precision="low">c. 1300</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 90</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STRADESELL. Richard, son of John Taillour of Stradesell, quit-claims to William,
                  son of John Mesyngleghe, Roger his brother, and Richard Goldbell of Tunbridge, all
                  right in lands, tenements, &amp;c., which William, son of John Nailere, by his
                  charter gave to the aforesaid William, Roger, and Richard. Dated at Tunbridge the
                  day of the exaltation of the Cross, <date>23 Ed. III</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 106</bibl></p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TUDELEY. The official of the bishop of Rochester admits Edmund de Osseham, clerk,
                  to the church of Teudele, vacant by the death of John Geldtwyne, on the
                  presentation of the prior and convent of Tunbridge. Dated at Mailing the Wednesday
                  next after the feast of St. Matthew, apostle, 125 . . <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     58</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="117"/> KENT. Walter de Chitelcrofte grants to the prior and convent of Tun-
                  bridge the whole of his meadow which he bought of Matthew de Creuquer at Wh ....
                  in the parish of Teudelee, paying for all services id. annually, &amp;c. (<date
                     notBefore="1260" notAfter="1270" precision="low">c. 1260-70</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 74</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Ecclesiastical proceedings between Laurence, bishop of Rochester, and Walter de
                  Bestan, clerk, on the one part, and David, the prior, and the convent of
                  Tunbridge, on the other, concerning the right of admission of the said Walter to
                  the church of Teudele. Dated at Bronil the Sunday .... St. Martin, <date
                     when="1273">1273</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 76</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TUNBRIDGE. G. de Cratona grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalen and the canons
                  of Tunbridge in frankalmoigne the whole of the land which Nicholas, son of
                  Fromunt, held of him near his house, together with the whole service which the
                  said Nicholas and his heirs ought to make to him for the said land, for the health
                  of his body and soul, and of his ancestors, (<date when="1135" precision="low">c.
                     1135</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 1</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Ralph, son of Gilbert de Pencestre, grants to the church and canons of St. Mary
                  Magdalen of Tunbridge two messuages in (c. 1 2 10.) [Mutilated.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> .... de .... grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalen, Tunbridge, and the canons
                  there, in frankalmoigne, two shillings of annual rent that he received of Osmaro
                  de la . . gate . . . . (<date when="1200" precision="low">c. 1200</date>.)
                  [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Convention between Peter de Dudekindenn and the prior and convent of Tunbridge,
                  by which the said Peter grants in frankalmoigne a certain rent out of the land of
                  Christiana, who was the wife of Hugh de . . . . of Dudekindein. (<date when="1200"
                     precision="low">c. 1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Thomas de Morestun grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge, in frankalmoigne,
                  40$. of annual rent from the marsh of D .... for the sustentation of one canon to
                  perform religious offices for him and his ancestors, (<date when="1220"
                     precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 15</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alice de Res, daughter of grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge i %d. of
                  annual rent for the health of her soul and of William de . . . . and all her
                  ancestors and successors which Geoffrey de Solio, Adam de . . . . , John the
                  miller, William the smith, were accustomed to pay to her. (<date when="1230"
                     precision="low">c. 1230</date>.) [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     16</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Mutilated charter. [Illegible] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 23</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Recital of a grant to the prior and convent of Tunbridge. [Mutilated.] Dated
                     <date when="1242">1242</date>. [With a broken seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     30*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Bovill grants to the prior and convent of Tunbridge, for the health of
                  his soul, the homage and service of Ralph de Grayspore which he was accustomed
                  annually to pay for three acres of land in .... (<date when="1250" precision="low"
                     >c. 1250</date>.) [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 41</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Fragment of a charter by which widow of Martin Bun .... grants to the prior and
                  convent of Tunbridge the whole (<date when="1250" precision="low">c. 1250</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 44</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Fragment of a grant to the prior and convent of Tunbridge. (<date
                     notBefore="1280" notAfter="1290" precision="low">c. 1280-90</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 52</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="118"/> KENT. Thomas, son of Ralph le N . . . . , grants to J., the prior,
                  and convent of Tunbridge all his right to a certain annual rent , &amp;c. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 63</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard, the clerk of Wolkestede, grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge 20
                  pence of annual rent from the tenement which Gervase de Hauckesherst formerly
                  held. (<date when="1270" precision="low">c. 1270</date>.) [Mutilated.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 65</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Grant to Thomas le Prior and Alice of Tunbridge which he bought of Man (<date
                     when="1280" precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) [Mutilated.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 67</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter relating to the priory of Tunbridge. [Mutilated] (<date when="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 69*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Amicia, formerly the wife of grants to sir John, the prior, and convent of
                  Tunbridge all her right, &amp;c. in [Mutilated] Dated <date>14 Ed. I</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 72*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Amicia, formerly wife of Hamo Peche, grants to the church and canons of Tunbridge
                  all right and claim in the lands and tenements which Hamo Peche her husband,
                  herself, and her daughter Alice, at any time had given to the said church arid
                  canons. Dated the Wednesday next after the feast of St. Hilary, <date when="1278"
                     >1278</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 77-</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter by which the prior and convent of Tunbridge grant to .... a piece of
                  land. (<date when="1300" precision="low">c. 1300</date>.) [Mutilated] Ch. fS.
                  John, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge grant to sir Thomas de Somersete,
                  chaplain, each day in the year, 2 white loaves and one gallon of beer, commencing
                  the Sunday in the feast . . . . 1320. Dated the Thursday next after the feast of
                  the Nativity B. V. M v <date when="1320">1320</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     88*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter. Temp. Ed. II. [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 89*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Rental of lands belonging to the prior and convent of Tunbridge, arranged in
                  quarterly payments, (<date when="1340" precision="low">c. 1340</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 119</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture witnessing that the prior and convent of Tunbridge demise to "Walter ,
                  Clement his son, and Felicia, wife of Clement, for their lives, a certain messuage
                  in the parish of for an annual rent of 2*. Dated at Tunbridge, 8 April, TO Rich.
                  II. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 124</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture by which the prior and convent of Tunbridge grant to John Begby certain
                  land which Richard Skynhale formerly had, &amp;c. Dated . . . Michaelmas, 22 Rich.
                  II. [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 128</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture by which Thomas Lewes, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge demise to
                  John Maundeville of Stanesgate, co. Essex, a messuage, ten acres of land, and four
                  acres of marsh ; also a tenement and land in [Mutilated] Dated at Stanesgate, 20
                  April, <date>8 Hen. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 132</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture between the prior and convent of Tunbridge of the one part, and Richard
                  .... and Joan his wife of Bodkesham of the other part, witnesseth [Mutilated]
                  Dated at Tunbridge the feast of .St. Michael, <date>9 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 133</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="119"/> KENT. Indenture made 10 .... in the . . Hen. VIII, between Richard
                  Thomlyn, prior, and the monastery of Tunbridge, of the one part, and William Cook
                  of Estegreuewych, concerning their parsonage of . . . . , within the county of
                  Kent [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 141</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Bartholomew de Wichelindenn grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge one croft
                  lying near Tunbridge, between the land of the said canons and the land of Gervase
                  Palmer, (<date when="1240" precision="low">c. 1240</date>.) [Mutilated.'] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 11</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Edith, daughter of John the merchant, grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalen
                  of Tunbridge all her lands in the parish of Tunbridge. (<date when="1220"
                     precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Crispin grants to William Cuminehe the whole of his messuage in
                  Tunbridge, he paying for all services lib of cummin, saving the service due to the
                  church of St. Mary Magdalen, Tunbridge. (<date when="1260" precision="low">c.
                     1260</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 18</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry, son of Nicholas Fromund, grants to the church of Tunbridge an annual rent
                  of one penny from the land of ' la Denne ' in the parish of Tunbridge. (<date
                     when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     21</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of Eilwin, grants to John Rolland one 'deiwerk' of land in
                  Tunbridge. (<date when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) [Mutilated.'] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 38</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, son of Peter Blod, grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge the whole
                  gift which Peter his father with his body made to them, viz. one croft which lies
                  near the way going from Tunbridge to W T inchelsea, and 6d. annual rent from
                  Bartholomew the physician, (<date when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 39</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Peter Blod, son of Humphrey Blod, grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge a
                  croft which lies to the right of the way which leads from Tunbridge to Winchelsea,
                  and also 6d. annual rent received from Bartholomew the physician from a messuage
                  in the borough of Tunbridge which he holds of him. (<date when="1220"
                     precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 40</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> "Walter, son of Walter Scrotyn and Alice Cotel, quit-claims to the prior and
                  canons of Tunbridge all his right and claim in all the lands arid tenements which
                  were Richard's, son of Benedict Cotel, in the parish of Tunbridge. (<date
                     when="1250" precision="low">c. 1250</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     45</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, son of Ralph cle Hynesfeld, grants to the prior and canons of St. Mary
                  Magdalen, Tunbridge, 30 pence of annual rent which Walter and Roger, sons of . . .
                  . , were accustomed to pay out of the lands they held of him in Yndenne in the
                  parish of Tunbridge. (<date when="1230" precision="low">c. 1230</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 50</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, son of John de Hynesfeld, and Agnes his wife, grant to Ralph, son of
                  Jordan de Hynesfeld, 12 pence of rent which Baldwin was accustomed to pay for
                  certain land called in Ydenne. (<date notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240"
                     precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 50*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Nicholas Godere grants to Thomas .... one part of his enclosure [Hage] in the
                  borough of Tunbridge, namely, that which is called Fikeresland. (<date when="1250"
                     precision="low">c. 1250</date>.) [Mutilated.'] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     55</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="120"/> Roger, son of Baldwin the Convert, grants to the prior and canons of
                  Tunbridge the whole of the land called * Hoppereslond/ which came to him after the
                  death of his father, in the parishes of Tunbridge and Bitteberg', as well as other
                  lands in Tunbridge. (c. 1 260.) [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 57</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard, son of Benedict Cotel, quit-claims to the church and canons of Tunbridge
                  the whole of his land and tenement, with appurtenances, &amp;c., in the village of
                  Tunbridge. (<date when="1270" precision="low">c. 1270</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 61</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard de Fordhamtone quit-claims to the church of St. Mary Magdalen, Tunbridge,
                  all his right in certain land in Tunbridge. (<date when="1270" precision="low">c.
                     1270</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 64</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Grant to the priory of Tunbridge of 14^. of annual rent from a messuage in
                  Langport in Tunbridge. (<date when="1270" precision="low">c. 1270</date>.)
                  [Mutilated.] Ch.66. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>John Pistor of Tunbridge and Isabella his wife grant to John their son in the
                  village of Tunbridge called ' Hwetcroft.' (<date when="1280" precision="low">c.
                     1280</date>.) [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 70</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Grant to Ralph, son of Sab .. le .... all his right in certain land in the parish
                  of Tunbridge at an annual rent of zd. [Mutilated] Dated <date>9 Ed. I</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 70*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard, son of Nicholas le Deme of Tunbridge, grants to the priory of Tunbridge
                  in frankalmoigne the whole of his land called 'La Wetecrofte' in Tunbridge. (<date
                     notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 71</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of Richard le Deme of Tunbridge, grants to the prior and canons of
                  Tunbridge the whole of the tenement with houses thereon, which John le Deme his
                  uncle held of the said canons without their gate. Also he quit-claims to them all
                  his right in all other tenements which the said Richard his father, William and
                  John his uncles, at any time held in Tunbridge of the fee of the canons, (<date
                     notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 72</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Brekyuche and Christiana his wife, daughter of Peter de Hinherest, grant
                  to Richard, son of Peter de Hinherest, and Sibella, relict of Giles de Hinherest,
                  one messuage with a curtilage, and one half acre of land in Hesdenne, in the
                  parish of Tunbridge. Dated <date>10 Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     75</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Goman, senior, grants to John Paris and Margaret his wife two acres and a
                  half of land in the parish of Tunbridge. Dated at Tunbridge the Thursday on the
                  vigil of St. Andrew the apostle, <date>7 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     80</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Stephen Crabbe grants to John, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge one messuage
                  with a curtilage adjoining, which lies in the parish of Tunbridge, in a certain
                  place called Langporte. Dated <date>17 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     82</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Amicia, called Ma Deghestre/ and Isabella her sister, grant to Nicholas Lovecok
                  three ' deywercas ' and a half of land in Tunbridge, in a certain place called
                  Langeport. Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of the Trinity, <date>4 Ed. III</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 91*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="121"/> Roger de Bardenne grants to Robert and John de Hesedenne 2od. of
                  annual rent from a meadow called Dodekynesmed in the parish of Tunbridge, Dated at
                  Tunbridge the Wednesday on the feast of the Annunciation, <date>6 Ed. III</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 92</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Nicholas Lovecok of Tunbridge grants to John, son of Simon the tailor, of
                  Osprenge, the whole of the land which he acquired of Amicia Deghestre and Isabella
                  her sister, in a certain place called Langport in Tunbridge. [Mutilated.'] Dated
                  at Tunbridge the Monday after the feast of the Annunciation, <date>22 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 99</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Roger de Bardenne grants to farm to William, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge
                  22^ acres of land and nine ' deyworkas,' the land being near the way leading from
                  Tunbridge to Speldherst. Dated at Tunbridge on the vigil of the Epiphany, 2 2 Ed.
                  III. Ch. id. Roger de Barden remits and quit-claims to the prior and convent of
                  Tunbridge all right in >]d. annual rent from certain land held by the prior and
                  convent in Tuubridge. [Mutilated] Dated at St. Cuthbert, <date>22 Ed. III</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 102</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Simon of Osprenge quit-claims to the prior and convent of Tunbridge all
                  right in the lands he acquired of Nicholas Lovecok in a certain place called
                  Langeport in Tunbridge. [Mutilated] Dated at Tunbridge .... Purification B.Y.M.,
                     <date>23 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 104</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Emma, relict of William atte Sandhell of Tunbridge, attorns John atte Bourne to
                  give seisin to John Simon of Osprenge of a certain part of a curtilage in
                  Langeport in the parish of Tunbridge, which came to her by heirship after the
                  death of Richard le Mous her father. Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of the
                  apostles St. Philip and St. James, <date>23 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 107</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sampson de Middelton and Lucy his wife grant to the prior and convent of
                  Tunbridge, for 405. sterling, one acre of land in ' Stoncrouchecroft.' Dated at
                  Tunbridge on the octave of Easter, <date>19 Ed. III</date>. [Mutilated] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 98</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Sampson of Tunbridge, son and heir of Sampson de Middilton, and Lucy his
                  wife, grants to the prior and convent of Tunbridge and their successors all right
                  and claim in a certain croft called Stoncrouchcroft in the parish of Tunbridge ;
                  also in 8 days' work of land, with appurtenances which lie in the same croft.
                  Dated at Tunbridge the Thursday next before the feast of St. Dunstan, <date>23 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 108</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Roger de Barden quit-claims to the prior and convent of Tunbridge all his right
                  and claim in 22^ acres of land and 9 deywerks, &amp;c., in a place called
                  Quarerewode. Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of St. Matthew, apostle, <date>23 Ed.
                     III</date>. (See <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 101</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 109</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="122"/> William and Roger, sons of John Mesynglegh, and Richard Galdhelle of
                  Tunbridge grant to John Simon of Osprenge the whole of the land which they had by
                  the gift of Alice, relict of Richard Halecok, viz. i\ acre in the fields of
                  Tunbridge. Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of St. Mark, evangelist, <date>24 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 110</bibl></p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Pikot and Margaret his wife grant to the prior and canons of Tunbridge icd.
                  of annual rent which they acquired of John Chercote and Sarah his wife from a
                  certain meadow called ' Dodekynesmed ' in the parish of Tunbridge. Dated at
                  Tunbridge on the feast of St. Leonard, <date>27 Ed. III</date>. [With seals.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 111*</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, son of William Brounyng of Eylesford, grants to Espelon of Sandwich the
                  whole of his share in a tenement called Littlebarden in the parish of Tunbridge.
                  Dated at Tunbridge <date>28 Ed. III</date>. [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     112*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard, son of John de Hasden, grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge in
                  frankalmoigne lod. of annual rent from a meadow called Dodekynesmede in the parish
                  of Tun bridge. A Dated at Tunbridge on the morrow of the Assumption B. V. M.,
                     <date>30 Ed. III</date>. OA. 114. Richard Sandhelle of Tunbridge demises to
                  Robert, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge, for 20 years, the whole of his part,
                  viz. the half of the grange called Blackhel, which was formerly Richard Mous', at
                  an annual rent of ^d. Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of St. Michael, <date>50 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 116</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Symkyn of Tunbridge grants to Richard Hobecok of the same place all those
                  lands, fields, and pastures which were lately acquired from Robert Hobedy and
                  Alice Hemeres, lying in the parish of Tunbridge at Hesdenne, in a certain place
                  called Hemerys, in exchange for a meadow called ' Bothelmed.' Dated at Tunbridge
                  the Sunday next after the feast of St. Valentine, martyr, <date>50 Ed. III</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 117</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard Hobecok of Tunbridge grants to Richard Bysschop and Laurence Chyvaler de
                  Bello all those lands together with a field and garden in the parish of Tunbridge,
                  in a certain place called ' Hemerys/ Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of St.
                  Michael, <date>50 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 118</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Daniel of Childyntone quit-claims to William Hore of Tunbridge all his right
                  in lands and tenements in Tunbridge which were Joan's, daughter of Robert
                  Carpenter of Tunbridge, lately wife of the said William. Dated at Tunbridge the
                  last day of May, <date>3 Rich. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 121</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge lease to William .... a piece of land
                  in the parish of Tunbridge, at an annual rent of .... Dated at Tunbridge,
                  Michaelmas, <date>6 Rich. II</date>. [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     122</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="123"/> Roger Genow, clerk, John Brookes, and William Chaundeler of Ton-
                  bridge, grant to Richard Ernyld and others all their lands, tenements, and rents
                  in Tunbridge. Dated at Tunbridge, 17 Novemb., <date>9 Hen. IV</date>. [Mutilated.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 130</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The will of Agnes Ryng of Tunbridge, relict of John Ryng, made on St. Clement's
                  day, pope and martyr, <date>10 Hen. VI</date>, containing bequests to the priory
                  of Tunbridge. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 134</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture dated yth July, <date>I Hen. VIII</date>, between Richard Thomlyn,
                  prior, and the convent of Tunbridge of the one part, and Edward Markley of the
                  other part, witnesseth that the prior and convent have demised to E. M. two pieces
                  of land with a garden within the borough of Tunbridge for 50 years, at an annual
                  rent of 6s. Sd. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 136</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WETCROFT. Hamo Peche and Amicia his wife grant to Robert Peche and his heirs half
                  an acre of land lying in a certain field called ' Wetcroft ;' paying annually, at
                  the feast of St. John the Baptist, one rose. (<date when="1260" precision="low">c.
                     1260</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 54</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WICHERST. Clement, son of Martin, grants to the prior and canons of Tunbridge the
                  whole of his land which he had upon Wicherst, paying annually for the same one
                  penny, (<date when="1230" precision="low">c. 1230</date>.) See Haisden. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 29</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YALDING. Richard de Aldynge, son of Osbert the shoemaker, grants to John Melewere
                  of Tunbridge a certain garden with apple trees growing upon the same, and the
                  whole of his part of the house standing on the same, which came to him by
                  heirship, on the death of Osbert his father and Thomas Prest his brother, in the
                  parish of Ealdinge at Twyferde. Dated <date>15 Ed. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 81</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Agnes de Blakebrok, sister and heir of Thomas de Blakebrok of Eldyngg,
                  quit-claims to the prior and convent of Tunbridge all her right in messuages,
                  lands, &amp;c., which were Thomas de Blakebrok's in Eldyngg. Dated at Eldyng the
                  Thursday next after the feast of Michaelmas, <date>8 Ed. III</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 95</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture witnesses that the prior and convent of Tunbridge have granted to farm
                  to Gilbert and Joan his wife at Twyferd in the parish of Dated at Tunbridge the
                  Epiphany, <date>26 Ed. III</date>. [Mutilated.] Ch. in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Mellewere of Ealdyng grants to John Mellere, sen., a messuage and a garden
                  at Twyford in the village of Ealdyng. Dated the Wednesday next after the feast of
                  St. Peter ad vine., 2 <date>2 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     142</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Mellere of Ealdyng grants to John Mellwere and Ida his wife and John their
                  son a messuage with a garden and a piece of pasture at Twiford in the village of
                  Ealdyng. Dated at Ealdyng the Thursday on the feast of the Assumption of the
                  Virgin, <date>22 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 143</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YALDING, BRENCHLEY, TUDELEY and LEIGH. Letter of Thomas, bishop of Rochester,
                  concerning the appropriation of the <pb n="124"/> churches of Ealdyng, Brenchesle,
                  Tewdele, and Leigh, to the prior and convent of Tunbridge. Dated at the manor of
                  Trottesclyne, 28th Nov., <date when="1388">1388</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     125</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TUNBRIDGE. Fragments of a roll of documents belonging to the priory of Tunbridge,
                  viz. : <bibl type="shelfmark">Chh. 83-88.</bibl> (a) Mutilated document relating
                  to the convocation of the clergy of the province of Canterbury. (6) Petition of
                  the religious to the archbishop of Canterbury and others, setting forth the
                  non-fulfilment of the conditions contained in the king's writ, dated at Lincoln,
                  24 Nov., <date>10 Ed. II</date>, on which a subsidy of a tenth had been granted,
                  and praying that the same may be repaid to them. (See Wilkins Concilia, vol. ii.
                  p. 460.) (c) Deliberation of the clergy concerning the articles transmitted to
                  them, considered the "Wednesday after the Sunday in which is sung the office
                  Quasimodo geniti, in the church of St. Paul's, London, <date when="1319"
                     >1319</date>. [Mutilated, ] (d) Form of appointment of an attorney for
                  rendering an account of the profits and issues of a manor. (e) Letter to Walter,
                  archbishop of Canterbury, from the chapter and convent of Tunbridge, signifying
                  the appointment of William de Frend, canon of Tunbridge, as their proctor, to
                  appear before him in the church of St. Paul's, London, the Friday next after the
                  Sunday Quasimodo, to consult for the advantage of the Church of England, &amp;c.
                  Dated at Tunbridge the Id. of April, <date when="1318">1318</date>. (/) Bull of
                  pope John XXII, addressed to the abbot of Milton, Sarum diocese, for the prior of
                  Twynham. Dated at Ammon 4 Id. January. [Mutilated.] (g) Bull of pope John XXII, to
                  the prior and convent of Winchester, for the prior of Twynham. [Mutilated.] (fy
                  Letter from the pope's nuncio to the prior of Tunbridge, demanding that a good
                  horse, a palfrey, and a sumpter horse caparisoned, may be sent to his chamberlain.
                  Dated at London, 8 June, <date when="1318">1318</date>. (i) Letter directed to the
                  prior of Merton by the abbot of Cirencester and the prior of Lanthony near
                  Gloucester presiding at the general chapter of the order of St. Augustine, for the
                  collection of subsidy for the lawsuit against the priory of Twynham. Dated <date
                     when="1318">1318</date>. (&amp;) Letter to the heads of houses of the order of
                  St. Augustine from William, abbot of Merton, concerning the collection of the said
                  subsidy. Dated 4. Non. Nov., <date when="1318">1318</date>. (I) Letter of
                  presentation of the heirs of Okestede. [Mutilated] (m) Mutilated document
                  concerning the collection of the subsidy against the priory of Twynham. (n) Letter
                  of William, abbot of St. Mary of Merton, revoking the sentence of the greater
                  excommunication promulgated against the prior of Tunbridg-e for the non-payment of
                  the subsidy. <pb n="125"/> (o) Answer of the clergy to the archbishop of
                  Canterbury in the council held at London, containing the heads of matters proposed
                  for deliberation. [Mutilated.] (p) Mutilated document concerning the same council
                  (o). (q) Form for the appointment of a general proctor by John, the prior of
                  Tunbridge. (r) John, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge present Benedict de
                  Ealdyng (Yalding) to the church of Stradselle, Norwich diocese. (s) Mutilated
                  letter of Gilbert Clare, earl of Gloucester and Hertford, to the prior and convent
                  of Tunbridge. (t) Letter of Laurence ate Wealde, canon and proctor of the prior
                  and monastery of Tunbridge. (u) Benedict de Ealdyng (Yalding) indemnifies the
                  prior and convent of Tunbridge, on his presentation to the church of Stradeshulle,
                  against any suit, and promises to be satisfied with the allowances hitherto paid.
                  Dated the Thursday next before the feast of the apostles Simon and Jude. (v)
                  Letter of excuse from the prior of Rochester to the prior of Tunbridge.
                  [Mutilated.] (w) Letters testimonial for priest's orders from Roger, the prior of
                  Tunbridge, to the bishop of Rochester, in favour of "W. Mareschal. Dated 13 kl.
                  October. (x) The priors of the monasteries of Ledes and Combewell, deputed
                  visitors of the houses of the order of St. Augustine, Canterbury and Rochester
                  dioceses, notify to the prior and convent of Tunbridge their intention to visit
                  their house the Wednesday on the feast of the Conversion of St. Paul next. Dated
                  at Ledes on the morrow of St. John the Baptist, <date when="1311">1311</date>. (y]
                  Simon de Clare, clerk, swears that he will be faithful to the church of St. Mary
                  Magdalen, Tunbridge, and to his lords the prior and convent of the same place.
                  Dated the Sunday on the feast of the Assumption of the B. V. M., <date when="1316"
                     >1316</date>. (z) Roger, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge acknowledge that
                  John de Gelderegg, their servant at Tunbridge, has rendered his account of
                  receipts and expenditure to the date of the feast of St. Michael, <date>5 Ed.
                     II</date>. Dated at Tunbridge, &amp;c. (aa) Mutilated deed of John Hering. (66)
                  Mutilated deed of Andrew (cc) Citation of the priors of Ledes and of Combewelle,
                  visitors of the houses of the order of St. Augustine within the dioceses of
                  Canterbury and Rochester, to the prior of Tunbridge to come to the general council
                  to be held in Christ Church, London, <date when="1318">1318</date>. [Mutilated.}
                  (dd) Letters patent of King Edward II, dated at Westminster, 22 May, 14 of his
                  reign, being a pardon for Henry de Shipton and <pb n="126"/> others for detaining
                  the castle of Tunbridge, in opposition to the king's writ to the sheriff for
                  seizing it and other possessions of Hugh de Audley. (ee) Writ of King Edward II,
                  concerning the lands, &amp;c. of Hugh de Audele, junior. [Mutilated.] (JT} Letter
                  of Walter, archbishop of Canterbury, to the prior and convent of Tunbridge
                  concerning an exchange between William, rector of Merston, and the vicar of
                  Brenchley. Dated at Lambeth, Nones May. (gg) John, the prior, and convent of
                  Tunbridge grant to master Walter de Grenewey an annual pension of two marks. Dated
                  at Tunbridge, &amp;c. (hTi) John, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge grant to sir
                  Thomas de Somersete, chaplain, a corrody of 2 white loaves and one gallon of the
                  better conventual beer from their common cellar, commencing the Sunday on the
                  feast of the exaltation of the Holy Cross, <date when="1320">1320</date>. (See Ch.
                  88*.) (ii) Letter of pope John XXII to the archbishop of Canterbury, directing him
                  to exhort the king to the due observance of the laws and just government,
                  especially for the non-exaction of subsidies for wars from the possessions of the
                  church. Dated at A . . . . ist year of his pontificate. (kfc) Claricia, who was
                  wife of sir Roger de Wellesworth, kt., deceased, and Alice, who was wife to sir
                  John de Hamme, kt., deceased, daughters and heirs of sir Roland de Hokstede,
                  deceased, present to the prior and convent of Tunbridge their faithful clerk
                  Robert Quyntyn as a canon of their house. Dated at London, 14 Aug., <date
                     when="1319">1319</date>. (II) Letter of H., bishop of Rochester, to the prior
                  of Tunbridge, inviting him to be present at his inthronement in the church of
                  Rochester on the octave of the Epiphany. Written at Borstall near Rochester, the
                  kl. January. (mm) "Writ of Edward II, tested at Westminster 25 Jan., nth of his
                  reign, to the bailiffs of Roger Dammory of Bodegesham, to allow the prior of
                  Tunbridge to appear by proxy at the court of Bodegesham. (nn) John, the prior of
                  Tunbridge, appoints in his place Richard de Hoton to make suit to the court of his
                  lord, sir Roger de Ammory of Bodegesham, according to the tenor of the king's writ
                  directed to the bailiffs of the said court. Dated at Tunbridge the day of the
                  Annunciation, <date>13 Ed. II</date>. (oo) Richard de Holedene, priest, having
                  been presented by the prior and convent of Tunbridge to the church of Leghe,
                  indemnifies them against any claim to the advowson. Dated at Bromlegk, 2 Non.
                  Sept., <date when="1320">1320</date>. An inrolment of evidences, records of
                  proceedings, presentations and various documents appertaining to the priory of St.
                  Mary Magdalen, Tunbridge. Kent Rotts, 6. <pb n="127"/> (a) Fragment of a bond
                  given by the prior and convent of Tunbridge to John de Feriby, to secure the
                  payment of an annual pension of four marks. Dated at Tunbridge, 30 March, <date
                     when="1322">1322</date>. (6) Mandate from the priors of St. Gregory of
                  Canterbury, and of Tunbridge, visitors of the order of St. Augustine for
                  Canterbury and Rochester dioceses, to the prior and convent of Ledes, to cite all
                  the brethren of the convent to be present at a visitation of their house to be
                  held the Monday next after the translation of St. Thomas the martyr ; also citing
                  the prior to the general chapter to be held at St. Frideswide, Oxon, the 2nd day
                  after the feast of St. Margaret the Virgin. Dated at Canterbury on the feast of
                  the translation of St, Thomas the martyr, <date when="1322">1322</date>. (c)
                  Letter of John, the prior of Tunbridge, appointing William de Mallyng, canon of
                  the same house, his proctor to act for him at the general chapter to be held in
                  the monastery of St. Frideswide, Oxon. Dated at Tunbridge, 16 kl. Aug., <date
                     when="1322">1322</date>. (d) Letter from John, the prior, and convent of
                  Tunbridge to sir William de Scelvestrod, prior of Michelham. [Mutilated.] (e)
                  Mandate from King Edward II, to the sheriff of Kent, to seise the lands, tenements
                  and goods of Henry d'Audley, junior, in his bailiwick. Dated at Gloucester the 9th
                  April, 14 of his reign. (/) Letter from Thomas, earl of Lancaster, to the mayor
                  and good men of London, inclosing a letter addressed to the king by the barons.
                  Dated at his castle of Pontefract, 2nd December. (g) Copy of the letter from the
                  barons to the king demanding redress, &amp;c., sent as above (/). [Mutilated.] (h)
                  Nicholas, son of Nicholas de Stanmer, clerk, has received of Walter, archbishop of
                  Canterbury, one field called ' le pykedecroft,' with one grange built thereupon as
                  inclosed within hedges and ditches. And one field called ' le sandpetfeld '
                  enclosed by ancient boundary ditches, also one field lying near the curtilage of
                  William de Londeshamne as is inclosed by the boundary ditches, which fields the
                  said William, a native of the archbishop, lately held of him in villenage, in the
                  borough (Iborgha) of Okkefelde at Londeshame rendering annually the same service
                  which the said William was accustomed to make. (i) Commission from the prior of
                  Tunbridge and the archdeacon of Rochester to the prior of St. Andrew the apostle
                  of Rochester, executor or provisor in the business of making a provision for
                  Richard, a poor clerk of Brenchley, Rochester diocese. [Mutilated] (k) Letter from
                  John, the prior of Tunbridge, (being absent,) to Nicholas de Faversham, sub-prior,
                  to nominate a fit clerk to the bishop of Norwich for the church of Stradeselle
                  then vacant. (I) Petition to the bishop for an indulgence to all who pray for the
                  soul of sir Richard de Clare, formerly earl of Hertford, whose body lies in the
                  church of St. Mary Magdalen of Tunbridge, and for the souls of all faithful
                  deceased and those who shall have assisted in the building, or sustentation of the
                  lights, &amp;c. of the same church. <pb n="128"/> (w) Citation from Simon,
                  archbishop of Canterbury, to the prior and convent of Tunbridge, to appear the
                  court-day after the feast of St. Luke the evangelist, or to show their privileges.
                  Dated at Wrotham, 8 Id. Oct., <date when="1329">1329</date>. (n) Order from the
                  bishop of Rochester for the publication in the greater churches of the deanery of
                  Mailing (?) of a certain chapter of the constitutions of the council of London.
                  Dated at Hallyng, 7 kl. Sept., <date when="1329">1329</date>. [Mutilated.] (o)
                  Document. [Mutilated.] (p) The prior of Tunbridge acknowledges that he owes to
                  Stephen de Cobeham, junior, .40, payable to him on the octave of Easter next.
                  Dated 3 Oct., <date>4 Ed. III</date>. (q) ' Provocatio facta per magistrum
                  Walterum de Gronweye.' General notice of an intended appeal to the pope by N. de
                  T., proctor of the priory of Tunbridge, in case of litigation. (r) Notice to the
                  bishop of Rochester that the prior and convent of Tunbridge are absolved from a
                  sentence of excommunication passed upon them for the non-payment of Peter's pence
                  for the years <date when="1329">1329</date> and <date when="1330">1330</date>.
                  Dated at London, 12 June, <date when="1331">1331</date>. (s) Ornaments, vestments,
                  and books in the churches of Aldyng [Yalding], Brenchley, Teudele [Tudley], and
                  Denardeston, at the feast of St. Michael the archangel, <date when="1331"
                     >1331</date>, <date>5 Ed. III</date>. (t) Taxation of all the goods of the
                  priory of Tunbridge both temporal and spiritual. (w) Form of oath to be taken by
                  the prior elect of the monastery of Tunbridge at the high altar, upon his
                  installation. (v) A form for letters credential. (w) The dress of the novices at
                  their first coming and entrance. (x) Letters patent dated at North wich, 23 Sept.,
                     <date>2 Ed. I</date>ll, being a licence to the prior and convent of Boxgrave to
                  enable them to give the church of Bilsington to the prior and convent of
                  Bilsington ; to hold the same for ever. (y) Walter de Shorham, priest, Chichester
                  diocese, renounces all action and right by reason of a provision or grace from the
                  pope to the prior and convent of Tunbridge. Dated 133- (z) Letter of Hamo, bishop
                  of Rochester, to the dean of Mailing, reciting the king's writ, dated at Salop, 15
                  Jan., <date>15 Ed. II</date>, concerning the burning of Bridgenorth by Humphrey de
                  Boun, earl of Hereford and Essex, and others, and ordering a levy of all men
                  between 16 and 60 to be armed, and commanding the same to be promulgated in each
                  collegiate church. [Mutilated^ (See Rymer, Foed., vol. iii. p. 923.) (aa) Mandate
                  for the visitation of the priory of Tunbridge the Monday after the feast of our
                  Lord, by the priors of Ledes and Combwelle. Dated at Ledes, 8 Id. May, <date
                     when="1317">1317</date>. (66) Form of a circular letter to bishops from bishop
                  J., prior of Tunbridge, for the ordination of a canon or canons. Dated at
                  Tunbridge. <pb n="129"/> (cc) John, the prior, and convent of Tunbriclge grant a
                  corrody to Richard de Wyth, commencing Quadragesima Sunday, <date when="1321"
                     >1321</date>. [Mutilated.] (dd) Indulgence granted by Walter, archbishop of
                  Canterbury. Dated at Lambeth the Nones of March, <date when="1321">1321</date>.
                  [Mutilated.] (ee) John, the prior, and convent of Tunbriclge appoint Roger,
                  perpetual vicar of Tunbridge, their proctor, to appear for them in the convocation
                  of the clergy of the diocese of Rochester. [Undated] (ff) Mandate of Simon,
                  archbishop of Canterbury, to the dean of Sydyngbourne concerning the scattering of
                  the tithe corn of the church of Bordenne appropriated to the prior and convent of
                  Ledes. [Mutilated] (gy) Mandate of Hamo, bishop of Rochester, for excommunicating
                  certain parishioners of Brenchley who absent themselves from, and injure the
                  church. Dated at Hallyng <date when="1329">1329</date>. (hh) Licence granted to
                  Laurence de la Wealde by John, the prior of Tunbridge, at the instance of sir Hugh
                  Daudele and the lady Margaret countess of Cornwall, his consort, to live in their
                  family. Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of the Epiphany, <date when="1329"
                     >1329</date>. (ii) Objections of the clergy at a council held at Lambeth, 16
                  Kl. May, <date when="1330">1330</date>, to the payment of a subsidy for the war in
                  Scotland. (kk) Letter from sir Hugh Daudele to the prior and canons of Tunbridge,
                  asking for a corrody for William de la Weald. [Mutilated] (II) Mandate from the
                  official of Rochester to the dean of Mallyng, commanding him to cite the prior and
                  convent of Tunbridge to appear by themselves or a proctor on the Monday next after
                  the feast of the translation of St. Thomas the martyr, in the church of Mallyng,
                  to answer certain articles of Robert, the master and brethren of the hospital of
                  Strode. Dated at Rochester, 14 Kl. July, <date when="1330">1330</date>. (mm)
                  Articles exhibited against the prior and convent of Tunbridge, by Roger, the
                  master, and the brethren of the hospital of Strode, for the subtraction of the
                  tithes of a place commonly called ' Horsherst ' in the parish of Aldyng, for 3^
                  years. (nn) John, the prior, and the convent of Tunbridge appoint William de
                  Mailing and sir Roger de Frendesbery, rector of Strateshell, their attornies, to
                  receive the manor of Bodkesham from Richard de Queye and Agnes his wife and to
                  deliver the same to John Loy to farm. Dated at Tunbridge the Thursday after the
                  feast of St. James the apostle, . . Ed. III. (oo) Letter of John, the prior of
                  Tunbridge, to the steward and bailiffs of Elizabeth de Burgh, lady of the honor of
                  Clare, appointing Walkeline de Caney to do suit and service for him at the court
                  of Bodkesham. Dated . . Easter, <date>2 Ed. III</date>. (pp) The official of the
                  bishop of Rochester to the archdeacon of Rochester, reciting the mandate of
                  Icherus de Concrete, canon of Sarum and nuncio of the pope, for promulgating the
                  sentence of K <pb n="130"/> excommunication passed upon the prior, and convent of
                  Tunbridge, for the nonpayment of Peter's pence. Dated at Rochester the Ides of
                  May, <date when="1331">1331</date>. (qq) Relaxation of the previous mandate (pp).
                  Dated at London, 23 March, <date when="1331">1331</date>. [Mutilated.] (rr) Decree
                  of Robert de Winchelsey, archbishop of Canterbury, concerning the providing of
                  ornaments, &amp;c. for churches by the parishioners and rectors, viz. the
                  parishioners to find the chalice, mass, principal vestment, viz. the chasuble,
                  albe, amice, stole, maniple, with ii. towels for use at the high altar, cope for
                  the priest, processional cross, cross for the dead, thurible, a lamp with a bell
                  for bearing the body of Christ to the sick, a lenten veil, a banner for rogation
                  days, two hand-bells to ring before the bodies of the dead, a bier, vessels for
                  the holy water, a pax, a candlestick for the Easter candle, and bells in the
                  tower, cords for the same, fonts with locks, reparation of the nave of the church
                  in length and breadth, inside and outside, both in the altars as well as in the
                  images and windows, the inclosure of the churchyard. All other things, whether for
                  the reparation of chancel and ornaments of the same both within and without,
                  belong to the rectors. (See Wilkins 1 Concilia, vol. ii. p. 280.) (ss) John, the
                  prior, and convent of Tunbridge grant to Nicholas Colepeper an annual pension of
                  two marks. Dated at Tunbridge on the feast of the apostles Peter and Paul, 133.
                  (tt) Bond given by William ate Melle of Aldyng, John de Teu . . . and Walter ate
                  "Wealde to sir Robert de Haghaw, kt., to secure the payment of &lt;io at
                  Michaelmas next in the church of Tunbridge. [Undated.] (uu) Mandate from the
                  archdeacon of Rochester to the dean of Mallyng, commanding him to sequester the
                  churches of Aldyng, Brenchley, and Teudele, for default in not repairing them.
                  Dated at Longefeld, 5 Kl. March, <date when="1331">1331</date>. (w) Mandate from
                  the abbot of Leicester and the prior of Kenilworth, presiding at the general
                  chapter of the order of St. Augustine within the province of Canterbury, to the
                  priors of St. Gregory of Canterbury and Tunbridge, commanding them to personally
                  visit each house of the above order in the dioceses of Canterbury and Rochester,
                  to inquire concerning the state, reformation, and observance of the order whether
                  by the head or its members, and to correct and reform abuses, and in case of being
                  themselves unable to settle any matters, then to cite the heads of the houses to
                  the general chapter to be held at Dunstable on the 6ctave of Holy Trinity, <date
                     when="1334">1334</date>, &amp;c. Dated 4 Non. October, <date when="1333"
                     >1333</date>. (ww) Mandate from the abbot of Leicester and prior of Kenilworth,
                  presiding at the chapter of the order of St. Augustine in the province of
                  Canterbury, to the heads of the monasteries of that order within the dioceses of
                  Rochester and Canterbury, commanding them to receive the priors of St. Gregory of
                  Canterbury and of Tunbridge <pb n="131"/> in a suitable manner at their
                  visitation, and to carry out sentences of excommunication or suspension, should
                  they be promulgated. Dated the 3 Non. of October, <date when="1333">1333</date>.
                  (xx) Appointment of N. de T., canon of Tunbridge, and master Richard, rector of
                  St. Benedict of Wodwarf, London diocese, proctors, to act for the prior and
                  convent of Tunbridge conjointly or separately. Dated, &amp;c. (yy] Letters patent
                  of King Edward III, at the request of Bartholomew de Bavelesmere, for the
                  appropriation of the church of Chert near Ledes, to the prior and convent of
                  Ledes. Dated, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TUNBRIDGE (Priory of). An inrolment of evidences, records of proceedings,
                  presentations, and various documents appertaining to the priory of Tunbridge.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">KentRolls, 7</bibl>. </p>
               <p> (a) Appropriation by "Walter, archbishop of Canterbury, of the church of Chert to
                  the prior and convent of Ledes. (<date when="1313">1313</date>-<date when="1327"
                     >1327</date>.) [Mutilated.] (b) Confirmation by H., the prior, and convent of
                  Christ Church, Canterbury, of the appropriation of the church of Chert to the
                  prior and convent of Ledes. (c) Mutilated form of a circular letter to a bishop.
                  [Illegible.] (d) Appointment of master John de "Waltona (?), clerk, to appear at
                  the Roman court as proctor for "William, prior of Tunbridge. Dated 10 Kl. Feb.,
                     <date when="1336">1336</date>. (e) Letter from William, the prior of Tunbridge,
                  to the abbot of Oseney and prior of Bernewell, that he has appointed Thomas de
                  Rossa, canon of Ledes, to appear as his proctor at the general chapter of the
                  order of St. Augustine to be held at the priory of St. Frideswide. Dated at
                  Tunbridge, 15 Kl. July, <date when="1337">1337</date>. (/) The abbot of Oseney and
                  prior of Bernewell, presiding at a general chapter of the order of St. Augustine,
                  to the religious of St. Gregory of Canterbury, Tunbridge, Heryngham, and others,
                  to cite the priors of Bradley, Walsingham, &amp;c. to appear in the next general
                  chapter in the church of Newenham near Bedford, on the octave of the Holy Trinity,
                     <date when="1340">1340</date>. Dated by the abbot of Oseney, 8 Id. June, <date
                     when="1339">1339</date>, and by the prior of Bernewell the Id. of June, same
                  year. (&lt;/) Mandate from the abbot of Oseney and prior of Bernwell, presiding at
                  a general chapter of the order of St. Augustine within the province of Canterbury,
                  to the priors of St. Gregory of Canterbury and of Tunbridge, commanding them to
                  visit the houses, &amp;c. of the order within the dioceses of Rochester and
                  Canterbury. Dated by the abbot of Oseney, and prior of Bernewell, <date
                     when="1339">1339</date>. [Mutilated.] (h) Mandate from the abbot of Oseney and
                  prior of Bernewell, presiding at a general chapter of the order of St. Augustine
                  in the pro- vince of Canterbury, to the heads of the monasteries of that order
                  within the dioceses of Rochester and Canterbury, commanding them K 2 <pb n="132"/>
                  to receive the priors of St. Gregory of Canterbury and of Tunbridge in a suitable
                  manner at their visitation, and to carry out sentences of excommunication or
                  suspension should they be promulgated. Dated 8 Kl. June, <date when="1339"
                     >1339</date>. (i) Citation of the abbot of Thorntone and -prior of Kirkham to a
                  general chapter of the order of St. Augustine to be held at Newstead near
                  Stamford, Lincoln diocese. Dated at Thornton, 3 Non. Novemb., and at Kirkhain, 8
                  Id. Dec., <date when="1340">1340</date>. Received by the priory of Tunbridge, 4
                  Kl. Dec., following. (k) Writ of King Edward III, for the collection of a ninth
                  granted by parliament i4th of his reign, in the county of Kent. [Continued on next
                  roll (a).] (I) Indulgence of 40 days, granted by John, archbishop of Canterbury,
                  to all who shall assist in rebuilding that portion of the priory of Tunbridge
                  which was destroyed by fire. Dated .... 133 . (m) Licence granted to Reginald de
                  "Wyk for the celebration of mass in his chapel at Romchedde by the bishop of
                  Rochester. Dated .... <date when="1338">1338</date>. (n) Absolution by Robert,
                  bishop of Sarum, from the sentence of suspension passed upon William de Handloo,
                  priest, for one year, because he solemnized matrimony between John de Foxle and
                  Matilda Brocas without the church of Bray. Dated at Sheftesbery, 5 Id. April,
                     <date when="1332">1332</date>. (o) Of the weight of lead. Memorandum that a
                  cart load of lead contains 30 feet, and each foot six stone, and each stone
                  i3^Ib., and one foot contains 8ilb. And so a cart load of lead contains, according
                  to the weight used at Me Pek,' <date when="2430">2430</date>^. Item, according to
                  the weight used at Sandwich, a cart load of lead ought to weigh six sacks of wool,
                  and a sack of wool should weigh 52 hooks, and each hook contains fib., and so a
                  sack of wool weighs 364!!). And so a cart load of lead weighs by the weight of
                  wool <date when="2184">2184</date>!!). And so each cart load of lead at ' le Boles
                  ' exceeds the weight of wool <date when="2461">2461</date>6. (p) Commission from
                  H., bishop of Rochester, to Adam de Murymouth, canon of London, for negotiating
                  the exchange between John de Beylham, rector of Chelesworth, and Alan de Lavenham,
                  vicar of Tunbridge. Dated at Hallyng, Id. July, <date when="1340">1340</date>. (q)
                  Institution by Adam Murymouth, canon of London, commissary of H., bishop of
                  Rochester, of John de Beylham, priest, to the vicarage of Tunbridge, by the
                  resignation of Alan de Lavenham, because of an exchange with the church of
                  Chelesworth, Norwich diocese, on the presentation of the prior of the hospital of
                  St. John of Jerusalem. Dated at Brues, 17 Kl. August, <date when="1340"
                     >1340</date>. (r) The prior and convent of Tunbridge present sir Roger de
                  Frendesbery to the church of Leigh by reason of an exchange with Henry de Shyptone
                  to the church of Stradselle, Norwich diocese. Dated 5 Kl. August, <date
                     when="1340">1340</date>. <pb n="133"/> (s) Resignation of the rectory of
                  Stradselle by Roger de Frend (sic), on account of an exchange with Henry de
                  Shipton, rector of Legh. Dated, &amp;c. (t) Appointment of proctors by Henry de
                  Schipton, rector of Legh, to act for him in the matter of an exchange with the
                  church of Stradselle. (u) Lease from John, the prior, and convent of Tunbridge to
                  Roger de Frendesbery, rector of Stradeselle, of their chapel of Denardestone for 1
                  2 years, at an annual payment of half a mark. Dated on the day of St. Peter ad
                  Vine., <date when="1336">1336</date>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An inrolment of evidences, records of proceedings, presentations, and various
                  documents appertaining to the priory of Tunbridge. Kent <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 8</bibl>. (a) Concluding portion of the king's writ, described Roll 7
                  (&amp;). (6) Letter of Hamo, bishop of Rochester, to the king for a writ de
                  excommunicato capiendo against Walter atte Hale. (c) Letter from Robert, abbot of
                  Lesnes, excusing himself from attending to a provision granted by the pope to
                  Richard Aleyn of Cokelestan, a poor clerk of Rochester diocese, on account of
                  urgent business touching his monastery. (d) Commission from the abbot of B. and
                  the prior of Tunbridge, co-delegates with the abbot of Lesnes, to two canons of
                  St. David, for carrying out the provision granted to the above Richard Aleyn by
                  the pope, to collate him to an ecclesiastical benefice with or . without cure of
                  souls, within the diocese of Rochester. (e) Mandate from John, archbishop of
                  Canterbury, to the bishops and ' archdeacons of the province of Canterbury,
                  ordering them to take steps to prevent the misappropriation of the goods of the
                  lord Hugh d'Audele, late earl of Gloucester, deceased, in their several juris-
                  dictions, in accordance with the complaint of his executors. Dated at Lambeth, 5
                  Id. April, <date when="1348">1348</date>. (/) Appropriation of the church of
                  Westham, with the chapel of Edulwesbregge annexed, to the prior and chapter of
                  Christ Church, Canterbury, by Hamo, bishop of Rochester, with the ordination of
                  the vicarage. Dated at Hallyng, 25 Jan., <date when="1327">1327</date>. (y)
                  Appropriation of the church of Lethered, Winchester diocese, to the prior and
                  convent of Ledes, by John, archbishop of Canterbury, (the see of Winchester being
                  then vacant). Dated <date when="1346">1346</date>. (h) Confirmation by Henry, the
                  prior, and convent of Canterbury of the appropriation of the church of Chart,
                  Canterbury diocese, to the prior and convent of Ledes, by Walter, archbishop of
                  Canterbury. Dated, &amp;c. [<date when="1320">1320</date>.] (i) A schedule of
                  debts owing to the prior and convent of Tunbridge, demanded from the executors of
                  Hugh d'Audele, earl of Gloucester, deceased. <pb n="134"/> KENT. (k) Letter of
                  attorney from N., the prior of Tunbridge, appointing Gk de B., canon, their
                  proctor, to receive in their name oblations and gifts for rebuilding their church,
                  destroyed by fire, and also to notify the indulgences (amounting in the whole to 8
                  years and 230 days) from the pope, archbishops, and bishops, to all benefactors,
                  with participation in the masses and other services of their church. (I)
                  Indulgence by the pope's authority from Stephen, archbishop of Aries, and
                  chamberlain of the pope, to all persons in the diocese of Rochester, that plenary
                  absolution may be given by any confessor during the plague now raging, to every
                  one without exception in articulo mortis, up to the next Easter. Dated at Avignon,
                  Tuesday, 23 December, <date when="1348">1348</date>. (m) Ordination of the
                  vicarage of Chart, Canterbury diocese. Dated at Lambeth, 4 KL March, <date
                     when="1320">1320</date>. (n) David, the prior, and convent of St. Mary Magdalen
                  of Tunbridge collate Nicholas de Debeham, priest, to the vicarage of Tudley, on
                  the recommendation of Laurence, bishop of Rochester. Dated at Tunbridge, 5 Kl.
                  March, <date when="1273">1273</date>. (o) The prior of Tunbridge appoints Henry de
                  Deseburgh to act in all pleas and quarrels moved by him, and against him during
                  his absence. (p) Letter of the king to the bailiffs of Ralph, baron of Stafford of
                  Eldyngge, allowing the prior of Tunbridge to appear by proxy at the court of the
                  said lord of Eldyng. Tested, &amp;c. (q) Petition to the king for a licence in
                  mortmain to purchase lands and rents of the value of &lt;io per annum. (r) Letter
                  from the prior of Tunbridge to the lady Margaret de Clare thanking her for a gown,
                  and asking for her continued assistance with regard to the appropriation of the
                  church of Stradesell. (s) Letter from the prior of Tunbridge to the lady Margaret
                  de Clare, praying for an allowance of the balance of a debt due to her of n 95.
                  2d. in consideration of the damage done to their manor of Tunbridge Hall. (t)
                  Mandate from the abbot of St. James, Northampton, and the prior of Dunstable,
                  presidents of the chapter of the order of St. Augustine, held at Northampton in
                  the Quindene of the Holy Trinity, <date when="1350">1350</date>, to the priors of
                  Tunbridge and of St. Gregory, Canterbury, visitors of the order within the
                  dioceses of Canterbury and Rochester, to visit all the houses of the order in the
                  said dioceses, and to report to a chapter to be held at Oseney in the Quindene of
                  the Holy Trinity, I 353- Dated Ides April, <date when="1352">1352</date>. (u)
                  Mandate from Hamo, bishop of Rochester, to the rural dean of Mailing, to cite the
                  clergy and laity of the parish churches within his deanery to appear at the
                  visitation to be held at certain churches and on certain days specified. Dated 18
                  Kl. October, <date when="1352">1352</date>. (v) A petition to lady Margaret de
                  Clare to prevent her officers from levying fines and holding courts, &amp;c.
                  within the moiety of the old <pb n="135"/> manor of Bodekesham, granted to the
                  priory of Tunbridge by Richard de Clare, formerly earl of Hertford, her ancestor.
                  (w) Letter of the archdeacon of Rochester to the dean of Mailing, sending the
                  mandate of John, bishop of Rochester, for holding a visitation on the Monday next
                  after the feast of SS. Tiburtius and Valerian, <date when="1352">1352</date>, in
                  the cathedral of Rochester. Dated at Langefeld, 2 Kl. April, <date when="1353"
                     >1353</date>. (x) Citation from the rural dean of Mailing to the clergy and
                  laity of his deanery to appear at the above visitation (w). (y) Notice of their
                  proposed visitation of the monasteries of Combwell, Ledes, and Bilsyngton, from
                  the priors of Tunbridge and of St. Gregory, Canterbury, the visitors of houses of
                  the order of St. Augustine in the dioceses of Canterbury and Rochester. Dated at
                  the priory of St. Gregory, Canterbury, 13 Kl. May, <date when="1353">1353</date>,
                  and at the priory of Tunbridge, 12 Kl. of the same month and year. (z) Return of
                  the priors of Tunbridge and of St. Gregory, Canterbury, to the abbot of Waltham
                  and the prior of Gisborne, presidents of the chapter of the order of St. Augustine
                  held, in the monastery of Oseney in the Quindene of the Holy Trinity, <date
                     when="1353">1353</date>, in accordance with the above mandate (t) for the said
                  visitation (y). Dated at Canterbury, 6 Id. May, <date when="1353">1353</date>.
                  (aa) Mandate from Thomas, the abbot of the exempt monastery of the Holy Cross of
                  Waltham, who, together with the abbot of Leicester and prior of Gisborne, presided
                  at the chapter of the order of St. Augustine held at Oseney in the Quindene of the
                  feast of the Holy Trinity, commanding the prior of Ledes to levy and collect from
                  each house of the same order in the diocese of Canterbuiy a payment of one
                  halfpenny for each mark upon their goods, according to their taxation for the
                  support of the said order, and to pay the amount collected, together with the
                  names of those who refuse payment, to the abbot of Waltham within 40 days of the
                  feast of the Purification of B. V. M. Dated at Waltham, i Dec., <date when="1353"
                     >1353</date>. The prior of Tunbridge satisfied this mandate the Sunday on the
                  morrow of the conversion of St. Paul, <date when="1353">1353</date>. Total, 6s.
                  2\d. (bb) Letter of John, bishop of Rochester, to the dean of Mallyng, giving
                  notice of his intended visitation of the deanery of Mallyng, to be held in the
                  church of Eld the Thursday and Friday after the feast of the exaltation of the
                  Holy Cross next ensuing, and com- manding him to cite the rectors, vicars,
                  &amp;c., of his deanery to the same. Dated at Hallyng, 14 August, <date
                     when="1354">1354</date>. (cc) Bond given by Robert de Waldyngfeld, Nicholas
                  Tone, and William Osebern, of Bodekesham, to sir Henry Motelot and Robert Marchal
                  in acknowledgment of the receipt of 20 35. lod. to be employed in merchandise for
                  the profit of the said Henry and Robert, and to be accounted for to them at
                  Tunbridge the 2nd of August next. Dated at Bodekesham, 30 January, <date>28 Ed.
                     III</date>. <pb n="136"/> (dd) Condition of the above bond (cc) is that if the
                  above Robert Waldingfield, or any one in his name, pay to the prior of Tunbridge
                  at Hokday, after the date of these presents, 12, and at the feast of St. Mary
                  Magdalen .8 35. lod. ; then the said bond to be null and void. Done at Bodekesham
                  the day and year above written. (ee) Letters patent of King Edward III, dated at
                  Westminster, i April, 14 of his reign, granting licence to John, archbishop of
                  Canterbury, to enable him to assign the advowsons of Boughton Bleau (' Bocton
                  under Blee') and Preston near Ospringe in the county of Kent held in capite, to
                  the abbot and convent of Feversham, in exchange for the manor of Trynge in co.
                  Hereford. (ff] John, archbishop of Canterbury, grants to the abbot and convent of
                  Feversham the advowsons of the churches of ' Bocton under the Bleu,' and Preston,
                  near Ospringe, in exchange for the manor of Trynge. Dated at Lambeth, 3 April,
                     <date>14 Ed. III</date>. (gg) Robert, the prior, and chapter of Christ Church,
                  Canterbury, ratify and approve the donation to the abbot and convent of Faversham
                  (jf). Dated in their chapter, 8 April, <date>14 Ed. III</date>. (hh) Appropriation
                  by John, archbishop of Canterbury, of the churches of Bocton under the Bleu and
                  Weston near Ospreuge to the abbot and convent of Faversham. Dated in the chapter
                  of his diocese, 18 May, <date when="1340">1340</date>, and confirmed by Robert,
                  the prior, and the chapter of Christ Church, Canterbury, same time. (ii)
                  Proceedings in the matter of a licence to John de Osprenge from the prior of
                  Ledes, for his admission into the order of the friars preachers, London, upon his
                  own petition. Dated at Ledes, 4 Id. Nov., <date when="1343">1343</date>. (kk)
                  Letter from Simon, archbishop of Canterbury, to Richard Vagham, LL.D., revoking
                  the admission of John de Rothewelle to the church of Great Hardres. Dated at
                  Maghefeld, 10 Kl. Nov., <date when="1359">1359</date>. (II) Commission from Simon,
                  archbishop of Canterbury, to the official of the archdeacon of Canterbury,
                  commanding him to hold an inquiry as to who is the true patron of the church of
                  Great Hardres, to which master John de Rothewell had been admitted on the
                  presentation of the prior and convent of Tunbridge, which admission for certain
                  causes was revoked (mm). The presentation claimed by Ralph, earl of Stafford.
                  Dated at Maghefeld, 10 Kl. Nov., <date when="1359">1359</date>. (mm) The prior and
                  convent of Tunbridge claim from the executors of sir Ralph Neadgeres, earl of
                  Stafford, certain debts due to them for rent, windows in the church, and for his
                  interment. Dated <date>7 Rich. II</date>. (nn) Composition for the endowment of
                  the vicarage of Teudell (Tudley) made by David, the prior, and convent of
                  Tunbridge to Nicholas de Debeham, priest. Dated at Tunbridge, 5 Kl. March, <date
                     when="1273">1273</date>. (oo) Mutilated deed. <pb n="137"/> (j>p) Petition from
                  the prior and convent of Tunbridge to the pope, concerning the appropriation of
                  the church of Legh, Rochester diocese. (qq) Presentation of Henry de Hegham to the
                  church of St. Mary Magdalen of Stokeby, Canterbury diocese, by the prior and
                  convent of Ledes. Dated at Ledes, 19 Nov., <date when="1347">1347</date>. (rr)
                  Henry de Hegham, presented to the church of Stokeby by the prior and convent of
                  Ledes, appoints A. de B. his attorney to act for him in all the business touching
                  the said presentation. ' Dated &amp;c. (ss) Letter from the prior and canons of
                  Tunbridge, to the earl of Lancaster, asking him to send letters to Robert de
                  Caustone and J. de Harwell, executors of the earl of Gloucester for arrangement of
                  an account. (tt) Petition to the king for his licence to appropriate the church of
                  Legh to the priory of Tunbridge. (uu) Letter from King Edward III to John de
                  Offord, dean of Lincoln, and chancellor, granting his licence for the
                  appropriation of the church of Legh to the prior and convent of Tunbridge, at the
                  request of Ralph, baron of Stafford. Dated at Westminster, 23 July, <date>22 Ed.
                     III</date>. (vv) Letters patent tested at Westminster, 23 July, <date>22 Ed.
                     I</date>ll, for the appropriation of the church of Legh as in (uu). (ww)
                  Petition from the prior and convent of Tunbridge to the bishop of Rochester,
                  setting forth the damage done to their church, chapter house, dormitories and
                  dining hall, as also the library and vestment room, witli the books, vestments,
                  and ornaments by fire, and asking that the church of Legh, taxed at 12 per annum,
                  may be appropriated and incorporated for their support, and also the support of
                  two canons in their priory. (xx) Letter from Ralph, earl of Stafford, lord of
                  Tunbridge, to the archbishop of Canterbury (?) praying him to assist his chaplains
                  the prior and canons of Tunbridge, on account of their loss by fire and other
                  grievous charges. Written at Tunbridge the 1 2th day of December. (yy) Petition
                  from the prior and convent of Tunbridge to the pope, for the appropriation of the
                  church of Legh, Rochester diocese, setting forth the disaster which had befallen
                  them, &amp;c. (see ww). (zz) Petition from the prior and convent of Tunbridge to
                  the pope, praying that their churches and tithes, privileges and indulgences,
                  rents and services, lands and possessions, with their appurtenances, which they
                  enjoyed before the nth day of July, <date when="1327">1327</date>, when their
                  house was burnt, may be confirmed to them, under pain of excommunication. (aaa)
                  Commission from Richard de Haversham, treasurer of the church of Llandaff, who
                  together with the prior of St. Bartholomew, London, the abbot of Westminster and
                  the prior of the Holy Trinity, London, had been appointed by the pope conservators
                     <pb n="138"/> of the rights and privileges of the order of St. John of
                  Jerusalem, England, to the dean of Mallyng, Rochester diocese, commanding him to
                  cite or cause to be cited, David, the perpetual vicar of Teudele (Tudley), to
                  appear before the said prior of St. Bartholomew or one of the above, in the church
                  of St. Bartholomew on the third law day after the feast of St. Juliana the virgin
                  next following, concerning the usurpation of ecclesiastical rights and the
                  adminis- tration of the sacraments, and also the unjust taking away of offerings
                  in the said church of the chapel [in ecclesia capelle], made to the same
                  hospitallers. Dated at London, 5 Kl. Feb., <date when="1351">1351</date>. (bbb)
                  Ralph, earl of Stafford, petitions the pope, that the church of Heghhardres with
                  the chapel of Stellyngge, taxed at 40 marks, may be appropriated to the priory of
                  Tunbridge, for the support of two canons. (ccc) Letter of sir John de Harewell to
                  sir Robert de Caustone, touching the settlement of the debts due to the prior of
                  Tunbridge by sir Hugh de Audley, earl of Gloucester, deceased, and receiving at
                  the hands of the prior the following goods which were in his custody, viz. ' siz
                  quill ers d'or et de Jaspre, et en cire oevrez cxc livres, xii. pieces de orailes
                  de leure en amaillez, viii. papilons des margeries, un pyn de Ivoir, un Tablet de
                  Ivoyr de ymagerie, ii. petitz forceas de Ivoyr dount jay donez luu al Eglise a
                  mettre dedeynz Corpus Christi et altres reliques ; ' the prior also requesting the
                  good offices of the earl of Lancaster for the obtaining a licence of mortmain from
                  the king. (ddd) Petition from the canons of Tunbridge to the king for a licence to
                  purchase 20 of land and rents to the memory of Hugh de Audley, late earl of
                  Gloucester, and Margaret his wife, cousin of the king. (eee) Letter of the prior
                  of Tunbridge to sir Robert de Caustone, recapitulating the contents of the letter
                  of sir John de Harewell (ccc\ and adding that the ' coffre ' would be sent to John
                  de Weston at Weston. (jff} Letter to John de Weston enclosing the letters of sir
                  John de Harewell (ccc), and of the prior to sir Robert de Caustone (eee), and
                  telling him that the ' coffre ' shall be forwarded to him at the first
                  opportunity. (ggg) Petition of the prior of Ledes for the appropriation of the
                  church of Lethered. (hhh) Appropriation by John, archbishop of Canterbury, of the
                  church of Lethered to the prior and convent of Ledes. Dated at Croydone, 12 Kl.
                  April, <date when="1345">1345</date>. (Hi) Letter from King Edward III to pope
                  Clement VI, setting out the depression of the priory of Ledes in consequence of
                  the damage done to it during the siege of the castle of Ledes. Dated at
                  Westminster, 24 May, . . . (kick} Petition of King Edward III to the pope on
                  behalf of the prior and canons of Ledes for the appropriation of the church of
                  Letherhed, Winchester diocese, valued at 52 marks sterling, to that priory. <pb
                     n="139"/> (Ill) Letter from King Edward III to A., bishop of Tusculum, con-
                  cerning the appropriation of the church of Lethered. Dated at Westminster, 5 July.
                  (mmm) Petition of King Edward III to the pope, on behalf of the prior and convent
                  of Ledes, for the appropriation of the church of Lethered to their use. (nnn) Form
                  of a bond. (poo) Part of a petition to the pope by the prior and convent of Ledes,
                  setting forth the damage done to them during the siege of the castle of Ledes, as
                  also to their manors and churches by burning, and asking him to cause the church
                  of Lethered to be appropriated to them. (ppp) Letter from John Colepeper to the
                  earl of Huntyngdon, to the effect that having been ordered to commit the office of
                  deputy of the hundred of Wechilston to Nicholas Merifeld in the place of Roger de
                  Barden, the prior of Tunbridge begs that the said Nicholas may be relieved from
                  that office, inasmuch as he has care of possessions of the prior in Brenchesley.
                  (qqq) Letter from the prior of Tunbridge to the earl of Huntyngdon, praying that
                  Nicholas Merifeld, their bailiff of Brenchesley, may not be appointed deputy of
                  the hundred of Wechilston. (rrr) Letter of thanks from the prior of Tunbridge.
                  (sss) John Vaccham, alias Freeman, rector of Leghe, Rochester diocese, appoints
                  master William Bradle, canon of London, sir Thomas Vacham, priest, and John
                  Godwyne, clerk, his proctors to act for him conjointly or dividedly in all matters
                  connected with his church or any other ecclesiastical business. Dated at
                  Canterbury, 12 Aug., <date when="1354">1354</date>. (ttt) Letter from the prior
                  and canons of Tunbridge to the archbishop of Canterbury, praying him to seal a new
                  bond to be laid before him by sir Thomas de Wolton in lieu of a former cancelled
                  bond. (uuu) Letter to sir Thomas de Wolton enclosing the foregoing (ttt) and the
                  new bond for the archbishop's seal. (vvv) Letter from King Edward III to John
                  bishop of Rochester, soliciting the prayers of the people of his diocese for the
                  success of his arms in France, in consequence of the conduct of the French at the
                  court of the pope in refusing to ratify the treaty of Calais. Dated at
                  Westminster, 9 June, 29 of his reign. (www) Notice of their proposed visitation of
                  the priory of Tunbridge from the priors of Ledes and of St. Gregory, Canterbury,
                  the visitors of houses of the order of St. Augustine in the dioceses of Canterbury
                  and Rochester, on the 8th of June following. Dated at Ledes, 20 May, <date
                     when="1356">1356</date>. (xxx) Bond given by Roger de Barden to sir William de
                  Mallyng, the prior, and the convent of Tunbridge, to secure the payment of ,10 45.
                  id., in case of default a distraint to be levied on his goods. Dated at Tunbridge
                  the Tuesday next after the feast of St. Katherine, <date>26 Ed. III</date>. <pb
                     n="140"/> "Warrant for preparing letters patent for the repayment of 4 to the
                  prior of Tunbridge, lent by him to the king on the 25 June, 21 Ed. HI. (zzz)
                  Letters patent, dated at Reading 25 June, <date>21 Ed. I</date>ll, for the
                  repayment at Michaelmas, <date when="1348">1348</date>, of the preceding loan
                  (yyy). (aaaa) Warrant from Ealph, earl of Stafford, to John Fromond his receiver
                  for the lordship of Tunbridge, to allow the prior of Tunbridge to keep 60 pigs
                  free of pannage within the forest of Tun- bridge. Dated 9th April, 31 Ed. HE.
                  (bbbb) John, son of Thomas de Cobeham, quit-claims to Walter, son of sir Thomas
                  Colepeper, kt., all right in all lands and tenements together with rents and
                  services which will fall to him after the death of Elizabeth his mother, wife of
                  the said "Walter, in the county of Surrey at Gatewick. Dated at Tunbridge, 4 July,
                     <date>33 Ed. III</date>. (cccc) John, son of Thomas de Cobeham, remits to
                  Walter Colepeper and Elizabeth his wife all right in all the lands and tenements,
                  which will fall to the said John after the decease of Walter and Elizabeth in the
                  county of Kent; nevertheless the said Walter grants for himself and his heirs,
                  that if the said John or Thomas de Weston in his name, come and pay to Walter or
                  his attorney .40 in the priory of Tunbridge on the day of the nativity of St. John
                  the Baptist, within 3 years next following the date of these presents, then the
                  writing of relaxation that John made to Walter shall be void. Dated at London, 4
                  July, 33 Ed ILL (dddrf) John, son of Thomas de Cobeham, is bound in a sum of 40
                  marks sterling to Walter, son of sir Thomas Colepeper, kt. Dated at London in the
                  house of John Tamworth, clerk, 1 5 July, 33 Ed.IIL (eeee) John, son of Thomas de
                  Cobeham, is bound to Walter, son of sir Thomas Colepeper, kt., in 40 marks
                  sterling, payable in the priory of Tunbridge on Easter day after the date of these
                  presents, to secure the payment of 20 marks. Dated at London, 16 July, 33 Ed. HI.
                  (Jfff) Letters patent of King Edward III, dated at Reading, 24 January, 33rd of
                  his reign, granting to John Parys of Tunbridge and Margaret his wife a certain
                  piece of land containing 2 acres of meadow in Tunbridge, formerly Roger Bavent's,
                  to hold the same for ever. (gggg) Letter of the prior of Tunbridge to the
                  archbishop of Canterbury desiring to be excused on the ground of poverty from the
                  charge of some person entrusted to the priory by him. (hhhK) Petition from the
                  prior and convent of Tunbridge to Lionel, earl of Ulster, for the continuance of
                  their privileges of a daily supply of wood, of pannage for 60 pigs, and of the
                  yearly gift of a stag within his forest of Tunbridge. ("TO) Warrant from Ralph,
                  earl of Stafford and lord of Tunbridge, to <pb n="141"/>John
                  Fromond his receiver there, to pay to the prior and convent 10 marks. Dated at
                  Tunbridge on the feast of the translation of St. Thomas, 35 Ed. III. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>STRADISHALL and DENERDISTON, co. SUFFOLK. Two membranes of a roll concerning the
                  chapel of Denerdiston and the rectory of Stradeshulle. Dated at Tunbridge on the
                  day of St. Dunstan the archbishop, <date when="1291">1291</date>, and attested by
                  Walter le Noreys, son of the late Robert Lawys of Kellum. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Kent Rolls, 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TUNBRIDGE (Priory of). Roll containing stipends of servants, payments and gifts,
                  allowances and reparations, (<date when="1420" precision="low">c. 1420</date>.)
                  [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Kent Rolls, 10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Rent Roll of the prior and convent of Tunbridge for the 4ist Ed. III. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Kent Rolls, 11</bibl>.</p>
            </div>

         </div>

<div type="county"><head>LANCASHIRE</head>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> . CROFTBATHOC. Benedict, son of Richard de Croftbathoc, grants to the
               hospital of St. John of Jerusalem three tofts which lie between Witingham and
               Selecroft, namely ' Gillecroft/ and ' Gillemihelecroft/ and the croft which Richard
               formerly held of the hospital ; and the third part of ' Eregehoved,' with 2 fields
               pertaining to it. (<date when="1160" precision="low">c. 1160</date>70.) Lancashire
               Charters, J.. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p>CALLAN. W., the prior, and convent of Cartmel acknowledge that they are bound to pay
               annually to the brethren of the hospital of St. John of Jerusalem an annual rent of
               ys. for the land of Callan. (<date when="1200" precision="low">c. 1200</date>.) <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 2</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> LANCASHIRE. Certificate of the appointment of Philip, lord Wharton, as lieutenant of
               the county of Lancaster by the parliament. [Signed by Jo. Browne, the clerk of the
               parliament] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 3</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Duplicate copy of the above certificate. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 4</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> LANCASTER (Duchy of). Copy of a writ of King Ed. Ill (undated) granting privileges
               to Henry Plantagenet, earl of Lancaster. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 5</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Charter of King Henry V confirming to John, duke of Lancaster, Blanche his wife, and
               their heirs, the privileges, &amp;c. belonging to the duchy of Lancaster. Dated at
               Westminster, 15 Feb., <date>2 Hen. V</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 6</bibl>.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> PRESTWICH. Letters patent of King William in, dated 23 Dec., <date when="1682"
                  >1682</date>, granted to John Lake, bp. of Sodor and Man, to enable him to hold in
               commendam the rectory of Prestwich and the prebend of Fridathorp in St. Peter's
               church, York. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 7</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> SKELMERSDALE. Bond in 200 given by sir Thomas Hesketh of Rufforth, kt., to Richard
               Smalshagh for the performance of certain covenants in a pair of indentures,
               concerning a sale of a messuage, &amp;c. in Skelniersdale. Dated 4 Jan., 2 and 3
               Philip and Mary. [Signed, Thomas Hesketh] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 8</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p>
               <pb n="142"/> Thomas, son of John Mersh, constitutes Oliver Assheton his attorney to
               deliver seisin to Richard Taillior of Bolde, of all his lands and tenements in
               Skelmersdale. Dated 24 August, <date>2 Rich. III</date>. Ch. g. Thomas, son of John
               Mershe, grants to Richard Taillior of Bolde all his lands and tenements in
               Skelmersdale. Dated at Skelmersdale the Monday next after the feast of the Assumption
               B.M.V., <date>2 Rich. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 10</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Thomas, son of John Mersh, quit-claims to Richard Taillior of Bolde all his right in
               a messuage and certain lands, &amp;c. in Skelmersdale. Dated the Wednesday next
               before the feast of St. George the martyr, <date>i Hen. VII</date>. Ch. n. Richard
               Tallior grants to Thomas Hesketh, esq., all his lands, messuages, tenements, &amp;c.
               in the village of Skelmersdale in the county of Lancashire, paying annually to the
               said Richard IQS. Dated 16 Feb., <date>8 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  12</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Richard Talior quit-claims to Thomas Hesketh, esq., all his right in messuages,
               lands, &amp;c. in Skelmersdale. Dated 17 Feb., <date>8 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 13</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Richard Tailor and Thurstan his son quit-claim to Thomas Hesketh, esq., all their
               right in all their messuages, lands, &amp;c. in Skelmersdale, for a payment of 21.
               Dated 9 Dec., n Hen. VIII. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 14</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Fine made at Lancaster the Monday in the 5th week of Lent, 2 and 3 Philip and Mary,
               between Richard Smalshawe, plaintiff, and sir Thomas Hesketh, kt., and Alice his
               wife, defendants, by which the .said sir Thomas acknowledges that a messuage,
               orchard, lands, &amp;c. in Skelmersdale belong to the said Richard, he paying 30
               sterling. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 15</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> "Will, inventory, and probate of James Smalshawe of Skelmersdale, yeoman. Will dated
               3 July, <date when="1614">1614</date>. Probate dated 8 Dec., <date when="1614"
                  >1614</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 16</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> HAWKESHEAD. A catalogue of books presented to the grammar school of Hawkeshead by
               Daniel Rawlinson, citizen and vintner of London, and friends, at his request, (<date
                  when="1680" precision="low">c. 1680</date>.) Lancashire Rolls, i .</p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> NEWTON, &amp;c. Roll containing four extracts from the pipe-rolls of <date>37
                  Eliz.</date>, <date>10 Chas. I</date>, and <date>6 James I</date>, relating to
               sums of money due to the crown on account of recusancy, from lands in Newton,
               Savilesbury, &amp;c. Extracted 27 June, <date>15 Chas. I</date>, <date when="1639"
                  >1639</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 2</bibl>. </p>
         </div></div>
         
         <div type="county"><head>LEICESTERSHIRE</head>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> . ASHBY de la ZOUCH. Thomas Ormond, esq., quit-claims to William
               Stephens and his heirs all his right in the manor of Assheby de la Zouche. Dated 2
               July, <date>12 Ed. IV</date>. [Signed, T. Ormond] Leicestershire Charters, i. IN THE
               BODLEIAN LIBRAKY. 143 LEICESTER. ASHBY de la ZOUCH, PACKINGTON, and the Hundred of
               FRAML AND. Thomas Harvey of Ashby de la Zouch, gent., grants to King James all his
               right in the rectory of Ashhy de la Zouch and the rectory of Packington, co.
               Leicester, and in the hundred of Framland, also in the manor of Ashby de la Zouch,
               and in a grange called 'Alton Grandge/ and in certain lands parcel of the manor of
               Packington, all in the county of Leicester, also in the manors of Aller and Allermore
               in the co. of Somerset, also in 2 parts of the manor of Canford in the co. Dorset,
               parcel of the possessions of Henry, earl of Huntingdon, to hold during pleasure.
               Dated 13 Feb., <date>9 James I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 2</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> BURTON OVERY. Indenture made I August, <date>36 Hen. VIII</date>, by which John
               Beaumont of Gracedew, co. ^Leicester, for the sum of .12 demises to John Weston of
               Burton Overey and Edward his son a close of land in Burton Overey for 200 years at an
               annual rent of i4i&amp; <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 3</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> BURTON LAZARS (Hospital). Letter from sir William Button, kt., master, and the
               brethren of the hospital of Burton Lazars to William of Barrytam (?) receiving him as
               a benefactor into the brotherhood. Dated at Burton, <date when="1475">1475</date>,
               April 17. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 4</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> ENDERBYE. Indenture made i Nov., 30 Q. Elizabeth, by which sir George Hastings of
               Goppishill in the county of Leicester, kt., in consideration of the receipt of 500,
               lets to farm the rectory of Enderbie for 31 years, to Dyonise Orme, citizen and
               merchant taylor of London, at an annual rent of g 6s. 8d. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  5</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Indenture made 25 Nov., <date>30 Elizabeth</date>, by which Richard Branthwaite of
               London, esquire, and Roger Bromley of Bagworth park, Leicester, esq., at the request
               of Henry, earl of Huntingdon, and for a certain sum of money, sell to sir George
               Hastings, kt., brother of the said earl, the rectory of Enderbye, lately belonging to
               the dissolved monastery of the meadow of Leicester. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  6</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Indenture made i June, <date>35 Elizabeth</date>, by which the right hon. Henry,
               earl of Huntingdon, &amp;c., grants to Dionise Orme of London, merchant taylor, the
               manor of Enderby in the county of Leicester. Deed recites a previous grant of the
               manor to his brother sir George Hastings for <date when="2000">2000</date> years, at
               an annual rent of .22. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 7</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> List (on paper) of deeds, &amp;c. relating to the rectory of Enderby. Ch.8. FOXTON.
               Will of Robert Sprigge of Foxton, co. Leicester, dated 26 November, <date when="1619"
                  >1619</date>. Probate dated 27 March, <date when="1620">1620</date>. <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 9</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Indenture made i October, <date>22 Chas. II</date>, by which Thomas Sprigge of
               Foxton, in consideration of the receipt of 55., sells unto* George Grene and
               Theophilius Grene, a messuage, close, and homestead, lying in Foxton, in the co. of
               Leicester, for a term of four months. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 10</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Exemplification of a recovery inrolled at Westminster, Michaelmas, <date>22 Chas.
                  II</date> (roll 60), between Theodore Grene and Edward Chapman, <pb n="144"/>
               plaintiffs, and George Grene and Theophilus Grene, gentlemen, defendants, concerning
               one messuage, 2 gardens, 10 acres of land, one acre of meadow, 8 acres of pasture and
               common of pasture for all cattle and appurtenances in Foxton. Dated at Westminster,
               28 Nov., 22 Chas. II. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 11</bibl>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> GREENBOROUGH. William, son of Robert de Harecurt, grants to William Part and his
               heirs, for his homage and service, the bodies of Geoffrey the carter and of Robert
               Batele, his natives, with all their belongings, together with half a virgate of land
               which the said Geoffrey and Robert hold in the village of Greneberue ; paying
               annually for the same one pair of white gloves of the price of one penny at Easter
               for all secular services and demands, (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280"
                  precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 17</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> HINKLEY. Exemplification of a grant of a yearly pension of 5 6s. Sd. to the parish
               priest of Hynkeley, out of the late possessions of the dissolved monastery of
               Mountegrace, co. of York. Dated at Westminster, 12 Feb., <date>36 Hen. VIII</date>.
               [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 12</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> LEICESTER,. Richard Glen of Leicester grants to Richard de Rothewell of Leicester
               one messuage with appurtenances in Belegravegate, Leicester, situated between a
               tenement of Roger de Gretham and the tenement of Richard de Glen, paying annually
               after the expiration of 1 6 years ios. Dated at Leicester, 2 Feb., <date>17 Ed.
                  II</date>; witness, John Alsis, mayor of Leicester. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  13</bibl>, </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Articles of enquiry concerning lands, &amp;c. in the county of 'Leicester held by
               those who had taken part in the late disturbances (turbatio regni) against the king.
                  (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 14</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Roger de Sileby and Leticia his wife (daughter of William the smith) grant to
               Alexander Persun for 295. of silver in hand paid, a certain piece of land in
               Leicester near the north gate. Dated the day of St. Agatha the virgin, <date
                  when="1266">1266</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 15</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> LEICESTER (Abbey of St. Mary Pre> Indenture made 1 6 August, <date>28 Hen.
                  VIII</date>, by which John, the abbot, and convent of the monastery of our Lady in
               the medows of Leicester, grant to Robert Grenwod of Sigresham a messuage and 2 yards
               of land in the town and fields of Sigresham for 31 years at an annual rent of 305.
               4^. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 16</bibl> .</p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> MOWESLEY. Roger, son of William Brabazon of Mowesley, grants to John Oudeby of
               Stokedrie, co. Rutland, the whole of his lordship in the village of Mowesley,
               together with 125. annual rent and the homage and services of the freemen for their
               lands and tenements held of him. Also attached to this charter is a schedule of the
               chief rents of Mowesley payable at Michaelmas. Dated at Mowesley, 4 April, 19 Ed.
               III. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 18</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> PACKINGTON, co. LEICESTER, and MEASHAM, co. DERBY. Exemplification of a decree
               between Henry, earl of <pb n="145"/> Huntingdon, plaintiff, and Thomas Pestell,
               clerk, defendant, concerning the claim to the tythes of the parsonages of Packington
               on the heath, and Mesam, in the counties of Leicester and Derby. Dated at
               Westminster, 29 January, <date>4 Chas. I</date>. [JFiA seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark"
                  >Ch. 19</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> SADYNGTON. Condition of a grant from sir William de Botereaux, kt., to John Cook of
               Leicester, of an animal rent charge of 6 upon his lands and tenements in Hardwick,
               co. Bucks, during the life of Elizabeth, wife of the said sir William, namely that if
               the said Elizabeth does not recover her dower out of the manor of Sadyngton, held by
               the said John, then the said grant of annuity shall become void. Dated the Friday on
               the feast of the translation of St. Thomas the martyr, <date>47 Ed. III</date>. [With
               seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 20</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> STERMESWORTH. Sir Richard de Egebaston, kt., in Swyneford, grants to John his son
               and heir for ever, a certain messuage in Stermesworth which William, son of Juliana
               de Neubolde, holds for the term of his life. Dated at Stermesworth the Sunday next
               after the feast of Easter, 1 <date>3 Ed. III</date>. [ With seal] <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 21</bibl> .</p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> STOUGHTON, PAKYNGTON, BILLESDEN, ASHBY de la ZOUCH, &amp;c. Letters patent of K. Ed.
               VI, granting to Francis, earl of Huntingdon, and Thomas Hasylwood, the rectories of
               Stoughton, Pakyngton with its vicarage, Billesden with its vicarage, Ashby de la
               Zouch and its vicarage, together with lands, houses, &amp;c. in Stoughton, Pakyngton,
               Snybston, Billesden, Asshby de la Zouch, Colwarby, Blakefbrdeby, Alton, and Assheby,
               in the county of Leicester ; also the chantry of the B.V.M. of Aller, co. Somerset ;
               also 4 messuages, &amp;c. in Frisbye, co. Leicester, to hold the game to their use
               for ever. Dated at Westminster, 2 Jan., 3 of his reign. [ With seal] <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 22</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> STRETTON (Little). Robert of the Hall of Little Stretton grants to his lord, sir
               Richard de Harecourt, one piece of land 100 ft. long and 60 ft. wide in Little
               Stretton ; to hold the same according to the custom of the manor, paying 455. of
               silver beforehand. Dated on the feast of St. Botulph, <date>18 Ed. I</date>. <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 23</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> STRETTON (Great). Robert Sauveye of Great Stretton grants to sir Richard de
               Harecourt, lord of Boseworthe, the half of a house and the whole of a toft which he
               had of the gift of Peter, son of Adam le Fraunceys in Great Stretton. (<date
                  notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 24</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Yvo Eyriby of Great Stretton grants to sir Richard de Harecourt, lord of Boseworth,
               the half of a house and the whole of a toft which he had of the gift of Peter, son of
               Adam le Franceys, in Great Stretton. (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280"
                  precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 25</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> WYTHCOK alias WYTHYCOK, &amp;c. Letters patent of King Hen. VIII ; dated at
               Westminster, 18 July, 36 of his reign, granting <pb n="146"/> to John Beaumont, esq.,
               in consideration of the payment of <date when="1040">1040</date> 45. 2d., certain
               lands, &amp;c. in "Wythcok alias Wythycok, co. Leicester, part of the late dissolved
               monastery of Launde in the same county, together with several other properties. [With
               seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 26</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> LEICESTER,. Proceedings in a matrimonial cause in the church of St. Martin's,
               Leicester, before Robert, the official of the archdeacon of Leicester, between Emma,
               daughter of William de Swineford of the one part, and Thomas de Limstil of the other
               part, <date when="1295">1295</date>-6. Leicester Rolls, i.</p>
         </div></div>
         
         <div type="county"><head>LINCOLNSHIRE</head>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> . CASTHOBP. Deed by which the testimony of Wm. Bretan and others is
               perpetuated concerning the manor courts of Casthorp. Dated in the said manor of
               Casthorp upon St. John, evangelist, in Cristamasse weke, <date when="1470"
                  >1470</date>. [With seals.'] Lincolnshire Charters, i. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p>FEBIBY. Hugh, son of Ralph, grants to Robert de Salceto with Beatrice his daughter,
               the whole of his land of Feryby, to hold the same to him and his heirs of the body of
               his said daughter, (c. 1230.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 2</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> GBETFOBD. Presentation by King James I, of Henry Carpenter, M.A., to the rectory of
               Gretford. Dated 4 September, n of his reign. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 4</bibl>.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> GBIMSBY. Adam, son of John le Carter of Grimesby, grants to Gilbert, son of William
               Rayn, two selions of arable land in the field of the village of Grimesby, paying
               annually one halfpenny for all demands. (<date when="1270" precision="low">c.
                  1270</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 5</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> HAXAY (Church of All Saints at). Thomas Long of Craslund grants to the church of All
               Saints, Haxay, in frankalmoigne, one selion (of land) in the fields of Craslund.
                  (<date when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  6</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> COTOM. Roger de Singilton grants to the Knights Hospitallers of St. John of
               Jerusalem, in frankalmoigne, a certain part of land in Cotom, namely, seven acres,
               and one piece upon which a certain barn is able to be built, (<date notBefore="1260"
                  notAfter="1270" precision="low">c. 1260-70</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  6</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p>* EBESBY, TOYNTON, FELETBY, BATHEBY, BELTESFOBD, WYSSYNGTON, and OBBEBY, co. LINCOLN
               ; and EGGESFELD, SHATEGBAVE, WHETACBE, GBAUNTHAUBOYS, and WALCOTES, co. NORFOLK.
               John, sou of sir John de Wylughby, kt., quit-claims to dame Joan de Wylughby, lady
               d'Eresby his mother, all right of action for waste in those lands she holds in dower
               in the counties of Lincoln and Norfolk for the term of her life. Dated at Eresby, 16
               April, <date>24 Ed. II</date>P. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 14</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> INGELBY (North). Indenture witnessing that sir John Gra, kt., and Thomasyn his wife,
               have let to farm to sir Gerveis Clyfton, <pb n="147"/> knight, their manor of North
               Ingelby in the county of Lincoln, with a close called the park, also the gardens,
               orchards, houses, &amp;c., courts, rents, and services, for 13 years, at an annual
               rent of jio. Dated at North Ingelby the 2ist day of March, <date>32 Hen. VI</date>.
                  <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 7</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> LEAKE. Writ from Oliver Cromwell to the Dike-reeves of the town of Leake to collect
               35 15$. 6d. assessed upon their town for the erection of a ' goale ' according to an
               order of the commissioners of sewers. Dated 8 March, <date when="1653">1653</date>.
                  <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 8</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> KINGEBBY. Deed made 24 May, <date>38 Elizabeth</date>, acknowledging that Henry
               Disney, of Kingerby, esq., has received the day above written Xiooo, of ladie Jane
               Pickeringe, widow, late wife of rt. hon. sir John Pickeringe, kt., according to a
               clause in a certain deed bearing date 12 Dec., in the said 38th year of Q. Elizabeth.
                  <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 9</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> KNIVETON. Robert de Acastra, for the health of his soul and Hauwise his wife, grants
               to the church of the Blessed Mary of Nebo and the canons there, in frankalmoigne, 2
               acres of arable land in the fields of Kniveton. (<date when="1230" precision="low">c.
                  1230</date>.) Ch. n.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> OBMESBY (Priory of). Charter (indented) by which the prior and <orgName>convent of Ormesby</orgName>
               agree with the prior of Rovenham, concerning the gift of certain lands in Rovenham by
               Clement Flandrers to the said priory of Ormesby in <date when="1243">1243</date>,
               viz. that the said prior of Rovenham quit-claims all right in the said lands, and the
               prior and <orgName>convent of Ormesby</orgName> agree to pay to the prior of Rovenham annually zd. [With
               seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 12</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> STANESFELD. Agatha de la Kersunera and Thomas her Bon grant to Thomas de Muleton the
               whole of the land which they hold of the fee of Peter de Nerford in Stanesfeld at an
               annual rent of 3** (<date when="1200" precision="low">c. 1200</date>.) [With seal]
                  <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 13</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> TEDILBY. Letters patent of K. James I granting to Edward South e, gent., an annuity
               of 203. from the manor of Tedilby alias Bayons, together with the custody of the
               lands and heirship of Gabriel Talbott, son of Brian Talbott, deceased. Dated at
               Westminster, 12 Feb., <date>5 Jas. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 16</bibl>.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> TOINTON. John, son of William the clerk of Toynton, quitclaims to John de Staverton
               all right to \\d. annual rent for 2 acres of land lying in the field called ' le
               Worse/ Dated at Toynton the Tuesday before the feast of the Annunciation B.V.M., 28
               Ed. L <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 17</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Alice, formerly wife of John the clerk of Great Toyntone, quit-claims to Ralph Ware
               of Toyntone all her right, by the name of dowry, in houses, lands, &amp;c., in
               Toyntone. Dated at Toyntone the day of the Annunciation B.Y.M., <date>9 Ed.
               II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 15</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> WILLINGHAM. Writ of Queen Elizabeth to the sheriff of Lincoln commanding him to
               distrain Thomas Compton for the manor of Willingham, and of divers messuages, &amp;c.
               in Potter, Hauworth, L 2 <pb n="148"/> Hadington, Thorpe, More, and Wilby, held of
               the Queen as of her duchy of Lancaster by kts. service, and for which Ambrose Sutton
               made fealty 17 Nov., <date>5 Ed. VI</date>, and to show by what title he holds the
               same. Dated at Westminster, 16 May, <date>22 Eliz.</date>
               <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 18</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> WITH AM. Petition of Anthony Thomas and John Worsoppe, esqrs., for themselves and
               others, to the House of Commons, for relief against the inhabitants adjacent to a
               certain number of acres of the Fens, drained, &amp;c. by the ancestors of the said
               petitioners, who have thrown down the buildings and inclosures, destroyed the corn,
               and driven away the cattle, (<date when="1650" precision="low">c. 1650</date>.) <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 10</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> LINCOLN (Diocese of). Return of the bishop of Lincoln, collector of the roths,
               &amp;c. for the diocese of Lincoln for the year ending <date when="1663">1663</date>.
               (Soil of two membranes.) Lincolnshire Rolls, i.</p>
         </div></div>
         
         <!-- appendix -->
         <div type="charter">
            <p> GLOUCESTEKSHIRE. GLOUCESTER (St. Peter's Abbey). Confirmation of Privileges of St.
               Peter's monastery at Gloucester by Burghred, king of Mercia, A.D. 862. <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 20</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> TEWKESBURY. Richard Whytehed, brother of John Whytehed of Worcester, vicar of
               Fayreford, quit-claims to William Tayllor of Tewkesbury the whole of half a burgage
               in Tewkesbury. Dated at Tewkesbury the Thursday next after the feast of the
               Exaltation of the Holy Cross, <date>8 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  21</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> THORNBURY. Confirmation by Walter, bp. of Worcester, of the appropriation of the
               church of Thornbury, Worcester diocese, to the abbot and convent of B. V. M. of
               Theokesbur'. Dated at Lamhuth, sth Nones of May, <date when="1316">1316</date>. <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 22</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> HAMPSHIRE. OKE. Grant of lands &amp;c. in Oke, which the donor, conjointly with John
               Gurdon, acquired by the gift and feoffinent of Walter, son and heir of Thomas Spolas,
               of Winchestre. Dated at Oke, 16 March, <date>17 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                  >Ch. 23</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p>
               <pb n="647"/> HEREFORDSHIRE. HEREFOEDSHIEE. LEDBUBY. Daniel Price, S.T.P., the dean,
               and the chapter of Hereford, present Francis Kerie, S.T.P., to the hospital of St.
               Catharine in the town of Ledburie, vacant by the death of Thomas Thornton, S.T.P.
               Dated 27 April, <date when="1629">1629</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 24</bibl>.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> Presentation of Francis Kerie, S.T.P., to the hospital of St. Catherine in Ledburie,
               on the death of Thomas Thornton, S.T.P., by Daniel Price, the dean, and chapter of
               Hereford. Dated 27 April, <date when="1629">1629</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  25</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> WELLINGTON. Letters patent of King Charles II, dated at Westminster 9 July, 1 2th of
               his reign, granting the prebend of Wellington in the church of Hereford to George
               Benson, clerk. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 26</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> HEKTFORDSHIKE. WABE. Counterpart of an indenture made 23 June, 18 Q. Elizabeth,
               reciting a deed of feoffment made by the Lady Katherine, Countess of Huntingdon, late
               wife of Francis earl of Huntingdon, by which the lordship and manor of Ware was
               granted to Thomas Fanshaw under certain conditions, and by the present indenture it
               is again recited that the said Thomas is seized as of fee of the park called Ware
               park, subject to the payment of four score pounds annually to the said Lady
               Katherine, her heirs, &amp;c., under the former indenture. [With seal and signature
               of Thos. Fanshaw.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 27</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> KENT. ISELHAM (Deanery of). Letter of William, bishop of Rochester, to the dean of
               Iselham, for the collection of a subsidy of \d. in the pound in the said deanery.
               Dated at Trottesclyne, 31 Oct., <date when="1395">1395</date>. On the back of the
               document is an early English verse entitled ' Hec est carta Dei.' <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 28</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> NONNINGTON. William, son of John Cundy of Sandwich, and Stephen, son of Andrew Yook,
               grant to John de Ketynton four acres of land at Ketynton, in the parish of Nonynton,
               and also 4 1 ac. 3 r. and 6 ft. of land, with the half of a certain place called Par-
               sonyestoun at Ketynton aforesaid. Dated at Nouynton, 20 Feb., <date>33 Ed.
                  III</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 29</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> PRIORY OF TUNBRIDGE. ELDYNG. Richard . . le of Eldynge grants to Roger de Frendes-
               bery, rector of Stradesele, Norwich diocese, one croft in the parish of Eldynge.
               Dated at Stradesele the Wednesday next after the feast of St. Edward, King, 4 Ed.
               III. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 30</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p>
               <pb n="648"/> KENT. TUDELEY. Mathew de Creuequer grants to Walter, son of Benjamin de
               Chytercrofte, the whole of his meadow in the parish of Theudelu, after the death of
               Hamon de Crewequer. (<date notBefore="1260" notAfter="1270" precision="low">c.
                  1260-70</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 31-</bibl>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> WESTWELL. A confirmation by William and Simon, archbishops of Canterbury
               successively, of the agreement between John Barler, rector of Westwell, and John
               Frebody, rector of Bocton Alulph, concerning the tithes of the hamlets of Chilberton,
               Shotyngdon, and Wyke. Dated at Lambeth, 4 Kl. Nov., <date when="1376">1376</date>.
               [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 32</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p> LEICESTEKSHIRE. BERMETON, &amp;o. John, son of the King, cons^ble of England,
               recites the grant by letters patent to Thomas Boteler of all his lands, tenements,
               &amp;c. in the counties of Leicester and Durham, in the villages of Bermeton,
               Bisshopton, Newebyggyng, little Staynton, and Hedley ; by this charter he appoints
               Sir William Fulthorp, kt., and John Nonwyk, esq., his attorneys to deliver seisin of
               the same. Dated at Werkeworth, 14 May, <date>i Hen. V</date>. [With seal] <bibl
                  type="shelfmark">Ch. 33</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="county"><head>LINCOLNSHIRE</head> <div type="charter">
            <p> . INGELBY, &amp;c. Thomas Spenser of Somercotes, William Mailore of
               York, John Craven of York, and Robert Luflese, vicar of Bukmynstyre, quit-claim to
               John Talbot, earl of Shrewsbury, and Thomas de Dacre, all their right in the villages
               of Salfletby and Somercotes, the church of Basyngham, with the free chapel of
               Ingelby. Dated at Ingelby, 3 April, <date>27 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                  >Ch. 34</bibl>. </p>
         </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LINCOLN. Presentation of James Brooke, clerke, to the prebend of South Scarle in the
                  church of St. Mary, Lincoln, vacant by the cession of Hamlet Marshall. [Mutilated]
                  <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 35</bibl>. </p>
            </div></div>
         
         <div type="county">
            <head>KENT. </head>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ICKHAM. Rent roll of John de Kent <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MITPORD (Hundred of). Account of Richard Welby, bailiff of Thomas de Arundel, bp.
                  of Ely, for the hundred of Mitford, from Mich., <date>2 Rich. II</date>, to the
                  same feast, 3 Rich. II. Norfolk <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 99</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
