<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="county">
            <head>YORKSHIRE</head>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> . ABEBFOBD. Elesya de Lascy confirms the grant which Andrew le Trameyre made to
                  John Sampson of York of the mill of Aberford. Dated at Bowelle on the octave of
                  the Epiphany, <date when="1274">1274</date>. Yorkshire Charters, 109. ALBEBSTON.
                  Sir Ed. Hastings, kt., lord de Hastings, (after reciting the grant of William,
                  lord Hastings, his father, for the foundation of &amp; chantry within St.
                  George's, Windsor, of an annual rent charge of 20, which is only valued at ,18
                  5.9.), grants to Geoffrey Symeon, <pb n="601"/> the dean, and the canons of St.
                  George's, Windsor, a rent-charge of 355. on his manor of Alberston, Yorkshire, to
                  complete the said sum of 20 granted by his father. Dated 15 December, <date>20
                     Hen. VII</date>. [Seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 331</bibl>. ALDEBURGH,
                  BEFFORTH, &amp;c. "William cle Dryffeld, draper, of Beverlac', and Alice his wife
                  grant to John Driffeld, their son and heir, all the lands and tenements, rents,
                  &amp;c. which they have in villages and territory of Aldeburgh, Befforth, Asnall,
                  Gemlyng, Ulrom, Emeslay, Foston, and elsewhere. Dated 25 Sept. <date when="1413"
                     >1413</date>, and <date>13 Henry IV</date>. [With seals.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 338</bibl>. ALLERTON. Thomas le Chamberlain of
                  Potterneuton grants to William, son of Thomas of Kylingbek and Dionisia his wife,
                  one toft and one acre of land in Allerton. Dated at Potterneuton the Monday next
                  before the Annunciation of the Virgin, <date>16 Ed. II</date>. Ch. no. William,
                  son of Nicholas de Alretun, grants to John, son of Adam of Cukeric, and his heirs,
                  one bovate of land in Alretun in free marriage with Silke his daughter. (<date
                     notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.) [With
                  seal.] Ch. in. Letia, formerly wife of Alan servant of Neuton, grants and
                  quitclaims to Richard, son of Elye, at the wood of Alverton, all right and claim
                  which she has in land and a tenement which Alan her husband sold to Richard the
                  Forester del Runhay. (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c.
                     1270-80</date>.) [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 198</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ALLERTON (Hospital of St. James at). Philip, bp. of Durham, grants to the
                  hospital of St. James, near Alverton, in frankalmoigne, the whole of the half of
                  his mills of Houhton, Reningt and Kolleforde, &amp;c. [<date when="1195"
                     >1195</date>-<date when="1208">1208</date>.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     86</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Philip de Collevill grants to the hospital of St. James, near Alverton, two acres
                  of land in Dritdale. (<date notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low">c.
                     1230-40</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 87</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, son of Adam de Alverton, grants to the hospital of St. James of Alverton,
                  in frankalmoigne, two parts of a toft. (<date notBefore="1250" notAfter="1260"
                     precision="low">c. 1250-60</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 88</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Nicholas de la Lounde remits and quit-claims to the hospital of Alverton all
                  right in a common of fishpond near Thorneton. <date notAfter="1310" notBefore="1290" precision="medium">(c. 1300.)</date> <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 89</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Nicholas de Lound of . utton in the Bems .... grants to .... Brumpton, master of
                  the hospital of Alverton, and the brethren there, all his claim and right for
                  actions, &amp;c Dated <date>13 ....</date> [Mutilated] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 90</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sir John Everyngham, kt., and Katherine his wife and others grant to Robert
                  Symson, master of the hospital of St. James, near Alverton, Yorkshire, a certain
                  annual rent of 3 from the lordship of Thornton. Dated 10 October, <date>8 Hen.
                     VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 91</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="602"/> ALLERTON (North). Grant from James, the prior of the Carmelite
                  friers, to Thomas Gayneiig and Agnes his wife, of participation in the spiritual
                  benefits of the convent. Dated at North Alverton, <date when="1487">1487</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 91*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> APPLEBY. Receipt given by Thomas Wattson to Mr. Wm. Trigge for the purchase of a
                  messuage in Eppleby, alias Appleby, viz. 18 13s. 40*. due to the contractors for
                  impropriations and chauntries. Dated 25 November, <date when="1613">1613</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 112</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ARDISLAWE (West). Indenture made 25 March, <date>12 Charles I</date>, by which
                  Robert Greenwood, in consideration of a sum of 10 in hand paid, bargains and sells
                  to Robert Casson the remainder of a lease granted by John, lord Savile, of certain
                  lands called Mooredoles in West Ardislawe, co. York. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     113</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ATON. William Albus, son of Richard de Aton, grants to John, son of William of
                  Aton, two bovates of land in the territory of Aton. (<date notBefore="1200"
                     notAfter="1210" precision="low">c. 1200-10</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     114</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Adthwic, son of Sibline, grants to sir Gilbert de Atun the whole of
                  his land in Atun. (<date notBefore="1200" notAfter="1210" precision="low">c.
                     1200-10</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 115</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Gilbert de Atun grants to Robert, son of Robert, son of Ckar, one bovate of land
                  in the territory of Atun, with a toft and croft which John the shepherd held of
                  William his father, (<date notBefore="1210" notAfter="1220" precision="low">c.
                     1210-20</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 116</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>. William, son of Robert de Atun, grants to Gilbert de Atun and to his heirs, one
                  bovate of land in the territory of Atun. (<date notBefore="1210" notAfter="1220"
                     precision="low">c. 1210-20</date>.) Ch.ii^j. Convention between sir John,
                  brother of sir Gilbert de Aton, and William Albus, that the said William demises
                  to the said John one bovate of land in the territory of Aton. Dated Easter, <date
                     when="1223">1223</date>. [ With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 118</bibl>
                  .</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert de Gousel grants to Martin, son of Ralph the deacon, of Aton, and his
                  heirs, a certain part of his toft in Aton. Dated April Qth, <date when="1259"
                     >1259</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 119</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, son of Hervey de Aton, grants to Thomas, son of William Daudry of Aton,
                  for a certain sum of money in hand paid, because of his urgent necessity, the
                  breadth of one rood of meadow in the meadow of Aton. (<date notBefore="1210"
                     notAfter="1220" precision="low">c. 1210-20</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     120</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, son of Hervey de Aton, grants to Thomas Daudry of Aton a certain ridge of
                  land in the territory of Aton. Dated Pentecost, <date when="1260">1260</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 121</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of Gilbert de Aton, grants to Adam, son of William le Beaugraunt,
                  one toft with buildings, 3 acres and one rood of arable land, and one rood of
                  meadow in the village of Aton. (<date notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240"
                     precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 122</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="603"/> Roger, the clerk of Aton, grants to Alice his daughter and her
                  heirs, one toft in the village of Aton and one ridge of land there, (<date
                     notBefore="1240" notAfter="1250" precision="low">c. 1240-50</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 123</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Christiana, daughter of Ralph, son of Letitia de Aton, grants to Matilda, her
                  daughter, 35. of annual rent in Aton, subject to a certain condition in the event
                  of William, son of Richard le Palmer, her uncle, returning from France at any
                  future time. (<date notBefore="1250" notAfter="1260" precision="low">c.
                     1250-60</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 124</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Walter, the porter of Aton, grants to William Haralde of Aton the whole of his
                  land which he bought of Emma, daughter of Roger de Cnaresburg (Knaresborugh), in
                  the village of Aton. Dated the Sunday after the Sunday in which is sung ' Quasi
                  modo geniti? <date when="1285">1285</date>. [ With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 125</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Adam, son of William Carman, of Aton, grants and quit-claims to Simon, son of sir
                  William de Aton, kt, all right in one toft, 2 messuages, with a curtilage
                  adjoining in Aton, near Pikerynglyth. Dated at Aton, 4 Feb., <date>4 Ed.
                     III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 126</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BABDEWY. John, son of William de Celar' of Athelyngflete, remits and quit-claims
                  to sir Gilbert de Aton, lord of Bardewy, all his right in a messuage lying upon
                  the bank of the Ouse, in the fee of Bardewy. Dated at Bardewy the Monday next
                  before the feast of St. Mark the evangelist, <date>19 Ed. II</date>. [With seal.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 126*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BABMBY upon DUN. Inventory of the household goods of William Rydlyngton of Barmby
                  upon Doune, praysed after his -death, 7 November, <date when="1540">1540</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 127*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BATLEY. Deposition of Thomas Smalwood of Topliffe, late minister of Batley, co.
                  York, to the information of sir Jefferie Palmer, kt,, attorney-general. Sworn at
                  Leeds, 9 De<date when="1662" precision="low">c. 1662</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 127</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BAYLDON. Thomas de Thornore grants to William de Bayldon and Margaret his wife
                  his manor of Bayldon for their lives, with remainder to Nicholas de Bayldon and
                  Joan his wife and their heirs, &amp;c. Dated at Bayldon on the feast of St.
                  Michael, <date>9 Hen. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 128</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BEPOBD, &amp;c. Margaret, wife of Thomas Northiby of Gymelyn, grants to John de
                  Wartre and Alice his wife all the lands and tenements she holds in fee tallage or
                  fee simple in the villages of Beford, Seton, and Catfosse, also her goods and
                  chattels in Gymelyn or elsewhere in the county of York. Dated at Gymelyn the
                  Thursday next before the feast of the Purification B. V. M., <date>5 Hen.
                     IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 339</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BENTLEY. Adam de Swylington grants to Adam de Poo and Dionisia his wife one
                  messuage and land in Bentley for 20 years, paying annually 6s. Dated at Leeds the
                  Wednesday on the feast of St. Katherine, virgin, <date when="1327">1327</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 128*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="604"/> BBVERLEY. John, son of Philip of London, burgess of Beverley, grants
                  to John de Beverley, clerk, son of Petronilla Lambe, the whole of his edifice in
                  Beverley. (<date notBefore="1240" notAfter="1250" precision="low">c.
                     1240-50</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 129</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BOLTON. Indenture dated 8 May, <date>22 Hen. VIII</date>, by which William
                  Golthropp of Shepley and others demise to Roger Hanson of Derfelde a close with
                  two leys, 9 acres of arable land and one acre of meadow in Bolton. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 130</bibl> .</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BOLTON (Priory of). Alan, son of Richard de Wyntewrthe, quit-claims to the church
                  and canons of St. Mary, Boulton, for a sum of money in hand paid, all right in one
                  acre of land in the fields of Wyntewrthe within the lordship of the aforesaid
                  canons, (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c.
                  1270-80</date>.) [With seal'] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 41</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BOTHEM. John de Burton demises for a term to John Dade of Wakefield the whole of
                  his manor of Bothem for 20 years, paying annually 405. of silver. Dated at
                  Wakefield the Monday after the feast of St. Tiburtius, <date when="1323"
                     >1323</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 131</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BR-ADFIELD. Cecilia, who was the wife of Roger de Westone, remits and quit-claims
                  to Hugh de Bradefeld, clerk, and Mabil his wife, all right in that land which the
                  said Roger de Westone sold to the said Hugh and Mabil. Dated at Bradefeld the
                  Thursday next before the Assumption of B.V. M., <date>18 Ed. I</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 132</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRAMLEY and HEDINGLEY. Letters patent of Queen Elizabeth, dated at Westminster, <date>i
                  April, 34 of her reign</date>, granting to John Savile and Thomas LynchclyfFe a licence
                  of alienation of certain lands in Bramley and Hedingley to Robert Walshe and
                  Robert Crowther. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 328</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRAMLEY. Letters patent of King James I, dated at Westminster, i April, 21 of his
                  reign, granting to Henry Musgrave and Margaret Askwith, widow, a licence of
                  alienation of certain messuages and lands lying in Bramley, to James Gale, sen.,
                  James Gale, jun., Agues Lister, widow, and John Lister her son. [With seal.]
                  ^.-329. BREREHAGE and ECOP. Jordan, son of Stephen de Witton, quit-claims to Alan
                  de Brerehage, all right and claim which Richard, son of Peter his grandfather,
                  held in Brerehage and Ecop, excepting those two bovates of land which Stephen,
                  father of the said Jordan, held of Robert his father in Ecop. (<date
                     notBefore="1210" notAfter="1220" precision="low">c. 1210-20</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 131*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRETT ON (Priory of). G., bishop of Coventry, confirms to the canons of Bretton
                  two parts of the tithes of corn of the lordship of the Lord Ailric of the village
                  of Midelton, with the small tithes of the same lordship, (<date when="1206"
                     precision="low">c. 1206</date>.) [Douce, No. 6g] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     42</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Winteworth, son of Hugh, son of Henry of the same <pb n="605"/>
                  village, grants to God and the monks of St. Mary Magdalen of Bretton, in
                  frankalmoigne, 1 1 acres of land of his demesne in White worth. (<date
                     notBefore="1180" notAfter="1190" precision="low">c. 1180-90</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 43</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Gregory, son of William of Cothewrth, grants to the church of St. Mary Magdalene
                  of Bretton and the monks there, in frankalmoigne, the homage and service of Robert
                  the smith of Wirkesburg for a plot of meadow in Cothewrth. (<date notBefore="1270"
                     notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     44</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Convention between the prior of Monk Bretton of the one part and Robert de
                  Poyngton of Dunstall and John Williamson of the other, by which the said prior
                  grants to farm to Robert and John all their lands, &amp;c. in the village and
                  fields of Dunstall for 30 years, paying annually i6s. Dated at Monk Bretton on the
                  feast of St. John Evang., <date when="1392">1392</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 44*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Writ from K. Henry IV, dated at Westminster <date>loth of his reign</date>, addressed to
                  William Gascoigne and Thomas Tildeslegh, to hear a cause between the prior and
                  convent of Monk Bretton of the one part, and Roger de Preston of Hikilton and
                  William Jonson of Cudworth of the other, concerning common of pasture in Hykylton
                  and Cudworth. [ With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 45</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRIDLINGTON (Priory of). Sentence of the official of the archdeacon of Richmond,
                  concerning the appropriation of the churches of Couton and Grenton to the prior
                  and convent of Bridelington. Dated at York, 2 Kl. Aug., <date when="1319"
                     >1319</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 46</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BRUMPTON. Grant by King Hen. I of certain liberties to Eustace, son of John, in
                  his manor of Brumton, which he holds as of the fee of Roger de Dated at
                  Winchester. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 132*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BURTON (West). Thomas de Ardern, staying in Westburton, grants to sir Adam de
                  Spofford, vicar of Westburton, and sir William his brother, chaplain, the whole of
                  the land which he has of the gift of the dean and chapter of York in the village
                  of Westburton. Dated at Westburton, Ides of February, <date when="1284"
                     >1284</date>. [ With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 133</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BURLEY. Convention (indented) made the year Lodovic [King of France] returned
                  from England [i.e. <date when="1217">1217</date>], on the feast of St. Martin, for
                  a term of 6 years, by which Isabella des Rodiz and William her son demise to
                  Ralph, son of Bernard, and Jordan, son of Warine, three bovates of land in Burley,
                  which Owain held, for i is. of silver, which the said Ralph and Jordan gave for a
                  recognition, and a rent of 8s. per annum. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 133*</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BYLAND, alias BELLA-LANDA (Abbey of). Grant from King Hen. Ill to the abbot and
                  convent of Byland confirming their privileges. Dated at Windles (Windsor), 20
                  Feb., 31 of his reign. [Douce, No. 25.] Ch. i. <pb n="606"/> CALVERLEY. John
                  Symson of Pudsey, son and heir of William Symson, grants and quit-claims to Robert
                  Symson his brother all his messuages, lands, and tenements, within the parish of
                  Calverley. Dated at Pudsey, 22 Oct., <date>4 Hen. VIII</date>. [With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 134</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CAMPSALL. Cecilia, daughter of John the cook, confirms to Hugh, son of Agnes, one
                  plot of 32 feet in breadth and 88 ft. in length, in a toft which John the cook
                  formerly held in the village of Cannsall. (<date notBefore="1240" notAfter="1250"
                     precision="low">c. 1240-50</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 135</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CARLTON. Henry de Lamel grants to Richard de Normanville the whole of the land he
                  has in Duniscroft, viz. those two ridges which lie to the east of the way called
                  Kirkegate between Carleton and Sedling. (<date notBefore="1260" notAfter="1270"
                     precision="low">c. 1260-70</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 136</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> CROSSLAND (North), near HALIFAX. Adam de Linchweyt grants to the Knights
                  Templars, in frankalmoigne, the whole of his herbage in the village of North
                  Crossland, with a third part of his land, &amp;c. in the same village, (<date
                     notBefore="1240" notAfter="1250" precision="low">c. 1240-50</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 96</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> DARTHYNGTON and WENTBRIDGE. Sir Brian Sanforth, kt., appoints Robert Derkyn and
                  Richard Thwayt his attorneys to deliver seisin to John Secroft of "Wentbrigg and
                  Margaret his wife of all those lands in Wentbrigg and Darthyngton. Dated 12 Oct.,
                     <date>23 Hen. VI</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 142</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> DRAX (Priory of). Henry de Stainegreve pledges himself that the 4 acres of land
                  which Ralph, son of Richard ad Wei his man, demised to the prior and convent of
                  Drax for eight years, at Ss. rent, shall be enjoyed by them for that time. (<date
                     notBefore="1190" notAfter="1200" precision="low">c. 1190-1200</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 47</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry de Stainegrive grants to William, son of Nicholas Russel, and Richard his
                  brother, licence to sell or pledge to the church of St. Nicholas of Drax, in
                  frankalmoigne, the whole of his land in Neuhay. (<date notBefore="1190"
                     notAfter="1200" precision="low">c. 1190-1200</date>.) [With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 48</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The prior and canons of Torkesey grant to the prior and canons of Drax certain
                  land and a mill, paying annually to the lords of the fee i os. (<date
                     notBefore="1200" notAfter="1210" precision="low">c. 1200-10</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 49</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Martin, son of Ingeram de (' Nova haia ') Newhay, with the counsel of Agnes his
                  wife and Richard his heir, grants to the church of St. Nicholas of Drax, three
                  acres of land in Neuhay, (<date notBefore="1200" notAfter="1210" precision="low"
                     >c. 1200-10</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 50</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de la Pomeray confirms to John, son of Nicholas de Osgotby, a certain assart
                  in Osgotby called 'Arnebrandriding,' also I2d. annual rent out of the said assart
                  and one ridge of land near the way leading to Osgotby, paying annually to the
                  prior of Drax at the altar of St. Nicholas one rose for all services. (c, <date
                     when="1270">1270</date>-80.) [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 51</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Jordan, son of John de la Pomeraye, grants to John, son of Nicholas de Osgoteby,
                  and his heirs, a certain assart in Osgoteby which is called ' Brenbrandridding ' ;
                  also he grants to the said John 1 2 pence rents, to hold of the prior and convent
                  of Drax by the service of one rose annually. (<date notBefore="1270"
                     notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 332</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="607"/> DUFFELD. Alan Wastehose grants to Peter, son of Godfrey de Roxtun,
                  one bovate of land in Duffeld. (<date notBefore="1200" notAfter="1210"
                     precision="low">c. 1200-10</date>.) [Seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     137</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ECCOP and ADELE. Roger Musteile grants to William de Wytheton ' tofhusu/ viz. one
                  carucate of land with the common of Ecob, within and without the field to the mill
                  of Adele. (<date notBefore="1210" notAfter="1220" precision="low">c.
                     1210-20</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 137*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> EMLEY, BIBTON, and THOBNTLAY. Richard Dronsfeld, parson of Helon, Richard de
                  Staynton, chaplain, William Lyle, and William Pelle, chaplain, grant to John, son
                  of Lawrence de Haynton of Lepton, and Cicely his wife, all lands, &amp;c. in
                  Birton, Emlay, and Thorntlay. Dated at Thorntlay, 10 July, <date>7 Hen. IV</date>.
                  [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 138</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ENESBY. Roger de Fulthorp grants to Raulyn de Eure all his lands and tenements in
                  the village of Enesby in Clyveland. Dated at Tunstall on St. Michael's day, <date>46 Ed. III</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 139</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ESTBESWIKE. Thomas de Langefeld grants to sir Brian de Thomhill, rector of
                  Bedall, the half of the land and meadow in the village of Estbeswike which William
                  de Langefeld his father held. Dated at Thornhill on <date when="1311-11-11">St. Martin's day in the
                  winter, 1300</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 140</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> FABNLAY and WHTTDEHUSE. Roger de Notton grants to Baldwin the Teuton the whole of
                  his land of Farnlay and Woodhouse within and without the village, also the homage
                  and service of William de Buelay and his heirs. For this gift the said Baldwin and
                  Margaret his wife quit-claim to the said Roger all right in land at Silkeston
                  which she had by the name of dowry of Gilbert de Notton his father and formerly
                  her husband. (<date notBefore="1220" notAfter="1230" precision="low">c.
                     1220-30</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 141</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> FOSTON, &amp;c. Indenture made between Peter Hykson of London of the one part,
                  and William Holburne of Beuerlec of the other, being an agreement for the safe
                  custody and delivery to the right heirs of certain evidences concerning lands,
                  &amp;c. in Foston, Gemelyng, Befforth, and elsewhere in the county of York. Dated
                  4 March, <date>13 Hen. IV</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     340</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> FOUNTAIN'S (ABBEY). Martin Birkhed of Cotyngham and John West of Beiston, for a
                  sum of 54 45. 40?., sell to John Bekwith a messuage and two closes of land in
                  Pathlobrigge, co. York, part of the monastery of Fountains. Dated 5 April, <date>4 Q.
                  Eliz.</date> <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 29*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Composition between the church of Fountains and the church of Messaham concerning
                  certain tithes of land called Aldeburch. (<date notBefore="1150" notAfter="1160"
                     precision="low">c. 1150-60</date>.) [With seal] [Douce, No. 5.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 30</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GEMBLING-. Roger Flex, Stephen Bernacle, William de Sauton, and William Gyliott,
                  chaplain, grant to John de Olburn of Gemlyng one messuage with a croft and one
                  bovate of land in the village and fields of Gemlyng which they had by the
                  feoifment of the said John de <pb n="608"/> Olburn, and which he first had by the
                  gift of Alice Fyrsmersk, mother of Beatrice, formerly his wife. Dated 3 April,
                     <date when="1413">1413</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 341</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Smyth of Gemelyng surrenders to John Bilton of Beverlaco, chaplain, the
                  whole of his title in one messuage in Gemelyng, situated upon ' le Hallhill/ by
                  virtue of a certain charter made by William Danyek, deceased. Dated at Gemelyng,
                  20 April, <date when="1435">1435</date>, and <date>13 Hen. VI</date>. [With seal.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 342</bibl>. John Warter of Gemling and Richard
                  Karter of the same place grant to John Elis of Gemling and Joan his wife one
                  messuage with a croft and two bovates of land in the village and territory of
                  Gemling which they held by the gift and feoffment of the said John Elis. Dated at
                  Gemling on the feast of St. Mary Magdalen, <date when="1437">1437</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 343</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GISEBURN (Priory). William, son of Walter Ingeram, confirms to the brethren and
                  church of St. Mary of Ghisburn the whole donation of his father in churches,
                  lands, and other things, viz. the churches of Erneclife, Welleburghe, and
                  Heslerton, with lands adjoining, in frankalmoigne. (<date notBefore="1180"
                     notAfter="1190" precision="low">c. 1180-90</date>.) [Douce, No. 70.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 52</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Hugh Malabestia, with the assent of Hugh his heir, grants to God and the church
                  of St. Cuthbert of Marton, in frankalmoigne, 40 acres of land in Marton. (<date
                     notBefore="1190" notAfter="1200" precision="low">c. 1190-1200</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 53</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letter addressed by Pope Celestine (III) to H., precentor of York, and B., prior
                  of Newburgh, to hear and determine a dispute between the canons of Giseburn and
                  the rector of the chapel of Herlessey, belonging to the mother church of
                  Erneclive. [5 Celestine III, i.e. <date when="1196">1196</date>.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 54</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An agreement between the prior and convent of Giseburn and the monks of St.
                  Mary's, York, concerning the tithes of Urvele Sich and certain other lands between
                  Piketon and Apelton, referred by Pope Celestine, by bull dated Lateran, 3 Kl.
                  Aug., 5th year of his pontificate (i.e. <date when="1196">1196</date>), to the
                  abbots of Kirkstall and Suanesbi and R., prior of Malton, for settlement. [With
                  seal.'] [Douce, No. 47.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 29</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Peter Escarbot grants to the church and canons of St. Mary, Giseburn, two bovates
                  of land in the fields of Upplium which Walter Pioneferthing held, with a toft
                  belonging to the same. Dated <date when="1188">1188</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 55</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> L., prior, and the convent of St. Mary of Giseburg, grant to Lucian de Lund that
                  house of Jarum on the north of the church, which Ernisius, the chaplain, gave them
                  in frankalmoigne. <date notBefore="1211" notAfter="1218">(c. 1211-18.)</date> <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 56</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Kelton grants to the church of St. Mary of Giseburn, in frankalmoigne,
                  his church of Lium. (<date notBefore="1200" notAfter="1210" precision="low">c.
                     1200-10</date>.) [Douce, No. 43.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 56*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, the prior, arid the convent of Gi sebum, grant to John de Jarum, tanner,
                  one toft with an edifice in the village of Jarum, paying annually for a light
                  before the image of the Virgin 55. (<date when="1230" precision="low">c.
                     1230</date>.) [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 57</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="609"/> "William, the prior, and the convent of Gysburn, grant to William de
                  Ryvaus, one toft and one croft in the village of Giseburn. (<date notBefore="1290"
                     notAfter="1310" precision="low">c. 1290-1310</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 58</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Walter Faucomberg, lord of the castle of Skekton, ordains John de Levincthon his
                  attorney to give seisin to the prior and convent of Gyseburn, of one acre of land
                  in exchange, lying near the church of Merskby. (<date notBefore="1290"
                     notAfter="1300" precision="low">c. 1290-1300</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 59</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Confirmation of the appropriation of the church of Brydekyrck, Carlisle diocese,
                  to the prior and convent of Giseburn by Ralph, bp. of Carlisle. Dated at
                  Skelderischoth Prid. Non. September, <date when="1287">1287</date>. [ With seal.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 260</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, the prior, and the convent of Giseburn, appoint Walter de -Harton their
                  attorney to receive full seisin of John Grethened, sen., of one messuage and a
                  croft in Marton. Dated at Gyseburn the Wednesday next after Easter, <date
                     when="1343">1343</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 61</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Confirmation by the dean and chapter of Glasgow of an instrument of John, bp. of
                  Glasgow, to the prior and convent of Giseburn, concerning the churches of Anan,
                  Cumbertree, Gretenhou, Kirkpatrick, Loch-Maben, and Rein-patric, in Scotland.
                  Dated at Gla?gow the Sunday next after the feast of the Ascension of our Lord,
                     <date when="1330">1330</date>. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     62</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, the prior of Gyseburn in Clyveland, and the convent of the same, demise to
                  farm to William Rypplyngham, burgess of Kyngeston on Hull, one tenement with a
                  garden lying in the north part of the cemetery of the chapel of St. Trinity, for
                  60 years, at an annual rent of 22s. Dated at Gyseburn, 3 Feb., <date when="1430"
                     >1430</date>. [ With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 63</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Lease from the court of exchequer, dated 10 July, <date>27 Q. Elizabeth</date>, granting to
                  Richard Man a messuage and four bovates of land lying in Ormesby, late the
                  monastery of Uiseburn, for 21 years, at an annual rent of 37*. [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 64</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GRAYSTAN. Richard, son of Adam de Screnam, grants to Robert, son of Hugh, 5 acres
                  of land in his croft in the middle place of Graystan near Godefreyhened. (<date
                     notBefore="1240" notAfter="1250" precision="low">c. 1240-50</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 142*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GRIMESTON. Andrew de Grimeston, clerk, grants to Thomas de Grimeston, clerk, one
                  piece of his close in Grimeston. Witness. Hugh, vicar of Garton, then deau of
                  Holderness. (<date notBefore="1260" notAfter="1270" precision="low">c.
                     1260-70</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 143</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alice and Isabella, daughters and heirs of Richard, son of Alan de Grymeston,
                  confirm and quit-claim to Thomas de Grymeston, clerk, two bovates of land with a
                  toft and croft in the village of Grymeston. (<date notBefore="1260"
                     notAfter="1270" precision="low">c. 1260-70</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     144</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of Ralph de Grymeston, grants to Thomas de Grymeston, <pb n="610"/>
                  YORK. clerk, a close in Grymeston, together with two ridges of meadow, a toft,
                  croft, and two bovates of land in the same village, (<date when="1260"
                     precision="low">c. 1260</date>70.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 145</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> GUTHMUNDHAM. Walter de Roclif of Barethorp, Thomas de Clyf, rector of the church
                  of Guthmundham, and Hugh Colvell, chaplain, grant to Thomas de Grymeston of
                  Guthmundham, one toft with a croft and bovate of land in Guthmundham. Dated at
                  Guthmundham, 29 May, <date>4 Hen. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  146</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HAGHE. Richard, son of Hugh del Haghe, grants to William his son and Anabella,
                  daughter of Adam de Tumbholm, wife of the said William, certain land with a
                  tenement and toft at Haghe. (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 147</bibl>, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HALIFAX. The will of John Schay of Halyfax, dated 4 June, <date>14 Henry
                     VII</date>. Proved 17 June, <date when="1499">1499</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 148</bibl></p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Elizabeth de Halifax, called the daughter of the chaplain, grants ta Elizabeth
                  her daughter the whole of her land in the territory of South- aure. Dated at
                  Halifax the Wednesday next after Palm Sunday, <date when="1337">1337</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 149</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard, the clerk of Halifax, quit-claims to William de Eland, chaplain, two
                  acres of land in ' Suthmerium ' which lie in Stonirode. (<date notBefore="1270"
                     notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 150</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Eland, chaplain, confirms to Amabilla, daughter of William the tailor
                  of Halifax and her children (pueris suis), viz. my foster-children, the whole of
                  that land which he holds in Suthmerium. Witness. Ingelard, then mayor of Halifax.
                     (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.)
                  [With seal] Ch.i^i. John, son of John Eli of Crumwelboym, grants to Richard the
                  clerk of Halifax the whole of his land in the territory of Huverum, viz, that land
                  which lies near the way called Morgate on the north and the water called
                  Halifaxbroych on the west. (<date notBefore="1260" notAfter="1270" precision="low"
                     >c. 1260-70</date>.) [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 152</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HAMSTERLEY and SOUTHBEDEURN. Final concord made at Durham on the feast of St.
                  Matthew, apostle, <date>20 Ric. II</date>, by which Robert Emeryson and Margaret
                  his wife acknowledge the right of sir Ralph de Eure to two messuages, 24 acres of
                  land, and 10 acres of meadow in Southbedburn and Hamsterle. For this the said
                  Ralph gave them a young sparrow-hawk. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 153</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HAUKESWORTH. Isabella Keterynge, lady of Haukesworth, grants to William de
                  Brerehagh de Menston, one messuage and one bovate of land which were formerly
                  William de Heller's. Dated at Haukesworth the Sunday next after the feast of the
                  Assumption of the Virgin, <date when="1384">1384</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 154</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="611"/> HEDON. John Chekym of Hedon grants to William, son of Stephen de
                  Hedon and Agnes his wife, a messuage lying between a messuage of the said William
                  on the west part and a messuage of Henry Brounesby on the east. (<date
                     notBefore="1290" notAfter="1300" precision="low">c. 1290-1300</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 154*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HESLEY. Richard, son of With, grants to Adam de Popelton and his heirs in fee,
                  &amp;c. one carucate of land in Helesseia. <date notAfter="1230" notBefore="1220" precision="medium">(c. 1220-30.)</date> <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 155</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HOLDEN. Letters patent of Queen Elizabeth, dated at Westminster <date>22 May, 27th year
                  of her reign</date>, granting to John Gate of Holden the manor house of Holden, &amp;c.,
                  for the term of years unexpired of a lease made by Richard, bp. of Durham, to the
                  crown of the said premises for 90 years, paying annually 34 os. 8d. [With seal.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 330</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HOLME. John, son of Ralph de Balnia, quit-claims to Ralph his brother the whole
                  of I2d. rent annually paid by the heirs of William, formerly Stote of Holme.
                     (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.)
                  [With seal.'] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 156</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HOTON. Cecilia, relict of Hugh de Driffeld, quit-claims to William called
                  'Schynner' of Hotun all right and claim in a toft and croft in the village of
                  Hoton. (<date notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.)
                  [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 157</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HOTON BUSCELL. Ralph Buscell of Hoton Buscell grants to John de ' Camera' of
                  Hoton one toft in Hotoii. (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low"
                     >c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 158</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HOTON PAYNEL. Adam Paynel of Hoton Paynel grants to Hugh his brother nine acres
                  of land for his homage and service in (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 159</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HOTON RUFS. Alice, relict of Adam de Melling, widow, grants to Sir John de
                  Hodeleston one acre of land in Hoton Rufs., together with the advowson of the
                  hospital of St. Leonard of Teneleshend in the same place, (<date notBefore="1270"
                     notAfter="1289" precision="low">c. 1270-89</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     160</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HOWELL. Bond given by William Woodroif of Howell, co. Ydrk, gentleman, to the
                  dean and canons of Ch. Ch. in 60, for the performance of covenants in a pair of
                  indentures. Dated 8 June, <date>1 Ed. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     160</bibl> *. HOW GRAVE. John de London grants to Robert de Coyngners all lands
                  and tenements which he holds by right of dowry of Joan his wife, formerly wife of
                  Robert de Melmorby, in the village of Hougrave. Dated at Ripon the Friday next
                  before the feast of St. Mary Magdalene, <date when="1339">1339</date>. [With seal]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 161</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> HUGBY and WYTHETON. Ingelram de Munceus grants to Thomas de Screvyn and Agnes his
                  wife certain lands and tenements in Hugby and Wytheton in Wherveldale. (<date
                     notBefore="1280" notAfter="1290" precision="low">c. 1280-90</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 161*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> E r 2 <pb n="612"/> INGLEBY. John de Kirkeby grants to John de Eure and Agues his
                  wife the homage and service of William del How and his heirs for lands and
                  tenements which he holds in Ingelbi near Grenehou, and also the homage and service
                  of the prioress of Basadale for lands, &amp;c. in the same village, and the homage
                  and service of Thomas the son of Walter Lane for lands, &amp;c. in the same, also
                  the homage, &amp;c. of William the son of Juliana, for lands, &amp;c. in the same,
                     (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 162</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Hugh Fouler of Ingelby near Grenehou confirms to John de Eure the homage and
                  service of Adam de Elleredby, son of Robert the clerk of Ingelby, and others, for
                  lands and tenements held of him in Ingelby. Dated at Ingelby the Monday next
                  before the Purification of the Virgin, <date when="1300">1300</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 163</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Hugh le Fouler grants to John de Eure the homage and service of his tenants of
                  Ingelby. Dated at Ingelby the Monday next before the feast of Pentecost, <date
                     when="1301">1301</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 164</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Euer confirms to Robert Snogel of Sayceby arid Ellen his wife one bovate
                  of land in the village of Ingelby. Dated at Ingelby the Thursday next before the
                  feast of St. Gregory, Pope, <date when="1305">1305</date>. [With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 165</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> A charter of obligation of John de Eure to pay to Robert, the son of Robert de
                  Malteby, after thirty years, 10 annually for a messuage and lands in Calde
                  Ingilby, if he should so long hold the same. Dated at Calde Ingilby the Sunday
                  next before the feast of the Assumption, <date>9 Ed. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 166</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sir Marmaduke Constable, kt., releases sir John de Euer, kl, and Thomas Stormy of
                  Dromundby from a bond upon a payment being made of 40 at Westminster to the work
                  of Queen Philippa. Dated at York the Thursday next after the feast of St.
                  Bartholomew, <date>35 Ed. III</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     344</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture witnessing that Robert de Eure grants to Isabella, who was the wife of
                  Thomas Sturmy of Dromonby, two parts of his dovecot of ' Dromondby ' and the right
                  of marriage of John son and heir of the said Thomas Sturmy. Dated at Ingleby the
                  Thursday next before the feast of St. Thomas, <date when="1365">1365</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 167</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert de Kendale and John de Westwik, chaplains, grant to William Dalton of
                  Westawk eland, and John Blakwell, chaplain, all lands and tenements which they had
                  of the gift of William Chaumberleyn, formerly of Stokeslay, in the village of
                  Ingleby. in Clyveland near Grenehowe. Dated at Ingleby 20 Sept. <date when="1426"
                     >1426</date>, <date>5 Hen. VI</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     168</bibl> .</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="613"/> JERUSALEM (Hospital of St. John of). William Painel grants to the
                  hospital, in fraukalmoigne, the whole of his lands and tenements which Robert
                  Dautry held of him in Cugric and elsewhere. (<date notBefore="1180"
                     notAfter="1190" precision="low">c. 1180-90</date> ) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     97</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Gilbert de Notton grants to the hospital one bovate of land of the four bovates
                  called Ravenesacre and two acres called Adbaldehage, in the village of Notton.
                     (<date notBefore="1170" notAfter="1180" precision="low">c. 1170-80</date>.)
                  [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 98</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alexander, son of William, grants to the hospital of St. John two acres of land
                  in the territory of Chivet. which William the son of Ote his father gave them, in
                  frankalmoigne. <date>[Temp. Ric. I.]</date> <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 99</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Gilbert de Chivet grants to the hospital of St. John, in frankalmoigne, three
                  acres of land in the fields of Chivet, and one toft in the same village, &amp;c.
                     (<date notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 100</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Walter de Chyvet, son of Gilbert de Fechiston, for himself and his heirs, is
                  bound to the hospital at Newland, co. York, in Sd. annual rent, from land in
                  Chyvet, which Gilbert his father and Havisia his sister confirmed to the said
                  hospital, in frankalmoigne. (<date when="1240" precision="low">c. 1240</date>50.)
                  Ch. loi. Walter, son of Gilbert de Chivet, confirms to the hospital of St. John,
                  in frankalmoigne, one toft with a croft in the village of Chivet, and land in the
                  territory of Chivet. (<date notBefore="1240" notAfter="1250" precision="low">c.
                     1240-50</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 102</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard de Rihil grants to the hospital, in frankalmoigne, a messuage and land in
                  the village of Crossland. (<date notBefore="1220" notAfter="1230" precision="low"
                     >c. 1220-30</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 103</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Godita, formerly wife of Adam, son of Richer, grants to the hospital, in
                  frankalmoigne, two acres of land in the village of Latherton. (<date
                     notBefore="1240" notAfter="1250" precision="low">c. 1240-50</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 104</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> KELYNGTON. Alexander de Kelyngton, clerk, having been unjustly instituted to the
                  church of Kelyngton, resigns the same to the archbp. of York, and Robert de
                  Meleburn his successor covenants to grant to the said Alexander a portion of the
                  tithes of Kelyngton and Beghale until he is again presented. Dated at Scroby, 6
                  Id. De<date when="1240" precision="low">c. 1240</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     169</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> KILLINGBECK. John, Lord Darcy, grants to Robert Turner of Colton a messuage lying
                  in Killingbeyck. Dated at Selby, the Thursday after the feast of St. Martin,
                     <date>8 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 170</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> KIRKEBY. John de Kyrkeby grants to Sir John de Eure, kt., his lord, all tenements
                  which he has in the village of Kyrkeby in Clyveland. (<date notBefore="1290"
                     notAfter="1300" precision="low">c. 1290-1300</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 171</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Kirkeby, senior, confirms to John de Eure the homage and all services of
                  Adam de Couppeland, clerk, and his heirs of all lands and tenements which the said
                  Adam holds of him in the village of Kirkeby. Dated at Stokesley on the vigil of
                  St. John the Baptist, <date when="1302">1302</date>. [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 172</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="614"/> John de Kyrkeby, senior, grants to John de Eure the homage and
                  service of his tenants of Kirkby, amongst whom are the prior of Hexaldesham, the
                  prioress of Basdale, and the abbot of Rieval. Dated at Inggelby the Wednesday next
                  before the feast of St. John the Baptist, <date when="1302">1302</date>. Cb. 173.
                  John de Eure grants and confirms to John de Kirkeby, senior, all right in 3$. 1 1
                  ^d. annual rent from two bovates of land in Kirkeby. Dated at Inggelby the
                  Wednesday next before the feast of St. John Bapt., <date when="1302">1302</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 174</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Thormotby, son and heir of Robert de Thormotby, confirms to Margaret,
                  daughter of John de Kyrkeby, one toft and croft in the village of Kyrkeby. Dated
                     <date when="1304">1304</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 175</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Kyrkeby remits and quit-claims to sir John de Eure all right and claim in
                  35. n\d. annual rents, which the said sir John covenants to pay to him annually;
                  also all right to a messuage and a bovate of land, all in the village of Kirkeby.
                  Dated at Engleby near Grenehowe, the Sunday next before the feast of St. Gregory,
                  Pope, <date when="1306">1306</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 176</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Kyrkeby, near Stokesley, grants to Margaret his daughter a messuage with
                  land in culture in the village of Kirkeby. Dated of All Saints, <date when="1308"
                     >1308</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 177</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of Robert de Thormotby, remits and quit-claims to sir John de Eure,
                  all right which he has in a toft, croft, and bovate of land in Kirkeby in
                  Cliveland. Dated at Kirkeby, 13 August, <date>7th Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     178</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Margaret, daughter of John de Kirkeby, remits and quit-claims to sir John de
                  Eure, her lord, all right in one toft and croft in the village of Kirkeby. Dated
                  at Ingilby, 3ist May, <date>8 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  179</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Chambyrlayne of Stokyslay and Katherine his wife grant to Robert Kendale
                  and John Westewyke of Rypon, chaplains, and William Laue of the same, an annual
                  rent of 335. \d. from the village of Kirkeby in Clevelande. Dated 13 August, <date>5 Hen
                  V</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 180</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> KIKKESTALL (Abbey of). Confirmation of the rights and privileges of the abbey of
                  Kirkstall, by K. Hen. II. Dated at Nottingham. [With seal.] Ch. i *. Robert de
                  Laci grants to the church of St. Mary of Kirkestall, in frankalmoigne, a messuage
                  in Pontefract to the south part of his castle. (<date notBefore="1180"
                     notAfter="1190" precision="low">c. 1180-90</date>.) [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Samson de Alretun, and William his son, and Ragenilda his wife confirm to
                  Alexander, the abbot, and the monks of Kirkstall, in frankalmoigne, two carucates
                  of land in West Alretun, [Alexander, abbot <date when="1147">1147</date>-<date
                     when="1182">1182</date>.] [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 3</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="615"/> Convention between the church of Kirkstall and the church of the
                  Holy Trinity, York, by which the church of Kirkstall agrees to pay annually 2os.
                  as compensation for tithes which they were accustomed to have from the monks of
                  Kirkstall for their holding in the parish of Ledes, viz. 4 carucates of land in
                  "West Hadigleia (Haddlesey), half in Est Hadigleia, 2 carucates in West Alretun,
                  one bovate in East Alretun, &amp;c. (<date notBefore="1130" notAfter="1140"
                     precision="low">c. 1130-40</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 4</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Ralph, the abbot, and the convent of Kyrkestall confirm to Rayner de Pontefract
                  and his heirs their messuage in Pontefract which sir Robt. de Laci gave them for
                  an inn, paying annually one stone of wax at the Assumption B. M. V. (<date
                     notBefore="1190" notAfter="1200" precision="low">c. 1190-1200</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Ralph, the abbot, and convent of Kirkstall grant to William, son of Ernisius of
                  Alreton, eleven and a half acres of land in West Alreton, at an annual rent of
                  vid. for all services ; also they grant one other acre in West Alreton which
                  Ernisius his father held of them. (<date notBefore="1190" notAfter="1200"
                     precision="low">c. 1190-1200</date>.)* <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 6</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Adam, son of William, son of Samson de Alreton, grants to St. Mary and the monks
                  of Kirkstall, in frankalmoigne, 205. of annual rent from thejvillage of Alreton.
                     (<date when="1200" precision="low">c. 1200</date>.) [With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Convention made between Maurice, the abbot, and convent of Kirkstall, of the one
                  part, and Robert the son of Richard de Lofthusun of the other, by which the said
                  abbot and convent grant to the said Robert a bovate of land in Lofthusun
                  (Lofthous), to hold the same from the feast of St. Martin, <date when="1235"
                     >1235</date>, for 8 years, at an annual payment of 3s. 6d. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Adam, the abbot of Kirkstall, grants to his prior and convent of Kirkstall los.
                  8d. of annual rents from the village of Roudun. (<date when="1249"
                  >1249</date>-59.) [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter reciting the contention in the year of grace <date when="1259"
                     >1259</date>, between sir Hugh, the abbot, and the convent of Kyrkestall, of
                  the one part, and Robert the son of Richard le Blund' of Alreton of the other,
                  concerning the liberties, rights, and easements belonging to one bovate of land in
                  Alreton which the said Robert holds as successor of his father and which are now
                  granted to him by the said abbot and convent. Dated on the feast of SS. Simon and
                  Jude, <date>44 Hen. III</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 10</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alexander de le Eschaleres and Alicia his wife grant to the monks of Kirkstall an
                  annual rent of 23s. 46?. which the monks were accustomed to pay to them for a
                  meadow in the territory of Folifayt. (<date notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240"
                     precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.) [With seals.] Ch. n. William, son of
                  William de Alreton, remits and quit-claims to the abbot and monks of Kirkstall all
                  right in one bovate of land, one <pb n="616"/> acre and one assart in Alreton, of
                  the gift of Henry the chaplain of Thornon. (<date notBefore="1250" notAfter="1260"
                     precision="low">c. 1250-60</date>.) [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     12</bibl>. Robert de Bernes grants to the church and monks of Kirkstall, in
                  frankalmoigne, lod. of annual rent in the village of Calverlay, with homages,
                  reliefs, and other services, (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Margaret de Roudun grants to the monks of Kirkstall, in frankalmoigne, one toft
                  which she has in Roudon, together with an essart called Le Stamrode and Le
                  Stampikel, and 2 acres and i perch which lie near 'Le Wellesie.' (<date
                     notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.) [With
                  seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 14</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Ralph, sou of Greoffrey de Ardington, quit-claims to the monks of Kirkstall all
                  right in two bovates of land in the village of Ardington. (<date notBefore="1240"
                     notAfter="1250" precision="low">c. 1240-50</date>.) [With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 15</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Jordan de Storthys, son and heir of Suain*de Leicester, grants to the monks of
                  St. Mary, Kirkstall, in frankalmoigne, the whole of his lands in Neuhal and
                  Belling. Dated in the year of grace <date when="1248">1248</date>. [With seal]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 16</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> / Robert, son of William de Stapelton, confirms to William his brother, for his
                  homage and service, the whole of his land &amp;c. which he has in the village of
                  Brameley of the gift of Emma his mother. (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 17</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard, son of Robert of the cemetery of Allerton, grants to the monks of
                  Kirkstall the whole of his land in Colwaynrode, al|p he quit-claims all his right
                  in all lands, mills, woods, &amp;c. of which the said monks were seised in the
                  year <date when="1238">1238</date>, viz. in the territory of Allerton, Hedingleid,
                  and Osmundthorp. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 18</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Maurice, the abbot, and the convent of St. Mary, Kirkstall, grant to William, son
                  of Henry Cythariste (the harper), the half of one messuage and the half of one
                  toft in the village of Calverley. (<date notBefore="1220" notAfter="1230"
                     precision="low">c. 1220-30</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 19</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Margaret, formerly wife of William de Brerehaye, remits and quitclaims to the
                  monks of Kirkstall the third part of an annual rent of 8s., which came to her by
                  the name of dowry, (<date notBefore="1260" notAfter="1270" precision="low">c.
                     1260-70</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 20</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Adam Gamlon grants to the monks of Kirkstall the whole of his land which he had
                  at the head of the land of the said monks in Pudekessai. (<date when="1230"
                     precision="low">c. 1230</date>40.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 21</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Walter, son of Adam Samson of Puddesay, confirms to the abbot of Kirkstall with
                  his body an annual rent of 2S. out of the village of Puddesay from land of Richard
                  de Puddesay, carpenter, (<date notBefore="1240" notAfter="1250" precision="low">c.
                     1240-50</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 22</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, son of Thomas, son of Rayner de Pontefract, remits and quit<pb n="617"
                  />claims to the abbot and convent of Kirkstall the whole of the services and
                  annual rents &amp;c. which . . . hel de Braddeford and others were accustomed to
                  render in the village of Pontefract and Darington. (<date notBefore="1270"
                     notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 23</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Convention, dated the Saturday next after the feast of St. Luke, evang., <date
                     when="1287">1287</date>, between Hugh, the abbot, and convent of Kirkstall of
                  the one part, and sir Henry de Lacy, earl of Lincoln and constable of Chester, of
                  the other part, concerning lands in the counties of Lancaster and York leased by
                  the abbey to the earl for certain annual rents. [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 24</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, the abbot, and the convent of Kirkstall demise to farm to William de
                  Brerehagh 5 acres of land and a meadow in Arthington, for 20 years, at an annual
                  rent of 2od. Dated <date when="1334">1334</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     25</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Putee of Pontefract confirms to the convent of Kirkstall that messuage in
                  the village of Poutefract in the way called Valesaygute. Dated at Pontefract the
                  Tuesday next after the feast of St. Barnabas, <date when="1344">1344</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 26</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Nicholas Adamson of Yedon, chaplain, grants to the abbot and convent of Kirkstall
                  one messuage and thirty-seven acres of land and meadow in Pudsay. Dated at Pudsay,
                  16 Feb., <date when="1398">1398</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     27</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Memorandum : Hilbert Lacy came in with William I, from whom proceeded Robert
                  Lacy, founder of the priory of Pontefract, from whom proceeded Hilbert and Henry.
                  Hilbert died s. p. and Henry founded Kirkstall abbey, from which Henry proceeded
                  Robert and Albreda. Prom Albreda came John de Lacy, son of Richard, constable of
                  Chester. From John came Roger. From Roger, John 2nd. From John, Edmund. From
                  Edmund, Henry de Lacy, earl of Lincoln, &amp;c.,. ending with K. Henry VI. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 28</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> KNAPTON (West). Warine de Vescy, brother of Eustachius de Vescy, grants to
                  Gilbert de Aton and Marioia his wife (daughter of the above Warine), one bovate of
                  land in West Knapton. <date notBefore="1280" notAfter="1290" precision="medium">(c. 1280-90.)</date> [ With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     181</bibl></p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> . KNABESBOROUGH (The House of the Holy Trinity at). Indulgence granted to William
                  Hepdenstall and Alice, by Robert, minister of the house of St. Robert near
                  Knaresburgh, of 80 days' relaxation from penance, by virtue of a bull of pope
                  Innocent VIII. Dated <date when="1491">1491</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     65</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indulgence granted to .... and Alice his wife by Robert, minister of the house of
                  St. Robert near Knaresburgh. Dated <date when="1503">1503</date>. [With seal.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 66</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="618"/> KNIGHTS TEMPLARS. William Puter(j) of Heddigeley grants to the
                  Knights Templars, in frankalmoigne, his mill of Heddigeley and a culture near the
                  mill, together with suit due to the mill from the men of the fee of Heddigeley and
                  Burgeley. (<date notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low">c.
                     1230-40</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 92</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Convention dated <date when="1257">1257</date>, on the feast of the Ascension of
                  our Lord, between Elizabeth, formerly wife of Jordan d'Lisle, and the master and
                  brethren of the Knights Templars in England, witnesseth that the said Elizabeth
                  quit-claims all her right to certain lands and tenements in Colton. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 93</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Jordan, son of Adam Freman of Colton, grants to the Knights Templars all his
                  right and claim in a certain wood called Coltundene, and in a certain piece of
                  meadow abutting on the said wood. (<date notBefore="1260" notAfter="1270"
                     precision="low">c. 1260-70</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 94</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Haimeric de St. Maur, master of the Knights Templars of England, with the counsel
                  and assent of their chapter at Cowley, grants to William, son of Nicholas, four
                  bovates of land and three tofts in Alreton. (<date notBefore="1220"
                     notAfter="1230" precision="low">c. 1220-30</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     95</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Adam de Linchweyt grants to the Knights Templars, in frankalmoigne, the whole of
                  his herbage, with woods, &amp;c., in the village of North Crossland. (<date
                     notBefore="1260" notAfter="1270" precision="low">c. 1260-70</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 96</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LEEDS. William Ledes, esq., and Joan his wife grant to Thomas Symson of Ledes,
                  draper, one burgage and half an acre of land lying upon Burmantoftes. Dated at
                  Ledes, 14 July, <date>5 Hen. VI</date>. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     182</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Vavasour and others grant to Peter Symson one burgage in Ledes and half an
                  acre of land lying upon Burmantoftes. Dated 3 April, <date>15 Ed. IV</date>. [With
                  seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 183</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Memorandum, dated <date>26 April, . . Ed. VI</date>, by which John Baynes and Margaret his
                  wife lease a cottage and garden to John Wylliamson for a certain term of years.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 184</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Memorandum extracted from the Manor Court Roll of Leds, held 1 1 May, <date>38
                     Hen. VIII</date>, of the grant of a house to Elizabeth Boithe. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 184*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard Newbye of Lamrigge, co. Westmoreland, in consideration of a sum of 33 6s.
                  8d., grants to Robert Hoythe the whole of his close called Oxlose containing five
                  acres lying in Littlewodhowse near Leeds. Dated 15 Dec., <date>14 Q. Elizabeth</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 185</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An inquisition post mortem taken at York, indented, 1 2 June, 1 <date>6 Charles
                     I</date>, before Thomas Hutton, esq., escheator of Abraham Smith, lately of
                  Leeds, co. York. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 186</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An exemplification of a recovery inrolled <date>23 Charles I</date>, between
                  Stephen Netherwood and Thomas Walker of the one part, and James Netherwood and
                  Nicholas Netherwood of the other, concerning five messuages, 5 gardens, and one
                  acre of land in Leeds. Dated at Westminster, 3 May, <date when="1649">1649</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 186*</bibl></p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="619"/> Marriage settlement by which Robert Clowdisley of Leeds, co. York,
                  in consideration of a marriage between his son Timothy and Mary Negus of Higham
                  Ferrers, grants a half burgage or tenement in Leeds. Dated 25 May, <date
                     when="1652">1652</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 187</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Final concord, by which Thomas Howley and Margaret his wife recognises that a
                  messuage, two barns, a garden, an orchard, 8 acres of land, and n acres of meadow,
                  &amp;c. belong to John Harrison, gent., and Thomas Wilcock. Dated <date>u May, n James
                  I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 188</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture dated . . . January, <date>12 Charles I</date> (reciting a previous
                  grant of the manor of Leeds, Yorkshire, from King James), witnessing that Robert
                  Townthwait of Leeds, clothier, in consideration of the receipt of &lt;n, sells and
                  confirms to Philip Dilworth of the same place, chapman, a parcel of land, with 2
                  tenements, in the west part of Leeds bridge within the manor of Leeds, paying to
                  the king the usual and accustomed services. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  188*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LEEDS and GRETLAND. Fine dated at Westminster on the morrow of the Purification
                  of the B.V. M., <date>13 Charles II</date>, between John Houldsworth, gent.,
                  William Milner, gent., Edmund Hinde, John Ellistones, and Jeremiah Elli stones,
                  petitioners, and John Rolston and Frances his wife, Grace Deane, widow, Robert
                  Gamble, John Dransfield and Jane his wife, defendants, concerning messuages,
                  barns, and land in Leeds and Gretland. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 189</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LEPINGTON, &amp;c. Fragment of the charter No. 189 6, Yorkshire, q. v. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 189 a</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>. Mutilated indenture, dated 5 July, <date>16 Hen. VIII</date>, between sir Robert
                  Ughtred, kt., of the one part, and Symon Webb of London, and William Challoner, of
                  the other, witnesseth that the said sir Robert has sold to the said Symon and
                  William his manors of Lepington and Barthorpe. [See also <date when="1890"
                     >1890</date>.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 1896</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Bond given by sir Robert Ughtred, kt., to Simon Webbe of London of 250. Dated 5
                  July, <date>16 Hen. VI</date>H. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 190</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Simon Webbe and William Chaloner grant to sir Henry Wyatt, kt., John Zowche, and
                  others the manors of Lepyngton and Barthorp. Dated 20 July, <date>16 Hen.
                     VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 191</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Thomas Wyott and others remit and quit-claim to Henry Wyott and sir John Zouche,
                  kt., all right in the manors of Lepyngton and Barthorpe, and in lands &amp;c. in
                  Lepyngton, Barthorpe, and North Dalton. Dated i July, <date>18 Hen. VIII</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 192</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> LOFTHOUS. Hervey, son of Hugh de Loftus, grants to Roger, son of Roger de Loftus,
                  for his homage and service, that messuage and toft which Richard Carbonarius held,
                  paying i6d. for all services, (<date notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240"
                     precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 193</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, son of Jordan de Lofthus, grants to Hamo Dautrey [de Alta Ripa] three
                  acres and one rood and one toft of land in the territory of Lofthus. (<date
                     when="1290" precision="low">c. 1290</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     194</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="620"/> Hamo de Diutry grants to William de Hameletone, dean of York, his
                  capital messuage and land in Loftbus near Harewode. (<date notBefore="1290"
                     notAfter="1300" precision="low">c. 1290-1300</date>.) 6^195. Symon Chaumberlayn
                  of Pontefract grants to John, son of Thomas de Lofthous, i 11 kind of right,
                  services, rents, customs, &amp;c. which he had or was accustomed to take from
                  lands and tenements in the village of Lofthous. Dated at Lofthous the Saturday
                  next after the feast of St. Peter ad vine., <date when="1341">1341</date>. [With
                  seal.~] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 196</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MALT ON (New). Hugh de Wellom grants to Adam atte Cros of Neuton, near
                  Wintringham, a messuage in the village of Malton. Dated at Malton the Monday next
                  after the feast of the Epiphany, <date>35 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 197</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sir William de Aton, kt., son and heir of sir Gilbert de Aton, kt., assigns
                  Thomas de Swynton and William de Chamber to be his attorneys to deliver full
                  seisin to sir Thomas de Graffton and sir John de Yedingham, chaplains, of all his
                  lands and tenements in How, and Wytom near Malton, as well as in the langebrotes
                  of Malton. Dated at Aton in Pykerynglyth on the morrow of St. Bartholomew, <date
                     when="1384">1384</date>. I With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 199</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sir William de Aton, kt., son and heir of sir Gilbert de Aton, kt., grants to
                  Thomas de Graffton and John de Yedingham, chaplains, all his lands and tenements
                  within the villages of How and Wytom, near Malton. Dated at Malton on the feast of
                  St. Bartholomew, <date when="1384">1384</date>. [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 200</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made . . April, <date>2$th year of . . . .</date> , by which the right honble.
                  Raffe, lord Eure, demises to Richard Medd and Cristobell .... two closes and a
                  cottage within the lordship of Old Malton, for 21 years, at an annual rent of 30.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 200*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MALTON (Old), WICKHAM, YEASTROP, STOKESLEY, STOKESLEY MOORE, BAYSDAILE, WELHAM,
                  and SUTTON. Grant of free warren by K. James I to Ralph Eure of New Malton, esq.,
                  for the above lands and manors. Dated n July, <date>17 James I</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 201</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MALTON Priory. William, son of William de Redburn, confirms to the convent of St.
                  Mary of Malton, in frankalmoigne, six bovates of land in Little Edeston, with
                  tofts and crofts, &amp;c. pertaining to the same. (<date notBefore="1240"
                     notAfter="1250" precision="low">c. 1240-50</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     67</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> A confirmation and grant of a licence of mortmain to the prior and convent of
                  Malton by Rich. II. Dated at Westminster, 28 January, <date>10 Rich. II</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 68</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MARYKE Nunnery. ' The forme of takyng the fownder.' [<date>Temp. Hen. VII</date>.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 26*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="621"/> MENSYNGTON. Robert, son of Robert de Burnehaye, grants to Juliana
                  his sister, for her homage and service, half a croft and lynebutdale which lies
                  near Kersyde in Mensyngton. (<date when="1230" precision="low">c. 1230</date>40.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 202</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Thomas de Tordewrd quit-claims to Henry, son of Mathew de Mensyngton, all right
                  in 4 acres of land and meadow in the field of Mensyngton. (<date when="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 203</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry, son of Mathew de Mensyngton, grants to Robert de Button one rood of meadow
                  lying in the field of Mensyngton. (<date when="1280" precision="low">c.
                     1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 204</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alice, relict of Mathew de Mensington, remits and quit-claims to Henry her son
                  all right in the land formerly her husband's in Mensyngton. (<date when="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 205</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry, son of Mathew de Mensyngton, grants to Robert de Button the whole of his
                  arable land with a field adjacent in the field of Mensyngton. (<date when="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) Ch.zob. Henry, son of Mathew de Mensyngton,
                  grants to Robert de Button 8d. of annual rents in the village of Mensyngton.
                     (<date when="1280" precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     207</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Gilbert, son of Hugh de Mensyngton, and Juliana his wife grant to Robert de
                  Button one toft with a croft in the village of Mensyngton. Dated the Monday next
                  after the feast of the apostles SS. Philip and James, <date>23 Ed. I</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 208</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Walter de Middelton of Burley grants to Richard, sou of William 'cum Cartis' of
                  Mensyngton, 6d. of annual rent in the village of Mensyngton. Dated at Otteley the
                  day of the translation of St. Thomas, archbp., <date>22 Ed. I</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 209</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard ' cum Cartis ' of Mensyngton grants to Robert de Button two ridges of
                  land in the field of Mensyngton. Dated the Monday next after the feast of the
                  apostles SS. Philip and James, <date>23 Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     210</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard, son of Richard le Yykerman of Weston, grants to Martin, son of Henry de
                  Kelbrock, two acres of land and a meadow in the field of Mensyngton. (<date
                     when="1290" precision="low">c. 1290</date>.) . <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     211</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert, son of William de Brerehaye, and Agnes his wife grant to William, son of
                  Michael 'ad ductum' of Mensyngton, one toft and croft in the village of
                  Mensyngton. (<date when="1280" precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 212</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Mathew de Mensyngton and Joan his wife grant to William, son of John, son of
                  Thomas de Weston, the whole of his land in the field of Mensyngton which Joan his
                  wife, mother of the said William, had by gift of Matilda, daughter of Gilbert son
                  of Michael. Dated at Mensyngton the Tuesday next before the Ascension, IT Ed.
                     <date when="1113">1113</date>17. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 213</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alexander de Mensington grants to Richard, son of William de <pb n="622"/>
                  Haukesworth, the ward and marriage of John, son and heir of Mat hew, son and heir
                  of Gilbert de Mensington, and his land which he holds of the said Alexander in
                  Mensington. Dated at Mensington the Monday next before the feast of the
                  Purification of the Virgin, <date when="1320">1320</date>. Ch, 214, Matilda,
                  daughter of Philip, son of Thomas de Weston, quit-claims to Martin, son of Henry
                  de Kelbrock, all right in two acres of land in Mensyngton. Dated at Mensyngton the
                  Sunday next before the feast of St. Barnabas, <date when="1334">1334</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 215</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry, son of Mathew de Mensington, grants to William de Brerehaye a certain plot
                  of land in the field of Mensyngton. (<date notBefore="1290" notAfter="1300"
                     precision="low">c. 1290-1300</date>.) [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     216</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sibil, relict of John de Mensyngton of Ottelay, remits and quitclaims to Martin,
                  son of Henry de Kellebrok, all right in one toft and 8 acres of land in
                  Mensyngton. Dated at Ottelay the Tuesday on the feast of St. Nicholas, bp.,
                     <date>8 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 217</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Merbeck grants to Walter, son of Henry de Baildon de Ottelay, one toft
                  with a croft in the village of Mensyngton, also all that land and meadow which he
                  had by the gift of Alice, daughter of Gilbert and of William Hebbe. Dated at
                  Mensyngton the Thursday next before the feast of St. Hilary, <date when="1341"
                     >1341</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 218</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard, son of Paul Rudde of Ottelay, grants to Walter, son of Henry de Baildon
                  of Ottelay, one acre of land with a meadow adjacent in the field of Mensyngton.
                  Dated at Mensyngton . . . after the feast of St. Hilary, <date when="1341"
                     >1341</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 219</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of William Attebeck of Mensyngton, remits and quit-claims to
                  William, son of Richard de Merbeck of Mensyngton, all right which he had in that
                  messuage and bovate of land in the village of Mensyngton. Dated at Mensyngton the
                  Sunday next before the feast of the Conception of the Virgin, <date when="1343"
                     >1343</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 220</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Hebbe of Mensyngton remits and quit-claims to Walter de Baildon, staying
                  in Ottelay, all right in one messuage with a croft in the village of Mensyngton.
                  Dated after the feast of St. Matthew the apostle, <date>18 Ed. III</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 221</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John, son of Mathew, son of Gilbert de Mensyngton, grants to John Pykhard, sen.,
                  of Mensyngton, all his lands and tenements in Mensyngton. Dated at Mensyngton the
                  Sunday next before the feast of St. Margaret, virg., <date>30 Edw. III</date>. [With seal.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 222</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="623"/> William Dykson of Menston grants to Walter Grauer of Menston, John
                  de Merbek, John Thomson, and William Thomlynson, all of the same place, all his
                  lands &amp;c. in the village of Menston. Dated at Menston the Sunday next after
                  the feast of St. Leonard, <date when="1377">1377</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 223</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Dicson of Mensyngton remits and quit-claims to Walter Grauer of the same
                  place, all his right in all his lands &amp;c. in the village of Mensyngton. Dated
                  at Ottelay the Sunday on the feast of St. Margaret, virg. and martyr, <date>6 Ric.
                     II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 224</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Olive, who was the wife of Robert de Bradlay of Draghton, grants to sir John de
                  Denton, vicar of Bracewell, and sir Robert del Fflatte, chaplain, all her lands,
                  rents, &amp;c. which came to her after the decease of Martin de Kelbrok her
                  father, in Mensyngton. Dated at Mensyngton the Sunday next after the feast of the
                  Assumption, <date>18 Ric. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 225</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Denton, vicar of Bracewell, and Robert del Fflatte grant to Olive, who
                  was the wife of Robert de Bradeley of Draghton, all lands and tenements in
                  Mensyngton. Dated at Couunlay on the feast of Pentecost, <date>20 Rich. II</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 226</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Olive, formerly wife of Robert de Bradlay, grants to Richard de Brerhagh of
                  Mensyngton two messuages with two tofts and crofts and 20 acres of land in the
                  village of Mensyngton. Dated at Mensyngton the Wednesday next before the feast of
                  Corpus Christi, <date>20 Rich. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 227</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Bayldon grants to Robert Paslaw, Thomas de Haukesworth, John Mohand,
                  and Walter Grauer all his lands &amp;c. in Bayldon, Bynglay, and Menston. Dated at
                  Bayldon the Sunday next after the feast of St. Andrew the apostle, <date>4 Hen.
                     IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 228</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard Brerehagh and Alice his wife grant to Walter Grauer of Menston one
                  messuage with a toft and eight a,cres of land lying in the village and field of
                  Menston. Dated at Menston the Sunday next before the feast of the Epiphany, <date>n Hen.
                  IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 229</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard Brehagh of Menston grants to William Graver of Menston two messuages in
                  the village and field of Menston. Dated at Menston on the feast of the Nativity of
                  St. John Baptist, i<date>i Hen. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 230</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Pycard of Menston and Agnes his wife grant to Walter Grauer and Beatrix
                  his wife one messuage with a toft in the village of Menston. Dated at Menston the
                  Sunday next after the feast of the Conversion of St. Paul, <date>12 Hen.
                  IV</date>. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 231</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="624"/> Nicholas, son and heir of William de Bayldon, remits and quit-
                  claims to William Graver all his right in lands and tenements in the village and
                  field of Menston. Dated at Menston on the feast of St. William, confessor, 1
                     <date>2 Hen. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 232</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Grene, sen., of Ottelay, grants to William Graver of Mensyngton seven
                  acres of land between the field of Burlay on the one side and the field of Ottelay
                  towards the east on the other. . Dated at Ottelay on the feast of Corpus Christi,
                     <date>8 Hen. V</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 233</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Denton, vicar of Bracewell, and Robert de Fflatte, chaplain, appoint John
                  de Ffarnehill their attorney to deliver seisin in their name to Olive, who was the
                  wife of Robert de Bradelay of Draghton, of lands &amp;c. in Mensyngton. Dated at
                  Couunlay on the feast of Pentecost, <date>20 Rich. II</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 234</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Walter Graver of Menston grants to Richard his son one messuage with 8 acres of
                  land and meadow adjoining in the village and field of Menston called Scothlande.
                  Dated at Menston, 23 November, <date>2 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     235</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Grauer of Ottelay grants to Walter his son of Menston two messuages in
                  the field and village of Menston. Dated at Menston, 10 January, <date>14 Hen.
                     VI</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 236</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Graver grants to Walter his son one messuage lying in Mensyngton which
                  descended to him after the decease of his mother Beatrice. Dated at Mensyngton, 10
                  January, <date>14 Hen. VI</date>. [With seal.'] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     237</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Graver, sen., of Menston grants to Richard Graver, dean of the collegiate
                  church of Chester, one toft and croft in the village and field of Menston. Dated
                  at Menston, 9 November, <date>21 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     238</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Gravej, sen., of Menston grants to sir Richard Graver, dean of Chester,
                  one messuage and all that appertains to it in Menston. Dated at Menston, 9 Nov.,
                     <date>21 Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 239</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Brerehay of Menston grants to Thomas, lord Clifford and Westmorland,
                  Walter Calverlay, esq., and Robert Newell, vicar of Otley, all lands and
                  tenements, &amp;c. which he has in the county of York, also all his goods moveable
                  and immoveable at the time of his death. Dated at Menston on the feast of St.
                  Laurence, <date>22 Hen. VI</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     240</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Rudd, butcher, and William Lambert, butcher, citizens of York, are bound to
                  William Brerhawe of Menston in the parish of Ottelay in a sum of 33s. ^d., payable
                  to the said William at the feast of All Saints following. Dated n September,
                     <date>25 Hen. VI</date>. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 241</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="625"/> Richard Graver, Rector of Hurworth-upon-Tysam, grants to sir Thomas
                  Clifforth, sir Thomas Percy, and sir John Tempes, kts., two messuages and 28 acres
                  of land in Mensyngton. Dated at Menston, i September, <date>26 Hen. VI</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 242</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Walter Graver of Bayldon grants to sir John Newell, kt., Thomas Newell, kt., and
                  Oliver Elystons, all lands and tenements which he has in Manston and Otlay, also
                  one messuage in Bayldon, and all his goods moveable and immoveable at the time of
                  his death. Dated at Chester on the feast of St. Margaret, <date>31 Hen. VI</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 243</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> "Walter Graver of Baildon grants to Joan his wife the reversion of all his lands,
                  tenements, rents, and services, after his decease, which he has in the villages of
                  Baildon and Mensyngton, and 7 acres within a close called Storres in the field to
                  the west of Otley. Dated at Mensyngton, 6 June, <date>16 Ed. IV</date>. Ch, 244.
                  Oliver Elystones, chaplain, and Robert Pyncheware of Calthorn, grant to Walter
                  Graver of Bayldon and Joan his wife all lands, tenements, &amp;c., which they had
                  by the gift, &amp;c. of the said Walter in Mensington and Bayldon. Dated at
                  Bayldon, 30 August, <date>17 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 245</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Bond given by William Graver of Spoford and Richard Mawde of Menston and Richard
                  Smyth of Emsley to Percival Brerey in a sum of 40 to abide by the award of
                  Geoffrey Pikard and others concerning the lands &amp;c. of the late Walter
                  Graver's of Menston. Dated 24 Feb., <date>3 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 246</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Brerehaugh, clerk, rector of Langwath, co. Derby, and Hugh Brerehaugh of
                  Bassyngham, co. Lincoln, husbandman, appoint Alan Brerehaugh of IMewerk, their
                  brother, their attorney to act for them with the heirs, executors, &amp;c. of
                  Richard Brerehaugh for moneys owing them under a bond and last will of Esot'
                  Brerhaugh, late wife of William Bre of Skypton, co. York. Dated i September,
                     <date>4 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 246*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Percival Brerehaghe grants to Richard Clapeham, gent., William Brerehagh,
                  Christopher Pykard, and William Roods one tenement with all lands, fields, &amp;c.
                  belonging to the same in Menston. Dated 7 March, <date>14 Hen. V</date>HL <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 247</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Richard Clapeham, gent., William Brerehagh, Christ. Pykard, and William Roods
                  grant to Percival Brerehagh and Joan his wife one tenement with land and meadow in
                  Menston. Dated 7 March, <date>14 Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     248</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MIDELTON. William, son of John le Yong of Midelton, grants to Thomas de Linlay de
                  Thorp on the Hill and Alice his wife one assart which is called le Serlerode in
                  Midelton. (<date when="1300" precision="low">c. 1300</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 249</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Gilbert de la Legh grants to John, his younger son, and Clarissa, <pb n="626"/>
                  YORK. daughter of Thomas de Fenton, his manor of Mydilton near Rothewell, paying
                  annually for the same 8 6s. Sd. Dated at Midilton the Monday in Easter week, <date
                     when="1332">1332</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 249*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MORHOUSES. Thomas de Schepeldy grants to Peter the taverner and Christiana his
                  wife 25. annual rent in Morhouses. (<date when="1300" precision="low">c.
                     1300</date>.) [With seal.'] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 250</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MORTON. Simon de Skestling grants to Emma his daughter two bovates of land in
                  Morton, viz. two bovates that Christiana de Giseburne held. (<date
                     notBefore="1220" notAfter="1230" precision="low">c. 1220-30</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 251</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> MTTSTON. Institution of Sir John Somerby to the vicarage of the chapel of Muston
                  in the parish of Hundemanby, York diocese, on the presentation of the abbot and
                  convent of Bardeney, Line. dioc. Dated at York, 27 May, <date when="1508"
                     >1508</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 252</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NETTHAY. Henry de Steingreve grants to Robert Authendel one acre of land in
                  Neuhay. (<date notBefore="1190" notAfter="1200" precision="low">c.
                     1190-1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 253</bibl>, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry Staingreve, with the consent of Simon his brother, grants to John, son of
                  Waldigg, the chaplain, 1 1 acres of his demesne in the marsh of Neuhay and 7 acres
                  upon Fultac. (<date when="1200" precision="low">c. 1200</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 254</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry, son of Alice de Neuhay, daughter of Henry de Stainegrive r quit-claims to
                  Richard de Happlesthorp the whole of her land in the territory of Neuhay. (<date
                     notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 255</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry, son of Alice de Staingrive, confirms to Richard de Aplesthorp in the
                  territory of Neuhay one acre of land which he bought of Robert Houthendel of
                  Seleby lying in the marsh, and also 2 other acres in the marsh of the same
                  village. (<date when="1240" precision="low">c. 1240</date>.) [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 256</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alice de Newhay, daughter of Henry de Staingrive, sells to Richard de
                  Happlesthorp, for a sum of money which he gave her in her great necessity, 2\
                  acres of land in Neuhay. (<date when="1240" precision="low">c. 1240</date>.) [With
                  seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 257</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert Ditchendel of Seleby sells to Henry, son of Alice de Stainegrive, one acre
                  of land in Neuhay. , (<date when="1230" precision="low">c. 1230</date>.) [With
                  seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 258</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NORMANBY. Institution of sir Edmund Baynee to the church of Normanby, on the
                  presentation of William Romsden and Richard Vavasoure. Dated 27 Sept., <date>38
                     Hen. VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 259</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NORMANTON. William de Hertford grants to William de Normanton one windmill in
                  Normanton for his life. Dated at Smeaton the Tuesday in Easter week, 1 <date>7
                     Rich. II</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 261</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NOSTEL PRIORY. Richard, son of William the presbyter, and Beatrix his wife,
                  daughter of Swein Gunne, for the health of their souls grant to the church of St.
                  Oswald of Nostle, in frankalmoigne, one acre of land in Preston, (o. <date
                     when="1220">1220</date>-30.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 69</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="627"/> Writ of K. Rich. II, addressed to Thomas, archbishop of York,
                  reciting that William, prior of the monastery of St. Oswald, Nostel, in the king's
                  court had recovered his right of presentation to the perpetual chantry in the
                  chapel of St. John the Baptist of Preston, against Richard Haliday, gent., and
                  Richard Lemyng, chaplain. Dated at Westminster, 22 March, <date>2 Rich. II</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 70</bibl> Robert Flemmyng grants to Thomas Barbor of
                  Folby all tenement?, rents, and services which he holds for a term of 60 years,
                  also half an acre of land in Croston, paying annually 2s. to the said Robert, and
                  8d. to the monastery of St. Oswald of Nostell. Dated at Folby, 12 Jan., <date>2
                     Hen. V</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 71</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 1 3 Feb., <date>30 Hen. VIII</date>, between Robert, the prior,
                  and the convent of St. Oswald of Nostell of the one part, and Roger Malet,
                  gentleman, of the other part, witnesseth that the said prior and convent have let
                  to the said Roger all their tithes of corn and hay within the town of Wrangbroke
                  for 3 1 years, paying annually for the same 6 i os. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     72</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> NUW-APPLETON PRIORY. Richard de Fauconberg grants to the prioress and convent of
                  Apelton the whole of his land which is called Suthwod, with 6 acres of meadow in
                  the meadows to the east of Apelton. Dated on the feast of St. Martin, in the
                  winter, <date>29 Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 73</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ORMSBY. James Strangways appoints James Buyth and John Goldyngtre together and
                  separately his attorneys to give possession of two bovates of land in Ormsby, and
                  lands, &amp;c. in Great and Little Upsall near Ormsby. Dated at Ormsby, 3 May, <date>2
                  Rich. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 262</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> OSMUNDTHORP. Peter, son of Thomas de Hosmundthorp, confirms to Roger, son of
                  Gerard de Hosmundthorp, one bovate of land in the fields of Hosmundthorp. (<date
                     notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 263</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of Robert of the cemetery of Allerton, grants to Alexander, son of
                  Alexander de Osmundthorp, and his heirs, the whole of his land in Osmundthorp.
                     (<date notBefore="1260" notAfter="1270" precision="low">c. 1260-70</date>.)
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 264</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Ellen, wife of Thomas Bantan of Osmundthorp, and Agnes her daughter, grant to
                  William, son of William Ossemunde of the same place, one bovate of land and one
                  croft in Osmundthorp. Dated at Leeds on the vigil of the Purification of the
                  Virgin, <date>9 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 265</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Ellen, daughter of Adam dil Hole of Osmundthorp, grants to John, son of William
                  le Tynkler of Ledes, and Agnes his wife, one acre of arable land in Osmundthorp.
                     (<date notBefore="1290" notAfter="1300" precision="low">c. 1290-1300</date>.)
                  [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 266</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Agnes, daughter of William Broune, remits and quit-claims to S S 2 <pb n="628"/>
                  YORK. Robert de Caldecotes all right in lands and tenements in the village of
                  Osemondethorp. Dated on the feast of the Assumption of the Blessed Mary, <date>21
                     Ric. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 267</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Skelton of Osmondthorp grants to Henry Rokley, William Scott, esq., and
                  William Musgrave, chaplain, all messuages, lands, and tenements, &amp;c. within
                  the lordship of Osmundthorp. Dated 10 Oct., <date>7 Hen. VII</date>. [With seal.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 268</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter indented between sir William Darcy, kt., of one part, and John Skelton of
                  Osmundthorp of the other part, witnesseth that the said William grants to the said
                  John all his lands and tenements in Osmundthorp for 100 years, paying annually 8.
                  Dated 4 April, <date>23 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 269</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> OTTELEY. Richard Brerehagh grants to Thomas, lord Clifford and Westmoreland, kt.,
                  Richard Tunstall, Walter Calverley, and Robert Newall, vicar of Otley, all his
                  goods moveable and immoveable at the time of his death. Dated 20 August, <date>24
                     Hen. VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 270</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The will of Richard Breray, dated 16 May, <date when="1452">1452</date>. Proved
                  at Ottelay, i June, <date when="1452">1452</date>. [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 271</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> OVENBEN. Alice, formerly wife of Hugh de Fossat, quit-claims to William de
                  Metheley all her right in the village and territory of Ovendene. (<date
                     notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 272</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Writ addressed to Edmund Hastynges, sheriff of Yorkshire, to the effect that
                  Thomas Metheley had recovered in the king's court at Westminster, by default
                  against John Maude of Warneley, a messuage and land in Ovenden. Dated at
                  Westminster, 6 Nov., n Hen. IV. Seisin given by the sheriff the Friday after St.
                  Hilary, <date>n Hen. IV</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 273</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PATHLOBRIGGE. Martin Birkhed of Cotyngham and John West of Beiston, for a sum of
                  54 45. 4^., sell to John Bekwith the whole of a messuage and 2 closes of land in
                  Pathlobrigge, co. York, part of the monastery of Fountains. Dated 5 April, <date>4 Q.
                  Eliz</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 29*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> FARMANDBY, ESTHALGARTH, THORNETON, ELLERBURNE, PYKERING, and THURKYLBY. Indenture
                  made 1 5 December, <date>20 Henry VII</date>, between sir Edward Hastings, kt.,
                  lord of Hastings and Hungerford, son and heir of sir William Hastings, kt., late
                  lord of Hastings, deceased, sir Thomas Frowyk, kt., chief justice, and Thomas
                  Jakes, of the one part, and Geoffrey Symeon, dean of St. George's, Windsor, and
                  the canons of the same, of the other part, reciting the foundation of a chantry by
                  the said William lord Hastings for the souls of himself and Katherine his wife and
                  others''in the chapel of St. George's, Windsor, and endowing the same with lands
                  of the annual value of 20. By this indenture certain manors, land, and houses are
                  given up and demised to the said dean and canons in the above parishes, &amp;c. ;
                  and because they do not amount to 20 per annum, the said Edward gives an annual
                  rent charge of 253. from his manor of Alberston for the said purposes. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 274</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="629"/> PONTEFRACT. Letters patent of King Charles I, dated at Canbury <date>21
                  July, 4 of his reign</date>, creating sir John Savill, kt., baron Savill of Pomfret in
                  the county of York. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 333</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Matilda, daughter and heir of Thomas, son of Geoffrey de Pontefract, grants to
                  Thomas her son one tenement in New Pontefract. Dated at Pontefract the Monday next
                  after Palm Sunday, <date when="1328">1328</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     275</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Matilda, daughter and heir of Thomas, son of Geoffrey de Pontefract, grants to
                  Thomas her son 14 acres of arable land lying in the fields of Pontefract and
                  Preston. Dated at Pontefract the Monday next after Palm Sunday, <date when="1328"
                     >1328</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 276</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Henry, son of sir Henry le Vavasour, kt., releases Robert de Friston, staying in
                  Pontefract, from all actions real and personal. Dated at Pontefract the Sunday
                  next before Epiphany, <date>18 Ed. II</date> T. [With seal.] Ch.vi>j.
                  Exemplification of a plea inrolled at "Westminster, <date>14 Charles II</date>, by
                  which Robert Cowper and Thomas Cooke recovered from Thomas Lake two messuages and
                  two acres of land in Pontefract. Dated 28 November, <date>14 Charles I</date>E.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 277*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PONTEFRACT (St. John's Priory at). John, brother of William de Kamesale,
                  quit-claims to Eudo, the chaplain of Pontefract, or his assigns, one toft &amp;c.
                  which William de Kamesale gave him for his service, paying annually to the monks
                  of St. John xiio?. for all services, (<date when="1230" precision="low">c.
                     1230</date>40.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 74</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Builli grants to God and St. John the apostle, of Pontefract, and the
                  monks there, in frankalmoigne, half an acre of land with a toft in '
                  Kimberwurdia.' [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 75</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PRESTON and FARNEBTTRNE. Sir Adam de Preston, kt., son of sir Adam de Preston,
                  kt., grants to John de Raygate, kt., for 1 40 marks sterling, the whole of his
                  land in Farneburne. Dated the Thursday on the feast of St. Wilfrid in the month of
                  April, <date>54 Hen. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 278</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PUDSAY. Robert, son of Jossam of Pudkesay, sells and confirms to William, son of
                  Adam of Pudkesay, the whole of the rent which Simon, sou of Clariz and John Pie,
                  used annually to pay him for certain lands in Pudkesay. (<date notBefore="1220"
                     notAfter="1230" precision="low">c. 1220-30</date>.) [With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 279</bibl>, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Thomas, son of John de Byrell of Pudesay, remits and quit-claims to John Scot of
                  Newton, John de Roudon, and sir Nicholas Adamson of Yedon, chaplain, all right in
                  lands, tenements, &amp;c. which were John de Byrell's, his father, in the village
                  of Pudesay. Dated 30 January, <date>21 Rich. II</date>. [TFV^A seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 280</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Wyrkelay constitutes Richard de Thornhill, his servant, his attorney
                  to deliver for him and in his name to Geoffrey de Lowenthorp, John de Allerton,
                  Thomas de Clayton, and Walter, son of Robert of Rothelay, seisin of all his lands
                  &amp;c. in the village of Pudsay. Dated 10 November, <date when="1399"
                  >1399</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 281</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="630"/> Geoffrey de Lewenthorp, John de Allerton, Thomas de Clayton, and
                  William, son of Robert de Rothelay, grant to William Rothelay the half of all the
                  lands and tenements which he had of the gift of William de Wirkelay in Pudsey, in
                  the parish of Calverley. Dated at Pudsey, i Jan., <date>i Hen. VI</date>. [With
                  seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 282</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PIKERINGrLYTH. Final concord made at Westminster in the octaves of St. Hilary,
                     <date>20 Ed. II</date>, before the king's justices, between John de Crayk,
                  parson of Spofford, and sir Gilbert de Aton, kt., concerning the manors of Aton,
                  Hoton, Buscell Wyntryngham, and Grumpton in Pykerynglyth. . <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 283</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Wythington and Margaret his wife demise to Robert de Conyers all lands
                  &amp;c. in Norton, Hoton, Heton, Skales, and Armeley, with rents and services of
                  Melmorby. Dated at Hoton the Friday next before Palm Sunday, <date when="1340"
                     >1340</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 284</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> RICHMOND (Abbey of St. Agatha). Henry, the abbot, and convent of St. Agatha grant
                  and quit-claim to the abbot and monks of Jorevall the cow-common of Mudebech in
                  Grarcedale which they formerly held of sir Adam fitz Hugh of Magneby, for 12
                  years, saving the common pasture, for the payment of 16 marks by the abbot and
                  convent of Jorevall. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 40</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> RIEVAL (Abbey of). Thomas, son of Paul, canon of the church of St. Peter of York,
                  quit-claims to the church and monks of St. Mary, Rievall, all tlie claim he has
                  upon the bounds (divisas) of Welleburn near his land of Nagelt' and Wimbelt', viz.
                  that bound contained in the charters of Roger de Molbrai and Nigel his son ; which
                  bounds, the same Roger with his men and neighbours (vicinas) perambulated and
                  affirmed by oath to be the right bounds of Wellebr', because his men falsely
                  suggested that they belonged to his land of Nagelt and Wimbelt, and being
                  unwilling unjustly to vex the said monks, (<date notBefore="1190" notAfter="1200"
                     precision="low">c. 1190-1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 30*</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Licence from K. Rich. II to the abbey of Rieval to hold a messuage in York of the
                  gift of Roger de Mereton, jun., in mortmain. Dated at Westminster, 13 April, <date>3
                  Rich. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 31</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter (indented) witnessing that John de Euer quit-claims to the abbot and
                  convent of Rievall all his right and claim in the puture of the forester or his
                  servants, for their lands and tenements in Westerdale, also he releases the said
                  abbot and convent of homage for the lands and tenements held of the said John in
                  Little Brocton, Kirkeby, and Clyveland. Dated at Rievall on the octave of St. John
                  the Bapt., <date when="1302">1302</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 32</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Walter, son of Alice, formerly wife of Henry, son of Walter de Ffolketon, grants
                  to the abbey of Rievall, in frankalmoigne, the whole of his meadow in Staynton in
                  the territory of Osgoteby. (<date notBefore="1280" notAfter="1290" precision="low"
                     >c. 1280-90</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 33</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ROCHE ABBEY. William, son of Robert le Plumer of Hymleswrth, remits and
                  quit-claims to the abbot and convent of Roche all right which he has in the land
                  which was Richard's, the son of Thurstan de Balna. (<date notBefore="1250"
                     notAfter="1260" precision="low">c. 1250-60</date>.) 6^.34. <pb n="631"/> YORK.
                  Walter, the abbot, and convent of Roche grant to Robert, eon of Roger de
                  Tyneflowe, for his homage and service, two bovates of land in Bramleye. (<date
                     notBefore="1254" notAfter="1268" precision="low">c. 1254-68</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 35</bibl>. BOSSE. Indenture made 7 March, <date>6 James
                     I</date>, by which sir William Cecill, lord Burghley, grants to sir Robert
                  Dormer, sir John Dormer, and sir William Dormer, an annual rent-charge of 240
                  issuing out of the manor of Rosse in the county of York, for 10 years, or during
                  the lives of sir John Hobart, Barbara his wife, and John their son. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 284*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BOSTON. Baldwin de Wicham and HuglT'son of Hugh, and Roger son of Roger, and
                  Robert son of William, and Ralph Buscell grant to Eustace de Vescy a certain
                  turbary in the territory of Roston which is called 'Ludepaic.' (<date
                     notBefore="1190" notAfter="1200" precision="low">c. 1190-1200</date>.) [With
                  seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 285</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Isabella and Alice, daughters and heirs of Emma la Rus of Roston, grant to Peter,
                  son of Alan de Roston, the whole of their toft in Roston and half of their part of
                  land at Boudalemun, &amp;c. (<date when="1290" precision="low">c. 1290</date>.)
                  [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 286</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, son of Ralph de Ruston, and Sibil his wife grant to Robert le Baker of
                  Aton four cottages lying in Ruston in Pikeringlyth. (c. 1 2 9 o-1 300.) [ With
                  seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 287</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Thomas, son of Robert de Roston, grants to Robert le Baker of Aton and Alice his
                  wife two acres of land in Roston and Wykham. Dated at Roston in Pykeringlyth, 17
                  Oct., <date when="1331">1331</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 288</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Simon de Aton grants to John, son of Ralph the carpenter of Roston, and Tylle his
                  wife one toft in Roston in Pykeringlyth, and one acre and 2 roods of arable land
                  in the same village, &amp;c. Dated at Roston in Pykeringlyth, on Trinity Sunday,
                  133s. [With seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 289</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alan, son of Ralph de Hoton, grants to Simon de Aton lands in Roston and Wyjtham
                  in Pikeringlyth. Dated at Roston in Pikeringlyth, 14 May, <date when="1340"
                     >1340</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 290</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alan, son of Ralph de Hoton, staying in Roston, remits to Simon de Aton all right
                  and claim which he had in one bovate of land in Roston and Wikham in Pikeringlyth.
                  Dated at Roston in Pikeringlyth, 2 August, <date when="1340">1340</date>. [TF^A
                  seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 291</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Alan, son of Ralph de Hoton Buscell, remits and quit-claims to sir Gilbert de
                  Aton all right in a messuage and two bovates of land, with rents and services of
                  the free tenants of Roston and Wikham in Pikeringlyth, Dated at Snaynton the
                  Thursday next after the feast of St. Michael, <date>134317 Ed. III</date>. [With
                  seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 292</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert Passelewe of Ledes grants to sir William de Fynchedene, kt., <pb n="632"/>
                  YORK. sir William de Mirfeld, parson of Bradeforth, William de Mirfeld, Richard de
                  Normanton, vicar of Batelay, Hugh de Wombewelle and William de Geldesome, two
                  tofts and two bovates of land in Ruston. Dated at Ruston the Tuesday next after
                  Palm Sunday, <date>43 Ed. III</date>. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     293</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter (indented) of obligation by which John Staynton is bound in a sum of Xioo
                  to pay to Laurence Kay a sum of 18 marks at the feast of St. John the Baptist
                  next, with other covenants in case of default. Dated n March, <date>12 Henry
                     VI</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 294</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ROTHERHAM. Bull of Pope Innocent V, confirming William Donke in possession of the
                  mediety of the parochial church of Rotherham. Dated 3 Kl. May, 9th of his
                  pontificial year (i.e. <date when="1361">1361</date>). [With Sulla.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 294*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Robert Inkersell grants to sir Thomas Fitzwilliam, kt., Thomas Fitzwilliam his
                  son and heir, Richard Fitzwilliam, Edward Fitzwilliam, esq., Thomas Reresby and
                  John Beit, his capital messuage called Moundesderhall in the parish of Rotherham.
                  Dated at Moundesderhall on the feast of St. Peter in cathedra, <date>2 Hen.
                     VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 295</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> ROTHWELL. Indenture between William Calverley, John Burton, Richard Pek, Water
                  Baildon, and Thomas Gargrave, esqs., feoffees of William Watson, of one part, and
                  George Box, esq., of the other part, witnesseth that the said feoffees have
                  demised to George Box a close and land near Rothwell for six years. Dated 24
                  November, <date>10 Hen. VII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 296</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Inquisition taken on the death of Robert Tailler at Rothwell, dated <date>3
                     Elizabeth</date>. [Held lands at Rothwell and Leeds] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     297</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SALDEN. Robert de Arturret, son of Ralph de Beremund, surrenders Bernard de Ripel
                  and his heirs to his lord Eustace de Vescy and his heirs to make to him and his
                  heirs the service of a I3th part of one knight's fee for two carucates of land
                  which he gave him in Salden. (<date notBefore="1190" notAfter="1200"
                     precision="low">c. 1190-1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 298</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Thomas Chaymang of Brunton grants to Thomas de Dales, staying in Salden, that
                  land which he has at Fukedal which extends from the valley of Salden to the ....
                  of Buttes. (<date when="1290" precision="low">c. 1290</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 299</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William Portar, staying in Saldan, grants to sir Gilbert de Aton all his goods
                  and chattels in a certain messuage in Saldan in Pykeringlyth. Dated at Saldan, 6
                  January, 9 Ed. HI. [ With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 300</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Sir William de Aton, kt., sen., appoints sir Richard de Hoton,. chaplain, his
                  attorney to receive for him and in his name of Richard fitz -William of Salden in
                  Pykeringlyth seisin of one acre of land, as is contained in a certain writing.
                  Dated at Aton in Pykeringlyth the Tuesday after the feast of the translation of
                  St. Thomas, <date>3 Rich. II</date>. [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     301</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="633"/> SCARBOROUGH. William de Tothale, prior of the hospital of St. John
                  of Jerusalem, grants to the friars minor of Scartheburg one messuage in
                  Scartheburg. Dated at Helcheburn on St. Barnabas' day, <date when="1300"
                     >1300</date>. [TT^A seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 303*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SEDBERGH. The foundation charter and ordinances of the grammar school of
                  Sedbergh, containing the signatures of K. Ed. VI, R. Somerset, T. Cant., R. Ryche,
                  W. Wilteshr, L. Bedford, W. Northt, E. Clynton, T. Darcy, G. Cobham, T. Ely. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 302</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SETONE. William le Wasteneys, lord of Bressingburg, appoints Richard de
                  Herelthorp and William Artebrende his attorneys to place sir John de Lalford in
                  full and peaceable possession of all lands and tenements &amp;c. in the village of
                  Setone. Dated at Coltone in co. Stafford, the Monday next after the feast of St.
                  Andrew, <date>4 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 303</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SOWTHOWROME. Thomas Lacy of Crumwelbothome, esq., grants to Richard Mylner of
                  Halyfaxe two parcels of land called Sydale, parcel of the demesne of Sowthowrome.
                  Dated at Sowthowrome, 26 July, <date>22 Ed. IV</date>. [With seal.] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 304</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SPENYTHORNE. Extract from the plea roll <date when="1258">1258</date>, co. York,
                  held at Westminster, Hilary term, 6 George I. The chancellor &amp;c. of the
                  University of Cambridge against sir Marmaduke Wybill, bart., and Anthony Routh,
                  concerning the right of presentation to the church of Spenythorne. [Mutilated.]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 304*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STANLAY. John, son of John Mous of Wakefeud, grants to John le Botiller, staying
                  there, one acre of land in the fields of Stanley. Dated at Wakefeud the Friday
                  next after the feast of St. Mark, evang., <date>23 Ed. I</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 305</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John de Fery de Wakefeld grants to John, son of Robert of the same place, and
                  Joan his wife one acre of land in Stanlay near Fimane brigge. Dated at Wakefield
                  the Wednesday next before the feast of Easter, <date when="1314">1314</date>. [
                  With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 306</bibl></p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Convention indented and dated 25 . . . . <date when="1347">1347</date>, between
                  Robert, eon of John de Wakefeld, of one part, and Matilda, who was the wife of
                  John la Reyde of Stanlay, of the other, by which the said Robert demises to
                  Matilda one toft &amp;c. lying in the village of Stanlay. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 307</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STOKESLEY. Adam Cok of Bubwhyth and Agnes his wife grant to John de Hornly and
                  Cecilia his wife a messuage in the village of Stokesley in Cliveland. Dated at
                  Stokesley the Wednesday next after the feast of St. William, archbishop of York,
                     <date when="1344">1344</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 307*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, eon of Simon the smith of Stokesley, remits and quit<pb n="634"/>claims
                  to sir John de Eure, kt., all right he had in one burgage lying in Stokesley.
                  Dated at Stokesley the "Wednesday next after the feast of the translation of St.
                  Thomas, <date>21 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 308</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture between sir Ralph de Eure, kt., of the one part, and William Colynson
                  of the other part, witnesseth, .... <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 309</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> STUBBUSEM. Adam, son and heir of William de Stubbusem, grants to Matilda his
                  sister four acres of land in Stubbusem. (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 310</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SUNKTNGTHWAYT Priory. Matilda de Hornington grants to the nuns of Sunningthwayt,
                  in frankalmoigne, the whole of her land of Neuryding in Mensington, together with
                  pasture in Mensington for 20 cows and one bull, for 20 mares and one stallion, for
                  10 sows and one boar, and for 40 goats and 100 sheep, with their young of 3 years
                  old. (<date when="1230" precision="low">c. 1230</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 76</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> BUTTON. Stephen Lungespeye grants to Philip de Wappele 17^ acres and one rood of
                  arable land in the fields of Sutton. (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 311</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture (reciting a bond of Grace, lately wife of Hugh de Thorp of Thorp near
                  Newerk, for 26 13s. 4^., payable to Robert Merflete, rector of Sutton) fixing
                  payment of the same by certain instalments, when the bond shall become void. Dated
                  the Friday next before the feast of the apostles SS. Simon and Jude, <date
                     when="1424">1424</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 311**</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SWINDON. Grant of administration to Joan Southeron of Swindon, York diocese,
                  widow, of the goods of William Southeron, late of Swindon, deceased, by the
                  Prerogative Court of York. Dated York, 19 Feb., <date when="1576">1576</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 311***</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> TANPIELD (West). Licence from Nicholas, bishop of Chester, to Henry Lodge,
                  deacon, to perform the office of curate in the parish church of West Tanfield,
                  York. Dated 6 June, <date when="1701">1701</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     315*</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> THIKHEVED or THICKET Priory. Robert le Lyndesey of York confirms a donation of
                  los. annual rent from a tenement in Colbergate, York, to the nuns of Thikheved
                  which . . . . de Feryby and Juliana his wife and mother of the said Robert had
                  granted to them for 14 years. Dated at York the Saturday next after the feast of
                  St. Nicholas, bp., <date>8 Ed. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 77</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> THORPE (Manor of, in Balne). Articles of agreement (indented) made 20 September,
                     <date when="1632">1632</date>, between the lady Philadelphia Wharton, mother of
                  Philip, lord Wharton, of one part, and Rowland Wandesford of Lincoln's Inn, co.
                  Middlesex, esq., of the other, for securing certain settlements on the marriage of
                  the said Philip, lord Wharton, with Elizabeth Wandesford. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 311*</bibl> . WAKEPIELD. Peter, son of Robert de Bruer, Nicholas de <pb
                     n="635"/> Batelay, Adam son of Walter of Wakefeld, and Jordan le Mower of the
                  same, are bound to John, son of Robert the mercer of Wakefeld, in 53s. 4cZ., to be
                  levied on their goods and chattels if Ellen, daughter and heir of Thomas, son of
                  Thomas Dade of Wakefeld, or other of his heirs, claim a third part of a burgage in
                  Wakefeld. Dated at Wakefeld on the feast of All Souls, <date>4 Ed. I</date>. [With
                  seals.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 312</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> A licence granted to John Howssone of Wakefeud by John de Warenne of exemption to
                  beer-tasters entering his house. Dated Friday after the octave of Easter, <date>7
                     Ed. I</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 313</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Letters patent dated at Walden, i September, <date>35 Hen. VIII</date>, in
                  consideration of a sum of 215. a licence of alienation is granted to Richard
                  Andrews and William Romsden for property in Wakefeld, formerly belonging to the
                  monastery of Monkebretton. [With great seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                  336</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Adam, son of Robert de Wyrenthorp, grants to Robert, son of John de Wakefeld, all
                  and singular the messuages, tofts, crofts, lands, tenements, &amp;c. of Stanlay,
                  and one tenement in Wakefeld. Dated at Wakefeld the Friday next after the feast of
                  the Purification, <date when="1343">1343</date>. [With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 314</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WENTWORTH. Administration granted by Henry, archbishop of York, to John del Wod
                  and Joan his wife of the goods &amp;c. of William Wyntworth of Wyntworth,
                  deceased. Dated at Cawod, 3 August, <date when="1313">1313</date>. [With seal]
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 315</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WHITBY (Abbey of). Lease from the Crown granted to Christopher Pykarde of the
                  chapel of Newton, in Cleveland under Oversbury, part of the rectory of Ingleby,
                  and late belonging to the monastery of Whitby, for 21 years, at an annual rent of
                  33s. 46?., the reversion of which together with the rent granted to William, lord
                  Eure. Dated 27 July, 17 Q. Elizabeth. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 36</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WIKHAM, &amp;c. Juliana Galiz of Roston quit-claims to John de Aton one acre and
                  a half of meadow near Derewente, and \ acre of arable land to the east of Wikham,
                  and \ acre in Soldale. (<date when="1250" precision="low">c. 1250</date>.) [With
                  seal] Ch 316. Ralph Bucel quit-claims and confirms to Gilbert de Aton two bovates
                  of land in the territory of Wicham and Drostun. (<date when="1210" precision="low"
                     >c. 1210</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 317</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William, lord of Aton, grants to John Scote of Wycham a certain toft in Wycham,
                  and also half an acre of land in the same village for his life. (<date
                     notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c. 1270-80</date>.) [With
                  seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 318</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> William de Hatterberg, staying in Wycham, grants to sir William de Aton and his
                  heirs i2d. of annual rents which he was accustomed to pay to him for a part of
                  land in Wycham. (<date notBefore="1270" notAfter="1280" precision="low">c.
                     1270-80</date>.) [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 318*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WILBESAYE. William, son of Jordan de Vilbesaye, grants to William de Swinelington
                  and his heirs the whole of his land in the village of Vilbesaye. (<date
                     when="1220" precision="low">c. 1220</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     319</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="636"/> WINTON. John, son of Richard Barbot, grants to Reyner, son of
                  William de "Wambuelle, one bovate of land in the village of Winton. (<date
                     notBefore="1230" notAfter="1240" precision="low">c. 1230-40</date>.) <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 320</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WOMBWELL. Roger, son of Robert the sadler of Wambwell, grants to Matilda his
                  sister, for her life, a toft and a croft and 5^ roods of land. Dated at Wambwell
                  on the feast of St. John ante Port. Lat., <date when="1324">1324</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 321</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> WYLBEBPOSSE (Priory of). Indenture dated 2 May, <date>25 Hen. VIII</date>, by
                  which Elizabeth, prioress, and the convent of Our Lady of Wylberfosse demise to
                  Jorge Adayll, husbandman, their ferm in Semer, with 3 cottages, 4 oxgayngs of
                  arable land, &amp;c., for 31 years, at a yearly rent of 415. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 84</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Bond entered into by G.eorge Dayll of Semer and others in a sum of 10 to keep the
                  covenants of a certain lease made 2 May, <date>25 Hen. VIII</date>, between the
                  said George and Elizabeth prioress of Wilberfosse. Dated 2 May, <date>25 Hen.
                     VIII</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 85</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YOKEPLETE, BROMPTON, WESTOWE, and BILL YNGTOET. Letters patent of Q. Elizabeth,
                  dated at Gorambury, 20 Jan., 15 of her reign, reciting a grant to sir John Foster,
                  kt., of certain lands and tenements in Little Broughton in co. York, bearing date
                  12 April, 10 of her reign, for 40 years, parcel of the lands of the monastery of
                  Hexhame, and by these granting to William lord Ewre the manor of Yokeflete and all
                  that belongs to it in the parishes or hamlets of Yokeflete, Brompton, Westowe, and
                  Rillyngton, together with the reversion of the above grant, also an annual rent of
                  12 i8s. %\d., also the rectory of Inglebie, co. York, and the chapel and church of
                  Newton with all that belongs to them, late part of the priory of Whitby, with many
                  other properties, to hold the same for ever. [With seal.} * <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 337</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YOBK. William, son of Reynard Sporri of York, confirms to John de Housom, citizen
                  and merchant of York, one plot of land in Hertergate way in the city of York for
                  ever, at an annual rent of 55. Dated at York the Wednesday on the feast of the
                  apostles SS. Philip and James, <date when="1325">1325</date>
                  <date>18 Ed. II</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 322</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Nicholas de Appelby, citizen of York, remits and quit-claims to Richard de
                  Brakenthuait and Agnes his wife all right in a certain messuage in Bontham. Dated
                  at York, 20 Nov., <date when="1336">1336</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     323</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Final concord made at Westminster on the octave of the Purification of the
                  Blessed Virgin, 50 Edw. Ill, between John de Berden of York> John Brathwayt of the
                  same, and William de Brumpton, plaintiffs, and John de Westiby of York, butcher,
                  and Alice his wife, defendants, concerning the half of a messuage in York. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 324</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Indenture made 12 Jan., <date when="1603">1603</date>, by which Mathew,
                  archbishop of <pb n="637"/>York, leases to Edward Croft of the city of York a
                  messuage or tenement in the flesh shambles of the city of York. [ With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 334</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Probate of the will of Stephen Todd of York, gent., dated 4 March, *653, and
                  granted to Anne Todd, relict and sole executrix. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     325</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> A certificate of Thomas, archbp. of York, that in the register of John de
                  Thoresby his predecessor, Thomas de Saltmersse, deacon and acolyte, the Saturday
                  on the vigil of St. Matthew, apostle, <date when="1371">1371</date>, in the old
                  church of St. Mary, York, was admitted sub-deacon, and the Saturday in the first
                  week of Quadragesima, same year and place, was admitted presbyter by the venerable
                  Richard, then suffragan. Dated at York, 12 June, <date when="1392">1392</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 327</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YORK (St. Mary's Abbey of). R. de Appeltun grants to the abbot and monks of St.
                  Mary of York, two bovates of land in Appeltun. (<date when="1200" precision="low"
                     >c. 1200</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 37</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Wimarca, daughter of Gervase the constable, remits and quit-claims to the church
                  of St. Mary of York and the monks there, all right in a certain tenement, &amp;c.
                  [Partly obliterated.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 38</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter by which , rector of Kirkeby in Hindoldale, grants to the abbot and
                  convent of St. Marie of York, the whole of that plot which he had of the gift of L
                  ays de Pokelington in Boicchom. Dated 133-. [Mutilated.] <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 39</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YORK (Priory of Holy Trinity). At a court of the venerable Robert Halowe, prior
                  of the Holy Trinity, York, held 16 October, <date>10 Hen. VII</date>, came
                  Katherine , widow, and took of the lord a certain parcel of waste ip Kyrkgate to
                  hold to her and her assigns, paying annually Sd. [Memorandum] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 78</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YORK (Priory of St. Clement). Lord Peter de Percy confirms and quit-claims to God
                  and the nuns of St. Clement the whole of that area which is against their gate
                  towards the north, (<date notBefore="1250" notAfter="1260" precision="low">c.
                     1250-60</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 79</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Nicholas, son and heir of Ernisius ad Barram de "Walmegate, grants to Agues de
                  Wyten, prioress of St. Clement, York, his right and claim to the whole of his
                  lands and edifices in Walmegate in the suburbs of York. (<date when="1280"
                     precision="low">c. 1280</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 80</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YORK (Convent of White Friars). Grant from Mauger, prior of the White Friars of
                  York, to Roger Low, of the right of participation in the prayers of the convent
                  during his life, and commemoration after death. Dated at York, 8 Kl. April, <date
                     when="1387">1387</date>. Ch. Si. Grant from Robert, prior of the White Friars
                  of York, to Richard Wade and Joan his wife of the right and benefit to and in the
                  prayers of the convent during their lives, and commemoration after their death.
                  Dated <date when="1473">1473</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 82</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="638"/> Grant from John, prior of the Carmelites of York, to sir John
                  Hodghsone, chaplain, and his parents and others of the right of participation in
                  the prayers of the convent during life and commemoration after death. Dated on the
                  feast of St. John, evang., <date when="1520">1520</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Ch. 83</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YORK (Hospital of St. Leonard). "William de Kirtelington, chaplain, grants to the
                  poor of the hospital of St. Leonard, York, all his lands and tenements which he
                  holds of the said hospital in the village of Kirtelington. Dated at York, 1 1
                  April, 26 Ed. I. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 107</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter dated <date>29 Ed. I</date>, the Friday on the feast of St. Katherine the
                  virgin, at York, being a convention between Walter, bp. of Coventry and Lichfield,
                  master of the hospital of St Leonard, York, and Roger, abbot of Melsa, concerning
                  two mills (water) in Great Wharrum. [With seal.] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch.
                     108</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YORK (Hospital of St. Peter at). Grant from Paul, the master, and the convent of
                  St. Peter, York, to the canons of St. Mary, Bolton, of their land in Bleistreta in
                  York, paying annually 1 2d. and husgavel for all services. (<date notBefore="1200"
                     notAfter="1220" precision="low">c. 1200-20</date>.) [With seal] <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 106</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Crispin de Bramham, with the assent of Cecilia his wife, grants to the poor of
                  the hospital of St. Peter, York, in frankalmoigne, three acres of land in the
                  fields of Bramham and one toft in Bramham and common of pasture in the same
                  village, (<date notBefore="1200" notAfter="1210" precision="low">c.
                  1200-10</date>.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 105</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> John Apylton, receiver of sir Robert Bolneden, treasurer of the cathedral church
                  of St. Peter, York, received of Edward Dole and John Sallnam, esq., 20 marks
                  sterling in part payment of a greater sum. Dated at York, 22 October, <date>9 Hen.
                     VI</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 106*</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Charter dated 5 April, <date when="1375">1375</date>, by which sir William de
                  Atoun the father, in the presence of the sire de Percy, challenged sir Robert de
                  Boneton on account of the arms he bore, namely, Or, on a cross sable five
                  bullocks' heads argent, which had been a ground of controversy, and was submitted
                  to the sire de Percy, who after deliberation adjudged the arms to belong to
                  William de Atoun, who grants the same to Robert de Boneton and his heirs for ever.
                  [With seal] <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 335</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> An indenture made the loth of April, 25th year of Q. Elizabeth, between the rt.
                  hon. William lord Eure of the one part, and Richard Medd, Robert Bell, and
                  Christabell White, of the second part, witnesseth that lord Eure has demised to
                  Richard Medd, Robert Bell, and Christabell White two closes called Potter's and
                  White's closes, with a cottage, for 2 1 years, or during the life of Ralph Eure,
                  son and heir of lord Eure. <bibl type="shelfmark">Ch. 2</bibl> 1 . Blank
                  commission, signed H. Newcastle, for the appointment . . . in the Trained Bands, .
                  . . Riding of York. 4 K. James II <date when="1688">1688</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Ch. 326</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="639"/> ALLERTONSHIRE. Subsidy roll for part of Allertonshire. Temp. Chas.
                  I. <bibl type="shelfmark">Yorkshire Rolls, i</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> EMELDON, SHEPLEIGH, STANFORD, DONSTANBURGH, and PIKERING. The accounts of the
                  provosts, &amp;c. of the villages comprising the barony of Emeldon and the
                  lordship of Pickeringlyth pertaining to the duchy of Lancaster, from the 24th to
                  the 25th of Edward III. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 2</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> PYCKERING. i. The account of John Harding, provost of Pickering, from Michaelmas,
                  1 <date>5 Ed. I</date>ll, to the same feast, 1 <date>6 Ed. III</date>. 2. The
                  account of William Broune, provost of Esyngwold, from Michaelmas, <date>15 Ed.
                     I</date>ll, to the same feast, <date>16 Ed. III</date>. 3. The account of Ralph
                  Hastings, receiver of Pickering, from the 1 5th to the 1 6th of Ed. III. Rotts, 3.
                  The account of Alan Scot, herdsman there, from Michaelmas, <date>45 Ed.
                  I</date>ll, to the 46th, for one year. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 4</bibl>.
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The account of John Raufson, provost, from Michaelmas, <date>45 Ed. I</date>ll,
                  to the 46th, for one year. The account of William de Thurneyst, bailiff there,
                  from Michaelmas, <date>45 Ed. I</date>ll, to the 46th, for one year. The account
                  of Robert de Pokley, provost there, from Michaelmas, <date>45 Ed. I</date>ll, to
                  the 46th, for one year. The account of sir Ralph Assheton, kt., receiver, from
                  Michaelmas, <date>7 Ed. IV</date>, to the same feast, <date>8 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 5</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Roll of 2 membranes : 1 . The account of William West, provost of Pykering, from
                  Michaelmas, 1 <date>1 Ed. IV</date>, to the same feast, 1 <date>2 Ed. IV</date>.
                  2. The account of sir Edward Hastyngs, kt., bailiff of Pykering, from Michaelmas,
                  1 <date>1 Ed. IV</date>, to the same feast, 1 <date>2 Ed. IV</date>. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 6</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Roll of two membranes : 1. The account of John Kempe, provost of the manor of
                  Pykering, from Michaelmas, <date>16 Ed. IV</date>, to the same feast, <date>17 Ed.
                     IV</date>. 2. The account of sir Ed. Hastings, kt., bailiff of Pykering, from
                  Michaelmas, <date>16 Ed. IV</date>, to the same feast, <date>17 Ed. IV</date>.
                     <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 7</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The account of Robert Clay, provost, from Michaelmas, <date>22 Ed. IV</date>, to
                     <date>i Rich. III</date>. Also the account of sir Edmund Hastyngs, kt.,
                  bailiff, for the same year. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 8</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> * The account of Nicholas Lewnthorp, receiver of the king, from Michaelmas, i
                  Ric. Ill, to the same feast, <date>2 Ric. III</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 9</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Roll of 5 membranes, being The account of ... Reeve, from Michaelmas, 1 <date>8
                     James I</date>, to the 1 9th, for one year, for Pykering. <bibl
                     type="shelfmark">Rolls, 10</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p>
                  <pb n="640"/> SKYRAKE, (Wapentake of). Subsidy roll, dated 1 2th February,
                     <date>37 Hen. VIII</date>, for the wapentake of Skyrak, being the first subsidy
                  granted by act of Parliament in the 37th of his reign. (4 membranes.) JRolls, n.
                  Roll of three membranes, being Estreat indented, dated 1 1 March, <date>7 James
                     I</date>, between sir Thomas Fairfax and sir Henry Groodrick, kts.,
                  commissioners appointed for the wapentake of Skyracke, for assessing and levying
                  and collecting the second payment of the third subsidy granted in the <date>3
                     James I</date>, of one part, and Gilbert Kirke of Cowkricke, high collector, of
                  the other part. Payment to be made into the Exchequer on or before ist day of May
                  next. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 12</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YORK (City of). The account of Thomas Beverlay, William Crathorn, and John
                  Marton, chamberlains of the city of York, time of John Croyser, mayor, of receipts
                  and payments in their office from the feast of St. Blasius, <date>25 Hen.
                     VI</date>, to the same feast, <date>26 Hen. V</date>L <bibl type="shelfmark"
                     >Rolls, 13</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Part of a roll, with heading and side cut away, of the expenses of the Court of
                  Common Council for the city of York. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 14</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> The account of John Lee, fyssher, and George Hutchousen, baker, burgomasters, of
                  Ffossebrig, from the feast of St. Maurice, abbot, the <date>32 Hen. VIII</date>,
                  to the same feast, <date>33 Hen. VIII</date>, in the time of Robt. Halle,
                  merchant, mayor of York. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 15</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> Instructions to Thomas Viscount Savile, baron of Pontefract and Castlebar,
                  president of the councell of the north, and others therein named appointed to be
                  of the same councell, to be observed by them and every of them. (Roll of four
                  membranes.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 1 6</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> SHERIFF'S Roll. The great roll of the Exchequer for the county of York, being the
                  sheriff's account for the pth year of Q. Anne. William Nevile, esq., being sheriff
                  that year, and William Whitehead his deputy. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls,
                     17</bibl>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> YORKSHIRE and DURHAM. A return of the passing of various fee farm rents, parcel
                  of the dissolved monasteries, from the Crown to various persons, extracted from a
                  book as attested by ' Robert Paddon,' auditor, Dec. 24, <date when="1610"
                     >1610</date>. <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 18</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charter">
               <p> List of reserved rents from the dissolved monasteries and religious houses of the
                  county of York. (9 membranes.) <bibl type="shelfmark">Rolls, 19</bibl>. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
