<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

            <head>IV. VARIOUS HOUSES. <lb/> M. 1–134.</head>
            <div type="org">
                <head type="heading">Wallingford Priory [Berks.]</head>

                <p>Berks. chs. 1–160 refer to Wallingford. Of these the following have already been
                    fully dealt with in the <hi rend="italic">Calendar of Charters and Rolls in the
                        Bodleian Library,</hi> and have therefore been omitted: nos. 1 (p. 13), 2
                    (p. 6), 3 (p. 14), 6 (p. 14), 7 (p. 15), 13 (p. 6), 15 (p. 15), 17 (p. 15), 23–5
                    (p. 15), 32–5 (p. 16), 36 (p. 14), 38 (p. 16), 41 (p. 4), 44 (p. 17), 45 (p.
                    17), 47 (p. 5), 48–9 (p. 13), 55 (p. 6), 56 (p. 17). 57 (p. 14), 59 (p. 18), 60
                    (p. 14), 62-4 (p. 4). 67 (p. 6), 68 (p. 7), 70 (p. 18), 79–81 (p. 18), 84 (p.
                    13), 86 (p. 8), 87 (p. 19), 89 (p. 8), 90 (p. 8), 91 (p. 19), 94 (p. 19), 95 (p.
                    19), 96 (p. 9). 97-9 (p. 5). 100–1 (p. 9), 103 (p. 9), 104 (p. 19), 105 (p. 9),
                    106 (p. 19), 108 (p. 19), 109 (p. 12), 110–11 (p. 19), 112 (p. 9), 113 (p. 10),
                    114 (p. 12), 117<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> (p. 14), 117<hi rend="superscript"
                        >b</hi> (p. 10), 120 (p. 20), 122 (p. 4), 123 (p. 13), 124 (p. 14), 126 (p.
                    20), 127 (p. 14), 128 (p. 20), 129 (p. 20); 132, 134, 135, 139, 140 (p. 21); 141
                    (p. 12), 144 (p. 5), 145–8 (p. 22), 150–6 (p. 22), 157–60 (p. 23).</p>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Aston Rowant</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Oxon.</hi>)</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 20a</bibl> Hugh de Fonte grants to
                            W., prior &amp;c. of W. in free alms, 6½ acres of arable land in Eston
                            and one rood of meadow in Wynterdole, which John, formerly vicar of
                            Eston, once held from him. Witnesses: Robert of Sumel’, Alexander de
                            Stall[is], Nicholas de Stall[is], William the esquire, Roger the clerk,
                            William the marshal, Nicholas þinbern’. He …, Adam of Aldentone.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1220.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 42a</bibl> Hugh son of Robert of
                            Chalcford, grants to Ralph of Watlingtone, prior &amp;c. of W., in free
                            alms, 2 half acres and one rood of arable land in Eston, in
                            Wodewayforlong. Witnesses: Sir Alan fitz-Rowald, Auger of Rodelan’,
                            Henry … of Chalkeforde, Roger le marssal, Geoffrey Wodewarde.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1270.</supplied>–74.</date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 42b</bibl> The same grants to the
                            same, in free alms, two half acres in Eston in Longeheggesforlong.
                            Witnesses: Sir Baud[ewin] …, Sir Henry le Tyeys, Simon atte more,
                            William Thurburd, … le mareschal, Henry West, Geoffrey the prior’s
                            clerk. <date><supplied>c. 1270.</supplied>–74.</date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="134"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 19</bibl> Indenture by which the
                            priory grants to William de Leukenore 2½ acres of land in Chalcford
                            lying in Medforlang, la Lure, and by Copinghomeweye in exchange for land
                            lying in front of the court of the convent at Chalcford, called
                            Wiþescroft. <gap/> Witnesses: Roger parson of Leukenore, Walter Bacun,
                            Hubert of Hatfeld, Ralph Pol of Sidenham, Adam of Sopicote [Sapcote],
                            William the marshal, Robert de la more, Nicholas Gulias.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1270–74.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 22</bibl> Roger son of Peter of
                            Chalcford grants to W. in free alms a croft called Chalfcroft in
                            Chalcford, except a third part which Isowde, mother of William the
                            marshal holds in dower. Rent 12<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> For this the
                            monks gave him 2½ marks. Witnesses: Thomas of Gingestone, Adam of
                            Copicote, Nicholas the clerk, Hugh of Stockenechun …, Auger de la
                            Redelan’, Robert Melesop, Hugh de la <hi rend="italic">Lip,</hi> Henry
                            son of Peter, Richard son of Nicholas. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1270–74.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 37</bibl> Hugh son of Robert of
                            Chalkford, grants to W. in free alms one acre of arable land in C. in
                            Holewellefurlong. For this sir Ralph of Watlington prior of W. gave him
                            [7/- or 10/-]. Witnesses: sir Geoffrey de Leukenore, steward of the
                            honour of W., sir William Huschal, sir Thomas de Valencis, knights,
                            master Ralph of Belvero (?), Robert de Louches of W., William the
                            marshal, … of Chalcford, William the esquire of the priory of W.,
                            William of Synynes, Geoffrey the clerk of …etinge. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1270–74.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head type="heading">Clapcote</head>

                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 5</bibl> Geoffrey the cook of
                            Wareng’ grants to W. in free alms 7 acres of arable land and all his
                            other land in C., lying in ’peecam de W.’ on the North, free of all
                            secular service, ’ego enim et heredes mei eam acquietabimus per officium
                            nostrum in coquina’ … For this gift made for the souls of Brian
                            fitz-Count, his lord, and the lady Matilda his wife, he has received
                            from the monks 60/-, and his son half a mark. Witnesses: Thomas Balle,
                            Geoffrey de Yvoi, Nicholas son of Turolde, Thomas de Uruvall, Hugh de
                            Yvoi, Ralph of Alu’b, Hamo Purun, Gilbert Basset, Matthew of Sottewelle,
                            Andrew son of Peter, William son of Richard, James son of Nicholas,
                            Andrew the clerk. <date><supplied>1127–50.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="135"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 12</bibl> Gilbert son of Adam the
                            cooper grants to John of Devonshire that messuage in C. which R.
                            treasurer of the Hospital [of S. John] with the consent of the chapter
                            confirmed to Adam the cooper, father of the said Gilbert. Rent 12<hi
                                rend="italic">d.</hi> to the hospital and 1<hi rend="italic">d.</hi>
                            to Gilbert and his heirs. For this John gave him 16 marks. Witnesses:
                            James capellanus de opido, Robert de Bavra, Thomas of Devonshire, Henry
                            de porta, Walter son of Henry, Roger balistarius, John son of Adam the
                            cooper, Asketil the dyer. <date><supplied>c. 1220–30.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 11</bibl> Henry de porta grants to
                            William the clerk of W., for his homage and service one acre of arable
                            land in C. in Koclingforlong. Rent 1<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses:
                            William son of Simon, Nicholas de stall[is], Hubert of Hotfelde, Simon
                            Gurmund, Alexander Dublet, John de Luches, Robert de Bavra, Nicholas de
                            Basinges, Henry son of Ywo, William son of Henry, Gilbert cunarius,
                            Henry the clerk. <date><supplied>c. 1220–30.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 14</bibl> Gilbert de Hande grants
                            to W. and the sacristan, half an acre of land in C. Rent 2<hi
                                rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses: Nicholas de stall[is], Hubert
                            [Ho]tfeld, Clement the clerk, Peter the vintner, Nicholas de Basinges,
                            Henry son of [<gap/>], Simon de Basinges. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1220–30.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 18</bibl> William son of Geoffrey
                            de aula confirms to W. in free alms, the gift of his father, who is
                            buried there, of 5 acres of arable land and one acre of meadow in C.
                            Witnesses: …aller of Sandervile, John of Sottewelle, Miles of Mortone,
                            John le Fleming, John Basset, Alexander Dublet, Nicholas de Stall[is],
                            Clement the clerk, Hubert of Hatfelde. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1230–40.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 1</bibl> Stephen son of Richard de Clopcote
                            grants to Joan, late the daughter of John his son, for her service, 2
                            acres of arable land in C. of which ½ acre lies at Stanidelf between the
                            land of Henry de Furns and that of John son of Nicholas de Basing, ½
                            acre at Sunenhelve on the south of Sir Stephen de Cheynduit’s land, ½
                            acre between the said Sir S. de C.’s land and that of H. de F., towards
                            the north in the shot called Hilond, and ½ acre at Vifaker. Rent: 6<hi
                                rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses: Nicholas de Stall[is], Alexander de
                            Stall[is], John fitz-Nicholas de Basinges, Simon de Basinges, William de
                            aula, Henry fitz-Yvo, Henry son of Walter West, Peter Ywun, Henry de la
                            Barre, Robert son of Walter West, William the clerk. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1235.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="136"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 2</bibl> William son of John de Clopcote
                            confirms to Joan his sister the gift which Stephen her grandfather made
                            to her of two acres of land in C., ½ acre between Sir S. de C.’s land
                            and that of H. de F., reaching to the shot called Inlond, ½ acre at
                            Vifacres, which is the Westernmost of 3 half-acres lying together there,
                            by the land of H. de F. Rent 6<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses:
                            Nicholas the goldsmith, mayor of W., Nicholas de Stallis, Gilbert
                            Cunar’, John de Basinges, Robert de Luches, John de Luches, Walter de
                            Furno, Philip de Basinges, Adam de Cokam, clerk. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1270–80.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 3</bibl> Thomas de la Sale son and heir of
                            William de la Sale grants to Nicholas son of Clement, clerk, for 40/-
                            (1) 2 parts of an acre of arable land in Golasfurlonghetum the land of
                            N. f. C. and the land which Agnes, mother of T. de la S. held in dower,
                            reaching south to the prior’s long acre; (2) ½ acre of arable land in
                            the same shot between the said Agnes’ land on each side. Rent: a
                            gillieflower. Witnesses: Sir John de St. John, William de Mackenaye
                            [Macknay], John de Luchiis, Robert de Sottewelle, Robert de
                            Brihtwaltone, Andrew de Butelor’, John Huberd. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1270–80.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 4</bibl> Matilda relict of John le arblaster
                            of Clopcote grants to William le scheperde and Amye his wife (i) an acre
                            of arable land in C. in the shot called Schyllyngewurthe between the
                            said Matilda’s land and that of Anycya her daughter, reaching to the
                            South to Ruscheweye. (ii) an acre of meadow in the meadow called
                            Hememede. Witnesses: Richard de Louches, Osbert of Notele, Robert of
                            Meleborne, William of Muleborne, Richard atte Char, Alan Rossel,
                            Nicholas atte Barre, Robert Boneface, clerk. Given at C.
                                    <date><supplied>19 Jan. 1310.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 5</bibl> Isabella daughter of John Huberd of
                            C. quit-claims to Cecilia, late the daughter of Simon de Elyntone, her
                            right by inheritance or by reason of Wymarke her mother &amp;c. in one
                            acre of arable land called Leytoneacre, in C., between the land some
                            time of Matilda le arblaster and that of Jordan le carpenter. Witnesses:
                            Swayn of Mortele of W., Richard de Louches of the same, John Mariot of
                            the same, Thomas Gratard of the same, William of Mulebourne of the same.
                            Given at C. <date><supplied>8 April 1316.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 6</bibl> Richard son of John de Basyngges of
                            Wallingford quit-claims to Gilbert the goldsmith (1) 8<hi rend="italic"
                                >d.</hi> rent from William the dyer of W. <pb n="137"/> for land in
                            Clopcote, (2) 1½<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> rent from Henry le Munfort,
                            similarly, (3) 1½<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> rent from Simon … (4) 2<hi
                                rend="italic">d.</hi> from Elena la gardinere, similarly. Witnesses:
                            William Sundy, Nicholas le taverner, John le gredere, John de Louches,
                            Gilbert du char, Nicholas le Bercher, Roger the clerk. Given at
                            Wallingford. [<hi rend="italic">Partly effaced.</hi>] <date><supplied>1
                                    July 1316.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 61</bibl> Osbert son and heir of
                            Thomas le ferror of W. grants to Richard de Louches of W. his right in 2
                            crofts of arable land in C., viz. one lying above la Lhinche, the other
                            at Pute … s. Witnesses: Robert of Sottewelle, Rolond of Hastang, Robert
                            of Makkeneye, John atte Forteye of Astone, William of Lattone, Robert
                            Boneface. Given at C. <date><supplied>27 Dec. 1320.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 7</bibl> Roger son and heir of John le porter
                            of Wallingford grants to William Soundy of W. 2 acres 1 rood of meadow
                            in the North meadow of Clopcote, ’sicut sors annuatim condonat.’
                            Witnesses: Richard de Louches, John Mariot, Robert of Sottewelle,
                            Gilbert atte char, Alan Rossel, William of Mulebourne, Thomas le Noble,
                            John de Louches, Thomas of Berewyk, William Arnyat, Walter le cripse,
                            William Buty. Given at C. <date><supplied>9 July 1323.</supplied></date>
                            Small circular seal, in black wax; a squirrel, <hi rend="smallcap">S’
                                WILLELMI</hi> … </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 69</bibl> Richard son and heir of
                            John de Louches, of W., quit-claims to William Blakemer of Cokham and
                            Cecilia his wife, his right in one acre of land in Clopcote, which
                            Cecilia had of the gift of Jordan Huberd of C., and which lies between
                            the land of Jordan le carpenter and that of Ralph le arblaster, and is
                            called la Leightone acre. Witnesses: John de Louches, brother of the
                            grantor, Sweyn of Mortleye, Walter of Basinges, Walter le carpenter (?),
                            … son of Osbert of Notelee, Thomas Dene, Gilbert du char. Given at W.
                                    <date><supplied>16 March 1325.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 8</bibl> Indenture by which Benedict de
                            Glaunvyle of Wallingford grants to William de Suthmortone, clerk, a
                            piece of arable land called La Gore, outside the west gate of W. in the
                            field of Clopcote, with the adjacent head-acre between the highroad and
                            the field called Hongerhulle, the said Gore extending towards Sottewelle
                            Crouche, from 21 Dec., 1324 to Mich. next, and then for 11 years.
                            Witnesses: Robert of Sottewelle, Richard de Louches, Alan Rossel of
                            Clopcote, Nicholas le coupere, Thomas of Oterborne, Gilbert du char,
                            Walter le crypse. Given at Clopcote. <date><supplied>21 Dec.
                                    1324.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="138"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 9</bibl> Benedict de Glaunvyle of Wallingford
                            grants to William de Suthmortone, clerk, a head acre of arable land ’que
                            est forera’, lying in Clopcote between B. de G.’s land and that of the
                            prior of W., reaching north to Hongerhulle. <gap/> Witnesses: Richard de
                            Louches, John atte Forteye de Astone, junior, Robert of Sottewelle,
                            Robert of Makkeneye, Nicholas of Medford, Gilbert atte char, Alan Rossel
                            of C., Robert Boneface, clerk. Given at C. <date><supplied>13 Jan.
                                    1326.</supplied></date> Seal. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 10</bibl> Alan Russel grants to Richard his
                            son and Helen a daughter of William Blakemor, one acre of arable land
                            called Le ettonacur, in C., between the land of Jordan le carpenter on
                            the east, and that late of Agnes Ricote on the West, reaching on the
                            south to the said Jordan’s garden, and to the north to the land of
                            William le Schepherde and the land of John le Gredere. Witnesses: Robert
                            Butti, John Witing, Gilbert le char, Nicholas le coupare, Thomas of
                            Hoturboune, Walter le cripse, Simon Kenhelm. Given at C.
                                    <date><supplied>4 Nov. 1325.</supplied></date> Seal: pointed
                            oval, 1”, head of a man in armour, <hi rend="smallcap">S’ ALANI ·
                                ROSSEL.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 11</bibl> John son of Osbert of Notlee of
                            Wallingford grants to Walter le Cripse of W. one acre lying in Clopcote
                            at Le Vifacres between Walter le crispe’s land on the east and the
                            grantor’s land on the west. <gap/> Witnesses: Sweyn of Mortele, Roger
                            Badecok, John Whitynge, William Boty, Alan Russel, Symon Kenelm, John of
                            Blebury, Gilbert du char, Robert Boty. Given at Clopcote.
                                    <date><supplied>13 Nov. 1326.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 12</bibl> John son of Osbert of Notele of W.
                            and heir of Agnes daughter of Nicholas Clement, grants to Walter le
                            cripse of the same two ½ acres of arable land in C. (Boundaries.)
                            Witnesses: Richard de Louches, Swayn of Mortele, Gilbert du char, John
                            of Blebury, William le ferur, Simon Kynelm, Roger the clerk. <gap/>
                            Given at C. <date><supplied>8 July 1327.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 13</bibl> Indenture by which Roger Badecok of
                            W. grants to Alice his daughter 5 scattered acres of arable land in C.
                            by Wallingford, (1) is forera, at la Punde by Thomas le Arblaster’s land
                            on the south, reaching east to la Greneweye which leads to Hodesbot, (2)
                            between the land late of Sir William de Bereford, kt., on either side,
                            reaching to William of Melebourne’s land towards the north <pb n="139"/>
                            Mill, and called la Forsshetase, (3) ½ acre between the land late of
                            Henry Ywon on either side, at le Flexlond, reaching to the lynche
                            towards Shillingford bridge, ½ acre between the land of William le
                            Deyar’, merchant, and that of Henry Ywon, reaching to the said lynche,
                            (4) in the shot called Stomforlong between Eustace Clements’ land and
                            that of Richard de Louches, (5) one acre in Middelforlong between the
                            land late of Richard du char and that of Thomas le arblaster, reaching
                            to le Russhepathe towards the west. Rent: 10 qrs. of barley. Witnesses:
                            Richard de Louches, John son of Osbert of Notele, William Badecoke,
                            Gilbert du char, Walter le cripse, Thomas son of Alan Rossel, Thomas
                            Bone. Given at W. <date><supplied>1 Nov. 1327.</supplied></date> Berks.
                            ch. 69b. is the other half of this indenture. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 14</bibl> Roger Badecoke of W. quit-claims to
                            John son of Roger of Blebury of W. and Alice his wife and R. B.’s
                            daughter, those ten quarters rent [see M. 13]. Given at W. Witnesses:
                            Swayn. of Morteley, John Mariot, Thomas Bone, William Badecoke, Richard
                            Gratard, Roger of Mortone, Roger son of Nicholas the weaver.
                                    <date><supplied>8 April 1331.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 71</bibl> John, son of Osbert of
                            Notle of W., grants to John of Wy … of All Saints, W., one acre of
                            arable land in C., in Middelforlong. Witnesses: Gilbert du char, Walter
                            le crypse, Thomas of 0[tterburne], Peter son of Alan Rossel, [<gap/>]
                            called of Meleborne, inkeeper, John of Poleham, Simon Kynelm, Robert
                            Boneface, clerk. Given at C. <date><supplied>8 April
                                1329.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 72</bibl> William Badecok of W.
                            grants to Walter Crypse a toft with arable land adjacent, lying between
                            the said Walter’s land on the north, and the garden which belonged to
                            Sir William de Bereford by Wallingford castle on the south, in the
                            village of C., reaching from the high road on the west to the barbican
                            of the castle on the east. It is 28 feet wide by the road, and 68 feet
                            by the barbican; length 55 and 58 feet. Witnesses: Richard de Louches:
                            Gilbert du char, Thomas Aleyn, Simon Kenelm, Nicholas le coupere. Given
                            at C. <date><supplied>6 Feb. 1331.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 73</bibl> Indenture by which Walter
                            le crypse grants to William of Melbourn of the county of Leicester 12<hi
                                rend="italic">d.</hi> rent of an acre of arable land in C., lying at
                            Gourishesdene. Witnesses: Sweyn of Mortleye, Gilbert du char, Thomas
                            Aleyn, Simon Kenelm, Nicholas le coupere. Given at C. <date><supplied>23
                                    April 1331.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="140"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 75</bibl> John of Notele son of
                            Osbert of Notele of W., grants to the priory all his lands, goods, and
                            chattels in W., or C., or elsewhere. Witnesses: Richard Moryn, mayor,
                            Richard de Lusches, Richard Wyting’, John [ ? constable] of Wallingford
                            castle, Thomas Aleyn, Thomas of Otterburne, Gilbert de Char of C. Given
                            at W. <date><supplied>29 Sept. 1333.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 76</bibl> William son of William
                            the marshal of W., grants to William March Heron, prior, &amp;c. of W. 8
                            acres of arable land in C. viz. 3 acres in or abutting on Algarsforlong,
                            ½ acre in le Inlond, between the Shillingford road on the West and le
                            Rysshepathe on the east, 1 acre at Gykendene, 1½ acres Tounforlong, ½
                            acre in le Thistelforlong, ½ acre in Westlingforlong. Witnesses: Richard
                            de Louches, Gilbert du char, Thomas Aleyn, Thomas of Oterburne, Walter
                            Crips, William Knight, clerk. Given at C. <date><supplied>12 March
                                    1334.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 77</bibl> The same to the same: 5
                            acres of arable land in C., viz: 2½ acres at le Pende; 1½ acre in
                            Cockleforlong, 1 acre in Middelforlong. Witnesses: Richard Moryn, mayor,
                            Richard de Louches, Gilbert du Char, Thomas Alayn, Walter Crips,
                            Nicholas le coupere, Thomas of Oterburne, William Knight, clerk. Given
                            at C. <date><supplied>12 March 1334.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 78</bibl> Alan of Goldeburghe
                            grants to William Heron, prior &amp;c. of W. 7½ acres of arable land in
                            C., and an acre of meadow, viz.: ½ acre at Hongerhulle, ½ acre in le
                            Flexlonde, above le Pende, 2 acres in Algarsforlong, 1 acre at la
                            Grodelonde, above Algarsforlong, ½ acre near the Shillingford road, 1
                            acre at Gondricheshulle, 1 acre in Middelforlong (½ acre of which
                            reaches la Rysshepathe), ½ acre not specified, ½ acre in the common
                            meadow ’prout sors condonet annuatim in sorte Alicie Reynaudyn’, ½ acre
                            similarly ’in sorte Ricardi de Louches’. Witnesses: [as in no 77,
                            without Nicholas le coupere]. Given at C. <date><supplied>Same
                                    date.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 15</bibl> Indenture witnessing that John son
                            of Eustace Randoulf of W. has enfeoffed Andrew de Sutton of the same
                            with 2 acres of arable land in C. in the shot called Le Puynde between
                            Sir Edmund de Bereford’s land on the north and that of Richard Moryn of
                            W. on the south, reaching above Westweye on the east, and towards the
                            west to Monekedene. If John pays Andrew 40/- in 6 years the grant shall
                            be null. Witnesses: Richard Moryn, <pb n="141"/> Robert Butty, Robert of
                            Makkeneye, William Barefot, Gilbert du Char, Walter le Cripse, Thomas
                            Aleyn. Given at C. <date><supplied>23 Aug. 1335.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 82</bibl> Richard de Louches grants
                            to Wm. Heron, prior &amp;c. of W., a croft in C. at le Lynches.
                            Witnesses: Roger ate Nasshe, steward of Wallingford castle, Richard
                            Moryn, mayor, Robert Wityn, John Mariot, Gilbert du char, Thomas of
                            Oterburne. Given at C. <date><supplied>19 April 1336.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 16</bibl> Robert Butti of W. grants to
                            William of Mulleburne called the taverner of W. a toft of arable land in
                            C. reaching to the highroad from Wallingford to Dorchester on the west.
                            Witnesses: Richard Moryn, John Maryot, Gilbert du char, Thomas Alayn,
                            Thomas of Oturbourne. Given at W. <date><supplied>14 April
                                    1336.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 17</bibl> Henry le Veysin of Warborwe grants
                            to Walter Stephenes son William S., of C., and Elisia his wife, daughter
                            of John Saleber of Warborwe, 4 acres of arable land in C., at the Lynch,
                            in Middelforlonge, and over Clapcotehulle, (Boundaries). Witnesses:
                            Ralph Restweld, Richard de Louches, Alan Rossel, Gilbert atte char,
                            Robert Boneface. Given at C. <date>Wed. after St. Clem ent, 13 or 17 Ed.
                                III.</date> Seal. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 18</bibl> Indenture witnessing that John son
                            of Eustace Randolf of Wallingford has enfeoffed John atte Rysshe of the
                            same with the 2 acres mentioned in M. 15 on the same condition.
                            Witnesses: William Barefote, Walter Whatinod, Roger atte Mulle, Robert
                            of Mackeney, John Ruydale, Gilbert atte char, Robert of Toppefeld,
                            clerk. Given at C. <date><supplied>22 Oct. 1339.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 18a</bibl> The deed of gift of the same to
                            the same. Same date and witnesses. Blunted oval seal, ⅔”, a spread eagle
                            rising out of foliage. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 19</bibl> John Maryot of W. grants to John
                            ate Russche of the same, one acre of arable land in C. in Medforlong,
                            between William de Cornwaille’s land on the north, and that late of
                            Matilda Daynes on the south. Witnesses: Robert Butty, Philip de Louches,
                            Walter Crypsse, Gilbert du char, Thomas Alayn, William Wrouch, Thomas
                            Oturbourne. Given at W. <date><supplied>20 Jan. 1341.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="142"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 20</bibl> Walter le crupse of W. quit-claims
                            to John atte Rysshe of W. and Alice his wife, his right in one acre of
                            arable land in C. in the culture called Fyfacres between John
                            fitz-Richard de Louches’ land on the west, and that of William Badecoke
                            on the east, reaching on the north above the prior’s land. Witnesses:
                            William de Lattone, William Barefot, Roger atte Mulle, Robert of
                            Mackeneye, Gilbert atte char, Thomas de Oterboume, Robert of Toppefeld,
                            clerk. Given at C. <date><supplied>19 Feb. 1341.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 21</bibl> Walter Stephenes son of William
                            Stephen grants to Henry le Veysin de Warborghe [the 4 acres described in
                            M. 20]. Witnesses: as in M. 20, as the first, Richard de Louches.
                                    <date><supplied>30 Sept. 1341.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 22</bibl> Gilbert de char de C. grants to
                            John atte Rysshe of W. one acre of arable land in C. in Middelforlong,
                            between the land of Sir Edmund de Bereford on the south, and that of
                            Richard Moryn on the north. Witnesses [Robert of] Toppefeld, clerk. [The
                            others are illegible.] <date>… Ed. III.</date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 23</bibl> John Maryot of W. quit-claims to
                            John atte [Ru]ssche of the same his right in one acre of arable land in
                            C., in Medforlong. Witnesses: Robert Butty, John de Louches, Walter
                            Cirpsse, William du char, Thomas [<gap/>], William Wrouch, Thomas
                            Oturbourne. Given at C. [<hi rend="italic">Torn.</hi>] <date>1 March
                                    <supplied>1342.</supplied></date> Small circular seal in
                            reddish-brown wax: a man’s head, bearded. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 88</bibl> William Skyp of W.
                            quit-claims to Walter Cryps his right in ½ an acre of arable land in C.
                            in the shot called Cornwayles inlondes. Witnesses: John Maryot, Robert
                            Boti, John atte Russche, Richard Moryn, John of Blebury, Thomas Alayn,
                            William Wrote, Gilbert du char, Richard of Bryhtwalton, clerk. Given at
                            C. <date><supplied>5 May 1342.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 24</bibl> Walter Cirpsse of W. grants to John
                            ate Russche of the same ½ acre of arable land in C., in Algareforlang,
                            between Edmund de Bereford’s land on the east and that of Alice Kenelm
                            on the west, reaching from south to north over William de Cornwaille’s
                            land called Inlond. Witnesses: John Maryot, Robert Butty, Thomas Alayn,
                            William Wrouch, Thomas Oturbourne. Given at C. <date><supplied>14 Jan.
                                    1344.</supplied></date> Seal. </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="143"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 25</bibl> Robert de Croxford and Geoffrey
                            Cheyndut, chaplains, grant to John atte Rysshe of W. and Alice his wife
                            4 acres of arable land called la Goore, in C., of which one acre is
                            forera, between the prior’s land on the east and the land wh. J. and A.
                            his wife have of the gift of R. de C. and G. C., and 3 acres lie
                            together from the said forera to the cross on the way from W. to
                            Abingdon. Witnesses: John Mariot, John of Brictwalton, John Garstone,
                            Reginald le taverner, Thomas of Oterboume, Walter Crys, William Wyte.
                            Given at C. <date><supplied>15 Oct. 1344.</supplied></date> Two Seals:
                            (1) as in M. 24. (2) the Virgin and child, standing, a standing figure
                            on either side, blunted oval. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 26</bibl> William son of William Whicthele of
                            W., and heir of Joan wife of the said William Whicthele, quit-claims to
                            John atte Rysshe his right in one acre of arable land in C. in
                            Medforlong, between William de Cornewaille’s land and that late of
                            Reginald de Badecoke, which acre Hawise late the wife of Eustace Paring
                            held in dower. Witnesses: John Mariot, John Garstone, Reginald Taverner,
                            Thomas Alayn, Walter Cripse, William Wrote, Thomas of Oterbourne. Given
                            at W. <date><supplied>17 Jan. 1349.</supplied></date> Circular seal, ⅔”;
                            a stag. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 92</bibl> Indenture by which
                            Stephen Cryps, chaplain, grants to John Broun, porter, Alice his wife,
                            and John son of Henry of Stapleford, a tenement in All Saints’, and two
                            acres of land in C., in Medforlond, for their lives, reserving to
                            himself a plot containing a well, from which his father Walter Cryps
                            used to procure free stone. Rent 6/-. They have granted to the said
                            Stephen a solar with free entry and exit at reasonable hours (<hi
                                rend="italic">temporibus opportunis</hi>). Witnesses: John de
                            Anesty, John atte Ruysche, Philip Gylot, John Horspathe, Richard Folyot,
                            John Louches, Robert, clerk. Given at W. <date><supplied>29 June
                                    1349.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 93</bibl> Richard Oterbourne of C.
                            grants to John atte Rysshe of W. 3 acres of arable land in C. … viz. one
                            acre at le Pathe leading to le Westweye, one at le North Mulle, and one
                            at Schillyng-wurthe. Also one acre of meadow in C. ’prout sors
                            condonat’. Witnesses: Reginald le taverner, Richard Folyot, John Kary,
                            John de Louches, Richard atte char. Given at C. <date><supplied>25 Oct.
                                    1349.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="144"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 142</bibl> John Horsepathe of W.
                            grants to Richard Folyot and Alice his wife one acre and one rood of
                            meadow in the gore of the northmede of C. Witnesses: Nicholas Payable,
                            mayor, John Ruysshe, Robert Taverner, William atte Garstone, John Broun,
                            porter. Given at C. <date><supplied>8 March 1352.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 27</bibl> Alice Horsepathe late the wife of
                            John Horsepathe of W. grants to Alexander de Chelseye, rector of the
                            church of Chynnore, Robert Wolveleghe, vicar of the church of
                            Westhenrerthe, and John de Estbury, junior, 3½ acres of arable land
                            lying together in C. at the north end of Inlondes de la Ruschecourt.
                            Witnesses: Robert Holte, John James, William Harewelle, Henry Redynges,
                            Robert Boty. Given at C. <date><supplied>25 Sept.
                                1358.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 28</bibl> Alice Folyot of W. grants to
                            Alexander of Sholseye rector of the church of Chynnore, Robert Wolvele,
                            vicar of the church of Westhenrerthe, and John son of John of Estbury, 5
                            acres of arable land late of Roger Badecok, in C. Witnesses: Robert
                            Holte, mayor of W., John James, John Ergtwoltone, William Harewelle,
                            William Arnegate, Thomas Hakeberne. Given at C. <date><supplied>25 Jan.
                                    1362.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 102</bibl> Richard of Lichfeld,
                            chaplain, grants to Alexander of Cholseye, rector of Chinnore, Thomas of
                            Kyngesburi, vicar of Harwelle, Robert Wolueleghe, vicar of Westchurche,
                            and John of Estburi, junior, 5½ acres of arable land in C. viz.: 2½
                            acres at le Buttes on the west of the highroad leading to le Barge, one
                            acre at the quarry, one acre at le Shitehap, one acre at the head of
                            Thistleforlong, abutting on the field of Sottewelle. Witnesses: William
                            Harwelle, Robert Butty, Henry Rodynge, and Roger Preston of W., Nicholas
                            Kenelm, and John Yonge of C. Given at C. <date><supplied>23 Oct.
                                    1363.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 29</bibl> Alice Horsepathe, late the wife of
                            John Horsepathe of W. grants power of attorney to John Arblaster, clerk,
                            to deliver seisin to [grantees of M. 70] of ½ acre in land of la
                            Russchecourt. <date><supplied>26 May 1366.</supplied></date> Small
                            circular seal, attached by torn tag: a ship. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 112</bibl> John Swayn grants to
                            Alexander of Cholseye, rector of Chinnore, Robert Wolveleghe, vicar of
                            West Henreth, and Walter Shatmot, <pb n="145"/> one acre of arable land
                            in C. in Bataylforlong. Witnesses: John James, William Harewelle, Henry
                            Deme (sic), Henry Redynge, Nicholas Kenelm. Given at C.
                                    <date><supplied>8 Feb. 1370.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 125</bibl> Alexander, rector of
                            Chynnore, grants to William de Dynham prior &amp;c. of W., a messuage,
                            83 acres of land, 5 acres 1½ roods of meadow in C. Witnesses: Richard
                            atte Felde, mayor, John Lorkyn, Roger Arniat, Roger Mylborne, William
                            Amiat, William Shelyngford, William Wodeward, Thomas Desforde of C.,
                            Adam Fauconer of C. Given at C. <date><supplied>10 May
                                1383.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 30</bibl> Alice Hapselon grants to Cristina
                            James de W., William Motte, and Elena his wife, one acre of arable land
                            in C., between the prior’s land on each side. Witnesses: Laurence
                            Hawman, Robert Hapselon, Richard Brouns. <date><supplied>3 Nov.
                                    1406.</supplied></date></p>
                        <p>Seal. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 31</bibl> William Motte of W., grants to
                            Thomas Rothewelle, Richard Kene, and William Cayme, one acre of arable
                            land in C., in the Overthystellefurlong, the fourth acre from the road
                            called West-bargewaye. Witnesses: John Warfelde, mayor, Lawrence
                            Hawemane, John Bensshef, Richard Colles, William Bodyngtone. Given at C.
                                    <date><supplied>23 March 1431.</supplied></date> Small circular
                            seal with monogram of William Motte. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 143</bibl> Indenture by which sir
                            Edmund Rede, kt., demises to Wm. Herdewik, prior &amp;c. of W., his
                            manors of Ruyschcourt and Clopcote lately held by Thomas Slade and
                            Robert Broun, with 2/- rent from an orchard and garden in W. by
                            Wodestrete on the west and Lekestrete on the east, for 99 years. Rent 40
                            marks. Given in the chapter-house. <date>7 Dec. 1465.</date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Goring</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 51</bibl> Indenture by which
                            Gregory, prior &amp;c. of W. grant to the lady Sarah, prioress &amp;c.
                            of Goring, one virgate of land in Goring, called Cunestables lond. Rent:
                            5/-. Witnesses: Peter, bishop of Exeter, Sir Hugh Bunival, kt., John
                            Luches, mayor of W., Gilbert Pynscoun, William de la Wyk, John son of
                            Hubert. Given at W. <date><supplied>3 Feb.</supplied> 1285.</date>
                        </p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mapledurham.</hi></p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="146"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 52</bibl> Indenture by which
                            Gregory, prior &amp;c. of W., quit-claim to Sir John de Chausy, kt., son
                            of Geoffrey de Chausy of Mapledurham, their right in one acre of meadow
                            called Hawlvesacre and a rent of 10 estiches of eels or 2/- in M., which
                            had been in dispute, in return for 5/- annually. Witnesses: Sirs John de
                            Dykeby, steward of the honour of W., Edmund de Wedone constable of W.,
                            Alan fitz-Rowald, Elias de Whytefelde, kts., Gilbert Pynsun of Molesham,
                            John Fachel, Thomas Hykun. <date><supplied>26 April
                                1289.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Nethercote [Oxon.].</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 4</bibl> Miles de Nothercot grants
                            to W. in free alms ½ a virgate of land in Nothercot, which Stephen the
                            son of Richard the miller of Salingford held. Witnesses: Adam parson of
                            Chenhora, Henry de scaccario, Matthew Brond, Hugh of Pochel’, John of
                            Cennore, William of Wudesmundeston, William son of Andrew, Gilbert son
                            of Gerard, Robert Lerun, William Germund. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1180.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Quainton Mallet</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Bucks.</hi>).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 9</bibl> Hirvoy Malet of Quentune,
                            son of Ruelend, grants to W. the ½ virgate which Hugh Malet his cousin
                            and tenent gave to the sacristran. Witnesses: Thomas de Munceas,
                            Geoffrey de la Mare, William de Arches, Reginald Leangeun, Richard
                            Morin, Thomas of Witeham, Robert son of William, Ralph de Port, Robert
                            de Basingges, Ralph Sailard. <date><supplied>c.
                                1200–1210.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 10</bibl> Hugh Malet of Quentune
                            grants to the sacristran of W. in free alms [the same] half virgate.
                            Witnesses: … Hyrvoy Malet, William de Arches, Reginald Langeun, Ri . . .
                            . . . Robert son of William, Ralph de Port, Robert de Basingges, Ralph
                            Sailard. [<hi rend="italic">Mutilated.</hi>] <date><supplied>c.
                                    1200–1210.</supplied></date> The witnesses are almost certainly
                            as in Berks. ch. 9, which is written in the same hand. </p>

                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Sotewell Stonor.</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 117a</bibl> Thomas Smyth of
                            Ippesdene [Ipsden] and Alice his wife grant to sir John Kentewode, kt.,
                            Alexander of Cholseye parson of Chynnore, Walter Whatmot, 7 acres of
                            arable land in Sottewelle, <pb n="147"/> late of Henry Sottewelle.
                            Witnesses: Walter Yonge, John Mayn, Henry Deme, Robert Boty, John
                            Arblaster. Given at S. <date>4 Sept. <supplied>1375.</supplied></date>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Wallingford and Clapcote.</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 8</bibl> Master Christian of W.,
                            grants to W. in free alms certain lands: (i) … which Robert son of P . .
                            hel’ holds, for 6/6; (ii) … mill for 4/-; (iii) the other land which
                            Renur the clerk gave to him; (iv) also Walter and Osbert for 2/4; (v)
                            after his death, all his books of the Divine Scriptures. For this they
                            have granted him a daily provision of food and drink for himself [as
                            long as ?] he shall remain a secular, and for his servant according to
                            the provision made for a servant of the priory. Witnesses: Andrew son of
                            Peter, … Ferr’, William Gurmund. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1190–1200.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 32</bibl> Geoffrey fitz-Edmund grants to
                            Gilbert the marshal a tenement ’in vallo castelli’ of Wallingford, which
                            David his father held before him. Rent: 2/-, but if the rent due from
                            the burgesses of W. to the King, and fixed by King John, shall be
                            pardoned, the rent shall be 6<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses: John
                            de Wechenholthe, sheriff of Berkshire, Thomas de Munceaus, Richard
                            Morin, Richard de parco, Richard of Brichtewelle, Walter Cotele, James
                            son of Jukell, William sapiens, Robert son of William, Thomas of
                            Witheham, Richard Ferrant. <date><supplied>1204–15.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 16</bibl> William Gurmund of W.
                            grants to the sacristan of W. in free alms, to provide 3 lamps and 6
                            candles (each of three pounds) annually, and at least two candles and
                            three lamps at every service, in honour of the blessed Virgin, 13/2 in
                            quit-rents in W. and C. Wm. abbot of S. Alban’s, and Th. prior of W.
                            seal the charter with Wm. Gurmund. Witnesses: Master Stephen of
                            Hettefeld parson of Wenggrave [Wingrave], Walter, parson of … horn,
                            William parson of Kingesburi, Roger of Cornwall, rector of Brithewelle,
                            Henry, chaplain of Holy Trinity, Wallingford, William … Robegild, Hubert
                            of Hatfeld, Nicholas des Estaus, Alexander Dublet, Peter the vintner,
                            John son of Robegild, Nicholas de Basinges, Ralph of Wy …, Roger of
                            Hatfeld, Andrew the baker. <date><supplied>1214–35.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 21</bibl> Stephen de Stallis
                            quit-claims to W., and sir William of Huntingdone, prior, in free alms,
                                6<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> rent from pasture held by <pb n="148"/>
                            Robert de Luches in Portmonfeld in W. Witnesses: Alexander Dublet,
                            Robert de Luches, Nicholas and Alexander de Stallis, …, Peter the
                            vintner, William vicar of Holy Trinity Wallingford, William the esquire.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1240–1254.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 27</bibl> Robert Louches grants to
                            W. in free alms a certain pasture of 5 acres in Portfelde. Witnesses:
                            Eustace the goldsmith, mayor, Nicholas son of Simon, Hubert Hatfeld,
                            Nicholas the clerk, Nicholas the chaplain of S. Mary, Simon Hous.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1260–70.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 30</bibl> John son of Hugh of
                            Brehull, with the assent of Nicholaa his wife, grants to Alan of W.,
                            physician, his fish-pond (32 feet in length) at the East Gate. Rent:
                                2<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> For this Alan has given him one mark.
                            Witnesses: Alexander Dublet, mayor, master Peter of Benham, Nicholas the
                            goldsmith, John Robechild, Ranulf the goldsmith, Stephen de Stallis,
                            Jordan the goldsmith, [<gap/>], William the clerk. <date><supplied>c.
                                    1250–1265.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 39</bibl> Geoffrey son of Robert de
                            aula grants to W. 5 acres of land with meadow lying between the land of
                            Kuth his brother and the land of Hubert of Hethfeld, paying 6<hi
                                rend="italic">d.</hi> to the lord of the fee. Also with his body he
                            grants to them in free alms a messuage between the house of William
                            Barat and that of Ralph Cruday. Witnesses: Ralph of Mackeneie and
                            William his brother, John of Sotwelle and John his son, Henry
                            bahstarius, Hubert of Hethfelde, Ralph [de Stallis?], Walter Bacun,
                            Robert of …, Walter of Leccon’. <date><supplied>c. 1260–c.
                                    1270.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 43</bibl> Hubert of Hethfeld grants
                            to W. in free alms rents of 5/6 from half a virgate and ½ one acre of
                            land which Henry de Furno holds, lying by Northmulle, in Weyforlong,
                            Thistelforlong, and Monekedene—a total of acres—for the upkeep of a
                            candle weighing two pounds to burn before the image of St. Mary in the
                            south part of the church of the Holy Trinity, during the celebration of
                            mass, and whenever anyone else bums a candle there. Witnesses: Sir
                            Richard de Turri, steward of the honour. Sir Henry de scaccario, Sir
                            Robert Bryand, master John of Pesemer, master John of Tyvener, William
                            son of Simon, Alexander Dublet.<note type="foot" n="1">This looks like a
                                14th century deed, but the attestation of Alexander Dublet requires
                                a date before 1265, when he died leaving a son and heir John. It may
                                be a transcript or a forgery.</note>
                            <date><supplied><gap/></supplied></date><note type="foot" n="1">This
                                looks like a 14th century deed, but the attestation of Alexander
                                Dublet requires a date before 1265, when he died leaving a son and
                                heir John. It may be a transcript or a forgery.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="149"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 56</bibl> Richard Gratard, son of
                            Roger Gratard, grants to Richard Louches of W. the plot with the
                            barbican by the West Gate of W., also a plot outside the West Gate, to
                            build on at pleasure. Witnesses: Robert of Sottewelle, Nicholas de la
                            Barre, Nicholas of Medforde, John Maryot, John atte Forteye, junior,
                            Swayn of Morteleye, Robert Boneface. Given at W. <date><supplied>28
                                    March 1314.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 121</bibl> John Mannyng, clerk,
                            grants to Henry Deme of W. and Elene his wife all the lands and rents
                            &amp;c. which he and John Hogecote had in W. and C. Witnesses: Richard
                            ate Felde, mayor, John James, Nicholas Tannare, Roger Mulbone, Roger
                            Arniat. Given at W. <date>4th … <supplied>1378–9.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 131</bibl> Robert Haward of W., and
                            Magote his wife, grant to master Geoffrey Prentys, John Kyng, chaplain,
                            Richard Wysebeche, and John Herdyngtone, clerk, a messuage and garden in
                            All Saints’, between Hunstrete on the north and a croft called le
                            Komynger late of Robert James on the south, one end abutting on the high
                            way opposite the castle towards the east, the other abutting on the said
                            croft towards the west, which the grantors had of the gift of William
                            Noke, rector of S. Peter’s, W., and Ralph Horsyngtone, clerk. Witnesses:
                            John Derby, mayor, John Coterelle, William Amyat, Richard Horlok,
                            aldermen, Robert Defhunt, Robert Perot, bailiffs, John Chalonere. Given
                            at W. <date>19 July. <supplied>1411.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>All Saints, Wallingford.</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 136</bibl> John Kyng, chaplain, and
                            John Hudyngton grant a messuage and garden [as in no. 131] to John
                            Tylton, John Waleys, and John Lycchefeld, chaplains, John Mason, and
                            Thomas Perucote. Witnesses: John Warfelde, mayor, William Borde,
                            Laurence Haweman, William Motte, Richard Colles, Richard Dalgate,
                            William Bodyngtone. Given at W. <date><supplied>13 Jan.
                                1431.</supplied></date><note type="foot" n="1">It is actually dated
                                Friday, the feast of S. Hilary, 9 Hen. VI, but in that year the
                                feast of S. Hilary fell upon a Saturday.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 137</bibl> The grantees of no. 136
                            grant to John Warfeld, senior, (i) the same messuage, (ii) Also a croft
                            called le Conynger’ [i.e. the Warren] between the le Castelstrete on the
                            East, and Bothecrofte on the West, one end abutting on Hundstrete and
                            Henry Deme’s <pb n="150"/> garden towards the north, the other abutting
                            on the garden late of Richard Tonworth, chaplain, on the south, which
                            they lately had of the gift of John Kyng, chaplain. Witnesses: William
                            Marmyon esq., John Warfeld, mayor, William Bodyngtone, Richard Dalgate,
                            aldermen, John Hertt, Thomas Thornelle, bailiffs. <date>13 Feb.
                                    <supplied>1437.</supplied></date>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Holy Trinity, Wallingford.</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 26</bibl> John Huberd of W. grants
                            to W. in free alms a messuage in Symeones Lane, in the parish of Holy
                            Trinity, between the messuage of Geoffrey the carpenter, and that late
                            of Hugh the miller, for which the monks used to pay him 4<hi
                                rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses: Richard of Brytweltune, mayor,
                            Eustace [C]lement, Nicholas the goldsmith, William Blonne, Richard de la
                            Wyke, William de la Wyke, Peter Le Ster, William le Ster, John de
                            Basinge. <date><supplied>c. 1270–c. 1280.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 29</bibl> John Ferarius of W.
                            grants to Henry of Yaunewith, for 14/- already paid, a messuage in the
                            parish of Holy Trinity, W., between Hubert Hatfeld’s messuage on the
                            north … Rent: 10<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> to the lord of the fee (i.e.
                            to the chamberlain of Holy Trinity) and 1<hi rend="italic">d. to</hi>
                            John and his heirs. Witnesses: Alexander Dublet, mayor, Nicholas de
                            Stallis, Richard of Bristewaltone, Robert de Louches, master Peter of
                            Benham, Alexander de Stallis, Alan the doctor, John the clerk. [<hi
                                rend="italic">Mutilated.</hi>] <date><supplied>c.
                                    1255–1265.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 31</bibl> [<gap/>] widow of Walter
                            Vergeley quit-claims to John Vyne her right in a messuage in the parish
                            of Holy Trinity, in Kanecroft, and M. rent from a plot by this tenement.
                            Witnesses: Alexander de Stallis, mayor, … Peter le Palefreur and
                            Nicholas Herui, bailiffs. [<hi rend="italic">Mutilated.</hi>]
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1260–c. 1270.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 53</bibl> William le Coveror of W.
                            grants to Richard de Louches of W., a messuage and curtilage in the
                            parish of Holy Trinity, between the messuage late of Simon of Sartrya
                            and that late of Ralph of Ruycote. Witnesses: John Maryot, mayor, Simon
                            of Heyworth, John le Gredere, Thomas of Berewyk, Robert Boneface. Given
                            at W. <date><supplied>26 Feb. 1310.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 33</bibl> Indenture by which Richard son and
                            heir of John de Louches of Wallingford grants to John le Gr[e]dere of W.
                            one acre of land in <pb n="151"/> Clopcote called Bataylacre, between
                            Osbert of Notele’s land and that of Robert de Meleburne, extending from
                            the north to the south in la Westwey, for a certain piece of land with
                            buildings in W., in the parish of Holy Trinity, by Corteyslane.
                            Witnesses: Robert of Meleburne, Richard de curru, Osbert of Notele,
                            Henry Ywon, William de Meleburne, Alan of Clopcote, Gilbert of
                            Maundeville, Richard West, William le Feron, clerk. <date><supplied>28
                                    March 1307.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 58</bibl> Joan Corteys of W., widow
                            grants to Thomas of Berewyk and Isabella his wife, a plot of land
                            between her cottages in Corteyslane on the east side; 35 feet in width
                            to the curtilege of Eustace the goldsmith towards the east and reaching
                            Corteyslane on the north, 55 feet long; in the parish of Holy Trinity.
                            Witnesses: John Maryot, mayor, Richard de Touches, Simon of Heyworth,
                            and Roger Badecok, aldermen, Thomas Bone, Eustace the goldsmith, John de
                            Louches, Robert Boneface. Given at W. <date><supplied>24 June
                                    1318.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 34</bibl> William Curteys of Wallingeforde
                            quit-claims to Thomas de Berewyke and Isabella his wife his right in a
                            piece of land reaching in length from the piece which they had of the
                            gift of Joan Curteys his mother in Curteyselane, to the curtilage of the
                            said Joan on the west—7½ feet; and in width from the curtilage of the
                            said Joan on the south to the tenement of Thomas de Horspathe on the
                            north—20 feet, in the parish of Holy Trinity, Wallingford. Witnesses:
                            John Mariot, mayor of W., Richard de Touches, Simon of He}nvorth, and
                            Roger Badecok, aldermen, Thomas Bone, John de Touches, and Robert
                            Boneface. Given at W. <date><supplied>23 July 1318.</supplied></date>
                            Seal, ⅔” long, in green wax, in the shape of a shield:’ 1 (or <hi
                                rend="smallcap">T)ELS</hi>’: a bird (long-billed) sitting on a nest.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 65</bibl> A charter to the same
                            effect as 66, and in the same hand; the only additional information is
                            that Th. of B.’s tenement was on the West and Richard de Touches’
                            curtilage on the East. Witnesses: the same. <date><supplied>21 Oct.
                                    1320.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 66</bibl> Joan Corteys, widow,
                            daughter and heiress of William Corteys of W., quit-claims to Thomas of
                            Berewyk of W., her right in a tenement in the parish of Holy Trinity,
                            W., between the garden of Richard de Louches and the tenements of
                            Eustace the <pb n="152"/> goldsmith and the said Thomas, in Corteyslane.
                            Witnesses: Nicholas de la Barre, mayor, Swayn of Mortele, Richard de
                            Louches, Thomas Bone, John de Louches, Thomas le Noble, Robert Boneface,
                            clerk. Given at W. <date><supplied>22 Oct. 1320.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 80</bibl> John son of Thomas of
                            Berewyk of W., junior, grants to John of Berewyk, his elder brother, two
                            granges, a well, and a curtilage in the parish of Holy Trinity, between
                            the principal tenement late of Thomas of B., on the east, in S. Mary the
                            Greater, and the garden of Richard le Louches on the west, reaching
                            Curteyslane [on the north], and the tenement late of Robert de Ossyndene
                            and the tenement of Alice, widow of … [on the south]. Witnesses: Richard
                            Moryn, mayor, John Whytyng, Thomas Heruy, John le Gredere, Peter
                            Restwolde, Robert of Toppesfelde, clerk. Given at W. <date><supplied>21
                                    July 1335.</supplied></date>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>St. Leonard’s, Wallingford.</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 20 b</bibl> Stephen de Stallis
                            grants to the Hospital of St. John, W., in free alms, a corner messuage
                            in the parish of St. Leonard’s, by the messuage formerly of Henry of
                            Medford, opposite the messuage of Bartholomew Fryburne within the South
                            Gate of W. Rent: 12<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> to the fee farm of W., and
                            a clove gilly flower to the grantor. Witnesses: Alexander de Stallis,
                            mayor, Richard of Britwalton, master Peter of Benham, William Blawe,
                            Eustace Clem[ent], John Hynner, Richard Mariot, bailiffs.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1230–c. 1240.</supplied></date> The whole is
                            excellently preserved. In the fold of the parchment at the bottom is, in
                            Wood’s hand: ’Given to me by Dr. Tob: Garbrand a° 1664. Ant: Woode.’ See
                                <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> ed. Clark, ii. 19. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 40</bibl> Richard le
                                [Wyth]ebolter<note type="foot" n="1">So in Coxe and Turner’s
                                catalogue: the deed is now torn.</note> with the assent of Lynina
                            his wife, grants to Robert of Cuxham and Norgana his wife, for 4 marks
                            of silver, a messuage and curtilage between the messuage of Simon Molle
                            and that of Peter Henthelon’ in St. Leonard’s, W. Rent: ½<hi
                                rend="italic">d.</hi> to the Hospital of St. John, 1<hi
                                rend="italic">d.</hi> to Eustace Clement and his heirs, 2/- to the
                            priory of W. Witnesses: Nicholas the goldsmith, mayor, Richard of
                            Brytwaltone, Eustace son of Clement, William de Wyck, William Alan, John
                            de Basinges, Walter Scympeyn, reeves, John Hyne, John de Luchiis, then
                            clerk, ’et aliis cum toto burgemot’. <date><supplied>c. 1270–c.
                                    1280.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>


                <div type="parish">
                    <head>St. Martin’s, Wallingford</head>
                    <pb n="153"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 83</bibl> Indenture by which the
                            prior &amp;c. of W. lease to Richard le Irmonger and Juliana his wife,
                            for 7 years, a tenement with the houses thereon near the cemetery of St.
                            Martin’s. Rent 4<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italic">d.</hi>
                            Witnesses: Richard Moryn, mayor, John Mariot, John of Blebury, John le
                            gredare, Richard Gratard, William of Meleburn. Given at W.
                                    <date><supplied>21 Dec. 1336.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 118</bibl> Roger Cole of W., grants
                            to Henry Redynge and Richard Coket of Abingdon a tenement with curtilage
                            adjacent in S. Martin’s, between the messuage of Thomas Horspathe on the
                            south, in which Nicholas Kyng lives, and the garden of Roger Milburne on
                            the north. Witnesses: Thomas Benshef, mayor, Richard ate Felde, Nicholas
                            Tannere, Roger Arniat, Robert Botty. Given at W. <date><supplied>9 Aug.
                                    1377.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>St. Mary the Greater, Wallingford</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 50</bibl> Matilda, widow of Richard
                            of Morton quit-claims to John de Luchiis and Eve his wife, for ½ a mark,
                            her right in 10<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> rent from part of a tenement
                            which Henry of Duolesdene held in the parish of St. Mary the Greater,
                            between the tenement late of William Lorimer and that late of Richard
                            Gratard. Witnesses: Thomas Hykon, Henry of Appelford, Ralph of Boneye,
                            aldermen, William de la Wyk, Nicholas Clement’, John Hyne, John le
                            Berner, William the lorimer, John of Meleburne, John Bone, Gregory of
                            Watham, Thomas Champeneys, Thomas Costard, Gilbert of Mandevile, and
                            Henry Folyot, bailiffs. <date><supplied>6 Dec. 1287.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 85</bibl> William Badecok of W.
                            grants to John Cary of W. and Joan his wife a tenement, which he had of
                            the gift of Thomas son and heir of Thomas of Berewyk, in S. Mary the
                            Greater, between the messuage of Agnes widow of John atte Dene on the
                            south, and that of Robert Boty on the north, reaching the highway on the
                            west above the messuage of the said R. B. Witnesses: John Maryot,
                            Richard Moryn, John Whytyng, Robert Boty, John atte Rysshe, William
                            Foerthyng, Robert of Toppesfeld, clerk. Given at W. <date><supplied>18
                                    Jan. 1341.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 115</bibl> John Teytfott of Tondon
                            grants to Alice Foliot of W. two messuages in S. Mary the Greater,
                            Wallingford, a curtilage in Canecroft, <pb n="154"/> and 2½ acres of
                            land in Croozmersche Giffard (Oxon.). Witnesses: Richard ate Felde,
                            mayor, John James, William Harewelle, William Spoute (?), Alexander Job.
                            Given at W. <date><supplied>17 June 1371.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 116</bibl> Alice Foliot of W.
                            grants to Reginald Wylder, chaplain, and Richard Redeford, a tenement in
                            W., between John Poulyn’s tenement on the south, and Denis Lane on the
                            north. Witnesses: Thomas Benecheff, mayor, Nicholas Tannere, Roger
                            Melborne, Dorkyn (?), aldermen, Richard ate Felde, Thomas Grove, Roger
                            Druyet, Roger Cole, Henry Redynge, Thomas Reginald, clerk. Given at W.
                                    <date><supplied>18 Aug. 1375.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 119</bibl> Alice Foliot of W.
                            grants to Sir John Kentwode, kt., John Arblaster and Henry Maundevile a
                            tenement in W., between that of John Poulyn on the south and
                            Denyseslane, on the north, reaching from the high road to Wodestret,
                            which she had of the gift of Reginald Bulde Ro rector of St. Mary’s, W.,
                            and Richard Bedford, chaplain, for life, with reversion to heir, heirs
                            and assigns, after the death of William Lytfot and Joan his wife.
                            Witnesses: John Bencheff, mayor, Richard ate Felde, Nicholas Tannere,
                            Henry Radynge, aldermen, Roger Milborne, Roger Druyat, Roger Cole,
                            William Cary, Thomas Grove, John Lerkyn, Thomas Reynald. Given at W.
                                    <date><supplied>Thurs. before S. Laurence, Ric.
                                II.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 130</bibl> Richard Horlok of W.
                            grants to Robert Haward and Magote his wife tenement in the parish of
                            St. Mary the Greater, with half a grange and a garden adjacent, between
                            Thomas Chapman’s tenement on the south, and Folyatlane on the north,
                            reaching from the high road on the west to Wodestret on the east. Rent
                            20/-. Witnesses: John Derby, mayor, John Cotterel, William Arnyat,
                            aldermen, William Essex, John Hert, John Denby, William Megre, William
                            Moite. Given at W. <date>10 March <supplied>1410.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 133</bibl> Robert Dunham and Joan
                            his wife quit-claim to John Pape junior of W. this right in a messuage
                            and garden in S. Mary the Greater, between the messuage of William Essex
                            on the east, and the garden of the Hospital of St. John the Baptist on
                            the south. Witnesses: Richard Horloke, mayor, John Coterell, William
                            Arniat, John Derby, aldermen, William Moite, John Denby, bailiffs, …
                            William Coterelle. Given at W. <date><supplied>26 May
                                1415.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="155"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 138</bibl> Robert [<gap/>] of W.,
                            chandler, quit-claims to the prior &amp;c. of W., a tenement in S. Mary
                            the Greater, between the tenement of Robert Hyndeman on either side,
                            facing the castle: the garden lies between … on the east, and
                            Goldesmithes tenement on the west. <date><supplied>15 July
                                    1447.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>St. Mary the Less, Wallingford</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Berks. 54</bibl> Alice and Joan, daughters
                            and heiresses of Bartholomew of Henlee of W., grant to Richard de
                            Louches, son and heir of John, a house in the parish of St. Mary the
                            Less, W., between the houses of the prior &amp;c. of W. on either side.
                            Witnesses: John Maryot, mayor, Ralph le Taverner, Gilbert of
                            Maundeville, and William le Feron, aldermen, Sweyn of Mortele, Simon of
                            Heyworth, Robert of Bedewynde, and Nicholas of Tomestone, reeves, ’et
                            multis aliis cum toto burgomoto’. <date><supplied>11 July
                                    1309.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>St. Peter’s, Wallingford</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 35</bibl> Robert Freman de Cestria, burgess
                            of Wallingford, grants to Henry le Bacheler of Basyng’ and Agnes his
                            wife, for 20/- the messuage which he had of the gift of Stephen de
                            Stallis, lying between the messuage of William de Stallis, chaplain, and
                            that of Ernald Boneface, in the parish of St. Peter’s, Wallingford, 22
                            feet in width: in length it stretches from the highroad to the outer
                            barbican of the castle ditch. Rent: (i) to the sacristan of Holy
                            Trinity, Wallingford, 3/1, and (ii) to the fee farm of the borough 2/-,
                            and (iii) to the heirs of Stephen de Stallis a pound of cummin.
                            Witnesses: Thomas de Chausee, mayor of W., William of Muleburne, Richard
                            of …ham, Henry of Hastings, and John le Gredere, bailiffs. Given at W.
                                    <date><supplied>20 March 1294.</supplied></date> Pointed oval
                            seal, 1¼”; an ornament: <hi rend="smallcap">S’ · ROB’ · LE ·
                                CHAPMAN.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Buckingham</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 36</bibl> Ralph son of Hugh de Stratford,
                            forester, grants to Henry son of Robert two messuages with houses
                            &amp;c., which he had of the gift of William son of Richard the miller
                            of Burtone, in the town of Buckingham, lying at la Hulle, between the
                            abbot of Butlesdene’s messuage and that late of Richard Musard. Rent:
                                8<hi rend="italic">d.,</hi> and 7<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> to
                            William son of Richard of Burton. For this grant Henry gave him 3½
                            marks. Witnesses: Sir Ralph Harang, Sir Hugh de <pb n="156"/> Castilun,
                            Sir William fitz-Reginald, kts., Berner of Horew[ode], William of Thame,
                            Henry the butcher, Hugh of Sybeforde, Laurence Perte, Roger Wygesoule,
                            Hugh le Taylur, William le Taylur. <date><supplied>c.
                                1260.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div type="org">
                <head type="heading">St. Leonard’s, Clattercote (Oxon.)<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Claydon</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bucks.</hi>).<lb/>M.
                    37–43.</head>

                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 37</bibl> Richard of Grimescote grants to St. L.,
                        in free alms, a croft near the hedge belonging to the Hospital (<hi
                            rend="italic">sepes infirmorum</hi>) <hi rend="italic">’</hi>and one
                        acre’ lying over Sugkewrche in Hafdelond above the acre held from the
                        Hospital in lancetagium (<hi rend="italic">infirmorum lancet’</hi>).
                        Witnesses: Ralph of Grimescote, Robert of Culewrthe, Simon of Cropiri,
                        William of Prestecote, William of Selvestone.
                                <date><supplied>1150–70.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 38</bibl> Richard son of Anselm of Grimescote
                        grants to St. L. in free alms land in C. which they formerly held from him
                        at farm, i.e. (i) the land once held by Walter son of John in villeinage,
                        (ii) a virgate which Ailwyn once held from the grantor in villeinage.
                        Witnesses: Sir Thomas de Arderne of Hanewelle, Sir John fitz-Guydo, Hugh of
                        Bereford, Walter le honorable, Simon of Cropp’, master Thomas of Molintone,
                        William his brother, Lawrence of Herdewic, Nicholas of Palsynton, John
                        Waudard, Henry Gadone. <date><supplied>c. 1210–c. 1220.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 39</bibl> Richard de Grimescote et de Cleydone
                        grants to the same in free alms a messuage with croft in Cleydone which John
                        le Capiere once held from him. Witnesses: Hugh de Bereford, John Cachelewe,
                        Walter le Honorable, master Thomas de Molintone. <date><supplied>c.
                                1260–70.</supplied></date> Broken seal as in M. 40. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 40</bibl> Richard de Grimescote grants to St.
                        Mary and St. Leonard’s, Clattercote, in free alms, a virgate of land and a
                        messuage in Cleydon, which Robert son of Aldewin once held from him.
                        Witnesses: Sir Robert de Wycham, Simon de Cropray, John Cachelen, Hugh de
                        Berford, Anselm de Grimescote. <date><supplied>1260–70.</supplied></date>
                        Pointed oval seal, 1¼ × ⅞”, in brown wax; a heron in flight, with something
                        in its mouth: <hi rend="smallcap">S’ · RICARDI · DE · GRIMESCOTE.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <pb n="157"/>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 41</bibl> Richard de Grimescote son of Anselm de
                        Grimescote grants to the same in free alms, (i) one virgate of arable land
                        in Cleydon, which Henry le Hunte once held from him; (ii) and a messuage
                        with a croft, lying between the prior’s land and the road to the church,
                        which William Faber once held from him; (iii) all his right in the land
                        called Presteshurne. Witnesses: Simon de Croprey, John Catheleu, Anselm de
                        Grimescote, Henry the marshal, Gilbert de Walecote. <date><supplied>c.
                                1260–70.</supplied></date> Seal as in M. 40. This charter is written
                        in the same hand as no. 32. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 42</bibl> Henry Faber of Farneberge grants to the
                        same, in free alms, Richard son of Walter Sweterich of Cleydon, with all his
                        issue and chattels, whom the grantor bought back from Richard fitz-Anselm de
                        Grimescote. Witnesses: Nicholas de Say, John Kachelewe, Alexander de
                        Wulfeye, Richard fitz-Symon de Bradewelle, Robert de Aubundele, clerks,
                        Richard de la Dene, Robert de Leueland, Stephen the baker.
                                <date><supplied>c. 1240–c. 1250.</supplied></date> Circular seal,
                            1<num type="fraction">1/4</num>″ in red wax, a fleur-de-lys, <hi
                            rend="smallcap">SIGILL’ · HENRICI · LEFEVERE.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 43</bibl> Henry called the Marshal of Farneberi
                        grants to the same, in free alms, a messuage and a virgate of land in
                        Claydon, which he had of the gift of Richard de Grimmescote, namely the
                        virgate which Richard Atteyate once held from R. de G. in villeinage.
                        Witnesses : Sirs John Passelewe, John Peche, knights, Jordan de Say, lord of
                        Farneberi, Walter le Honurable, Henry Mile of Chaddeleshunt, Anselm de
                        Grimmescote, William Gyffarde of Wirmelectone. <date><supplied>c.
                                1260–70.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Radcliffe</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Bucks.</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 44</bibl> William Foliot, senior, of Evenele
                        [Evenley, N’hants.], grants to Ralph Harang of Radeclef a messuage with a
                        garden, 20 acres of arable land, 10 acres of meadow, and 15 acres of pasture
                        which Nigel his father bought from Odo Borewater of Radeclef, in R. and
                        Schekem, lying between Ralph Harang’s messuage on the south and the manse of
                        John le Catur on the north, [boundaries specified]. Witnesses: Symon, abbot
                        of Betlesdene [Biddlesden], <pb n="158"/> William de Evenesholte, Walter
                        Bastarde, Ralph Porcel, R. his son, Robert de Bayntone, Walter Cotus, Yvo
                        Cotusforde, Roger his brother, Ralph Langeporthe.
                                <date><supplied><gap/></supplied><note type="foot" n="1">This is a
                                late fourteenth-century transcript. Simon, abbot of Biddlesden does
                                not occur in <hi rend="italic">V.C.H. Bucks,</hi> i.
                            367.</note></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div type="org">
                <head type="heading">Ravenstone Priory (Bucks.)</head>

                <p>Bucks, chs. 1–37 refer to Ravenstone. Of these the following are fully dealt with
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Calendar of Charters and Rolls in the Bodleian
                        Library,</hi> and have therefore been omitted: nos. 2 (p. 28), 9–12 (p. 29),
                    17–20 (p. 30), 22 (p. 30), 30 (p. 32), 31 (p. 31), 35–7 (p. 31.)</p>

                <note type="heading">M. 45–9.</note>

                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 1)</bibl> John de Basingham, lord of
                            Wahull,<note type="foot" n="1">John inherited the estate in 1238 and
                            died in 1239. (<hi rend="italic">V.C.H. Bucks.</hi> iv. 441.)</note>
                        grants to William the clerk for his homage and service, a messuage near the
                        cemetery, and 3 acres of land in R. Rent: 3/-. Witnesses: Hugh de Legh,
                        Ralph de Parentin, William (?) de R[ave]nestone, Simon of R., Walter
                        Caperon, Ralph his son, William son of [<gap/>]†, Walter the cook.
                                <date><supplied>c. 1238–9.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 3</bibl> Agnes, daughter of Walter the
                        cook, grants to sir William prior &amp;c. of R., in free alms 1½ acres of
                        land in R. viz. that acre lying in the upper shot nearer the ditch which is
                        between the assart of the heirs of Walter the cook and the assart of the
                        heirs of Richard Tonge. Rent:3<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> For this grant the
                        prior gave 16<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 8<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses:
                        Sir Walter de insula, kt., master John de Chishulle, Sir John de St. Maria,
                        William and Simon de R., William de Nodariis, Nicholas the clerk, Nicholas
                        of Haversham, Henry the mason, Walter of Scrintun. <date><supplied>1254–c.
                                1260.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 4</bibl> The same grant, with the
                        addition of a ditch and hedge. Rent, the same. For this grant the prior gave
                            24<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 8<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses: the
                        same. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 5</bibl> Richard Tonge of R. grants to
                        Walter the cook, for his homage and service and for 30/-, 2½ acres of land
                        with a ditch and hedge. Rent: 4<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses: . . . .
                        . . . [de Rave]nestone, William of Luttone, Walter Caperun, Ralph his son,
                        William the chamberlain, Helias of Cugeho. <date><supplied>c.
                                1260.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <pb n="159"/>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 6a</bibl> John son of Richard Tonge of
                        R. grants to R. the same ditch and hedge [lying as in 3]. Witnesses: master
                        John de Chishulle, Sir John de St. Maria, William de Nodariis, William of
                        R., William of Dudingtune, Simon of R., Walter of Scrintune, William
                        Ailward, Nicholas the clerk, Henry the mason. <date><supplied>1254–c.
                                1260.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 6b</bibl> Richard de Clifford, rector
                        of R., grants to William of R. and Christiana his wife the messuage which
                        Edmund formerly held of the fee of the church of R. Witnesses: Sir William
                        of Divises, then prior of R., Sir Michael chaplain of R., Nicholas the clerk
                        of R., John Tonge, Walter of Schyrintone, William Caperun, John the clerk,
                        Richard Facceneie. <date><supplied>c. 1260.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 8</bibl> Elizabeth, daughter of William
                        of R., grants to R. 7 acres of land in R. which were formerly of Walter
                        [<gap/>], near the great park, in the shot called Walt’ stocking Thone.
                        Witnesses: Sir Roger de Chiringham, kt., Almaric de Nodariis, kt., John of …
                        wile, Robert [of Crettone], [Edward] of Devisis, William the cook.
                                <date><supplied>c. 1290–1302.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 7</bibl> Quit-claim for the same. Same
                        witnesses. In the same hand. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 9</bibl> Nicholas, son of Richard Tonge
                        of R., quit-claims to R. all that he held of them, viz. (i) a messuage and
                        croft in R., (ii) all his land in the assart called Thongestocking, (iii)
                        also 4<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> rent from 1½ ac. held by William Caperun,
                            5<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> from 1 ac. held by Matilda Thebaud, 1<hi
                            rend="italic">d.</hi> from Nicholas son of John for two strips, ¼<hi
                            rend="italic">d.</hi> from Robert the chamberlain for part of a
                        messuage. Witnesses: Sir William de Nodariis, kt., Ahnaric his son, John of
                        Morewelle, William Caperun of R., Edward of R. <date><supplied>c.
                                1290–1302.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 13</bibl> William of R. grants to
                        Beatrice his daughter, for her homage and service, that assart with hedges
                        and ditches which he bought from Hugh son of the reeve. Rent: 2<hi
                            rend="italic">s.</hi> 0½<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses: William
                        Caperun, [R]ic[hard] son of Thomas of R., Richard s · cce … William the
                        cook, Nicholas Thonge. <date><supplied>c. 1270–80.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 14</bibl> Indenture by which R … d,
                        prior &amp;c. of R. grants to Simon of R., chaplain, the assart which they
                        had from Nicholas Tonge of <pb n="160"/> R., in the meadow of R., and which
                        Hugh Ode held, for 12 years from the feast of St. Clement. Rent: 9/-.
                        Witnesses: William of R., Robert then chaplain, William Caperun, Edward of
                        R., Richard Faccen’, Richard of Weston, William the cook.
                                <date><supplied>1280–90.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 16</bibl> Edith, daughter of William
                        Aylward, quit-claims to R. ½ acre of land in ’Cline hul’. Witnesses: Sir
                        Almaric de Nodariis, and Roger de [?Chiringham], kts., John of . . rwelle of
                        Stoke Goldingtone, William Caperun of R., William the cook of R. Given at R.
                                <date><supplied>18 July 1297.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 15</bibl> Henry de castro of R. demises
                        to Hugh Ode of the same and Isabella his wife … lying at Petronwelle between
                        the land of Henry Randolf and that of William Cok, for their lives. Rent:
                            6<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses: Richard
                        le spicer, Robert . . . ., Robert le Cok. Given at R. [<hi rend="italic"
                            >Mutilated.</hi>] <date><supplied>30 Sept. 1291.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 21</bibl> Thomas of Lyford and Joan his
                        wife grant to Philip Tone of R. and Matilda his wife, all that they held in
                        R. Witnesses: John of R., Thomas de Cretone, Simon de Cretone, … Alurich of
                        R. Given at R. <date>. . 9 Ed. II.</date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 23</bibl> Alice relict of John of R.,
                        grants to Philip Tone of R. and Alice his wife 2 acres 1½roods of land in R.
                        Witnesses: sir Richard perpetual vicar of R., Henry le spicer of R.,
                        Nicholas the smith of R., John B …, Philip Alurich. Given at R.
                                <date><supplied>22 Oct. 1320.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 24</bibl> Henry of Warewik and
                        Christiana his wife grant to Walter Wydmot of R. and Beatrice his wife and
                        Joan their daughter a rood of arable land in R. between the prior’s land and
                        that of Elizabeth daughter of John of R. Witnesses: John of Liforde, William
                        of L., Henry Lespicer of R., Henry de Noers, Simon de Cretone. Given at R.
                                <date><supplied>29 July 1324.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 25</bibl> Henry of Warewyk in R. and
                        Christiana his wife grant to Ely of Weston in R. 6 acres of land in R.
                        Witnesses: William de Nodariis, John de Haregrave, Henry son of Simon of
                        Westone, John de Lyvorde, Simon de Cretone, Henry le spicer, Nicholas the
                        smith, Philip Tone, Henry of Westone. Given at R. <date><supplied>6 Aug.
                                1324.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <pb n="161"/>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 26</bibl> Henry of Mulsho [Moulsham] of
                        R. grants to sir Richard of R. chaplain, one acre one rood of arable land
                        and two roods of meadow in … one acre of land in Scyttho near the land which
                        William Gyle holds of sir William de Mokelstone, kt. Witnesses: [<gap/>] de
                        Noers, Hugh de Warewyk, William of Lyford, Robert le Kong of R., Richard
                        lespecer of R. [<hi rend="italic">Mutilated.</hi>] <date>… 4 Ed. III.</date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 27</bibl> Alice [<gap/>] grants to sir
                        Robert, prior &amp;c. of R., 3½ acres in the fields and meadows of . . . .
                        for her life with reversion to Nicholas her husband, and on his death
                        remainder to the said prior &amp;c. Witnesses: Henry Lespicer of R., Richard
                        Le specer of R., Robert …, William of Lyforde. Given at R.
                                <date><supplied>23 Sept. 1333.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 28</bibl> Joane Adecok, widow of Roger
                        Ingelberd of Northampton, grants to John le Masun of R. clerk, one acre of
                        arable land … Weston at ’Le Smale hegges,’ near the abbot of Lavenden’s
                        land. Witnesses: Henry le spicer of R., Nicholas le [<gap/>] of R., Philip
                        Alurich of R., Robert Alewey of R. Given at R. [<hi rend="italic"
                            >Mutilated.</hi>] <date><supplied>1 Nov. 1337.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 29</bibl> The same is bound to pay the
                        same 30/- in the church of R. at the feast of Epiphany following. Witnesses:
                        Henry of Warewyk, William of Leyford, Robert the cook, John le gros, Richard
                        le specer. Given at R. <date><supplied>5 Nov. 1337.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 32</bibl> Henry, son of William de
                        castro, grants to Hugh Ode of R. one [… after rood of arable land lying at
                        le ‘Peretrewelle’. Witnesses: Nicholas the smith of R., Robert Alewey, John
                        Lawrence, Philip Alurich. Given at R. <date><supplied>… after 7 Oct.
                                1341.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Bucks 34</bibl> William of Haregrave of Stoke
                        Goldington, chaplain, grants to R. all his inheritance in Stoke, Ikelee,
                        Pyddington and Weston, with a messuage and 30 acres of land which he had of
                        the gift of Nicholas the smith of R. Witnesses: Thomas de Rayms, Simon
                        Northwich, William de Nowers, Roger …, … son of John, Robert Alewey … Given
                        at Stoke Goldington. <date><supplied>14 Aug. 1350.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 45</bibl> William called the Young of Weston
                        grants William his son 3 acres of land in W., of which 1 acre lies in the
                        south field above Longecroft, at the cross called Walter’s, between William
                            <pb n="162"/> Swirthing’s land and that of Martin Blund, and 2 acres lie
                        in the north field—one in Stenewelleforlong, between William Pynant’s land
                        and that of Robert Aunfray, the other in Northlongforlong, between John
                        Sybile’s land and that of … Rent: a rose at midsummer. For this William (the
                        son) gave 2/-. Witnesses: Sir Roger Damar’, kt., Sir Ralph de Cestertone,
                        kt., Sir Richard called the Poor (Le Poer) kt., Robert the Young of W.,
                        William de Millington, Philip the clerk. [<hi rend="italic">Torn.</hi>]
                                <date><supplied>c. 1270.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 46</bibl> Henry the Mason of Ravenestone grants
                        to Thomas his son, for his service, ½ acre of land in R., lying in land
                        called Goderode, between the land late of Henry Ascelene and that of Walter
                        Aluerhic, abutting at one head on the land of John fitz-William de R., and
                        at the other on the croft late of William Aylward. Rent: 1<hi rend="italic"
                            >d.</hi> and forinsec service. Witnesses: Walter de R., John his
                        brother, William Caperun, Walter Jurdan, Edward de Divisis, Nicholas Thonge,
                        Thomas the chamberlain. <date><supplied>c. 1280–1300.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 47</bibl> Indenture by which John de R. grants to
                        Philip Tone of R. and Alice, the grantor’s daughter, in free marriage all
                        the lands and tenements in R. which he had of the gift of Philip Tone.
                        Witnesses: Nicholas the smith of R., Henry the apothecary of the same,
                        Philip Alurich, Nicholas Golone, Walter the cook. Given at R.
                                <date><supplied>25 Nov. 1329.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 48</bibl> Indenture by which John Golone of R.
                        and Alice his wife grant to Hugh Ode of the same and Isabella his wife, and
                        Henry le Fullere and Agnes his wife, an acre of land in R. between Walter
                        Tone’s land and that of Henry Eve (or Ene) at Fonleslow. Rent: a rose at
                        Midsummer, for 12 years, and after that 13/-. Witnesses: Henry de … Robert
                        Alewey, Philip Alrich, Richard le spicer, Nicholas le smyth. Given at R.
                                <date><supplied>3 Oct. 1344.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 49</bibl> Indenture by which Richard Gateman of
                        R. grants to Hugh Ode of R. and Isabella his wife 6 strips and pasture at
                        the head of each, lying in the great croft by the land of Nicholas le smyth
                        in three places of the same croft, for 13 years from Michaelmas, 20 Ed. III.
                        Half the fruits are to go to the grantors, who may resume possession if the
                        land is left uncultivated. Witnesses: Robert Alewey, Henry de castro,
                        Richard Spicer, John le Feroner (?), John Laurence. Given at R.
                                <date><supplied>29 Sept. 1346.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Shalstone</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Bucks.</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <pb n="163"/>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 50</bibl> Walter son of William the carter of
                        Saldistone grants to William the clerk, his brother, of Westburi, for his
                        service and for a house which he bought from Peter, late the son of Richard
                        Franceis of Westburi, a piece of land lying between the grantee’s land on
                        either side, and reaching to the house of Richard le Pape: thirty feet by
                        twenty feet: with half a strip over Brerforlong by le Wodewei, reaching over
                        Flexlond. Witnesses: Ralph of Senliz, Jordan Bastard, Thomas Rikeward,
                        Robert Hardel, William the palmer, John the clerk, William the clerk.
                                <date><supplied>c. 1230–40.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                   
                </div>
              <div type="parish">  <head>Great Fordham [Essex].</head> <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. Ch. Essex 193) and M. 51</bibl> Matilda, relict of
                        William Seburc of Fordham, grants to Richard de Ewell of the same, for 40/-,
                        a field with hedges and ditches, called Haukeslond, and a path, in the
                        parish of Great Fordham. Rent: 2/-. Witnesses: John Chaucie, William Pol,
                        Walter Bichedun, Ralph son of Agnes, John his son, Richard Boli, Stephen the
                        cook, John son of William, John his son. Given at Fordham.
                                <date><supplied>17 May 1349.</supplied></date> Endorsed, ’Carta de 4
                        acris terre vocatis Haukeslond … quas Robertus Hoolde modo tenet in anno 8
                        Ric. II.’ </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Totham</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Essex</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 52</bibl> Bartholomew the cook, of Totham, grants
                        to Ivo fitz-Gilbert for his homage and service, (i) that croft in T. called
                        ’Tuong’ [or Twonge’ in M. 53.] which lies between the road and Symon son of
                        Anselm’s land; (ii) one acre of land in the field called Pirifield, lying
                        along the road, shut in by a ditch. Rent: 6<hi rend="italic">d.,</hi> also
                        the service due to the King, and for scutage 1½<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> For
                        this grant Ivo gave 5/-. Witnesses: Bartholomew de la more, Roger de
                        Vneseia, Roger the palmer, Henry the clerk, Gilbert fitz-Thomas, Nigel de
                        Sireburne, John Ballard, Walter fitz-Gilbert, Richard the clerk of Totham.
                                <date><supplied>c. 1230–40.</supplied></date> Circular seal, 1¼”,
                        attached by cord of green and white silk. A hammer? <hi rend="smallcap"
                            >SIGILL · BERTELUY · LE · CV[K].</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 53</bibl> Cristina and Emma, daughters of the
                        late Bartholomew the cook of T., confirm M. 52. For this Ivo gave them 3/-.
                        Witnesses: Bartholomew de la More, Roger de Vneseia, Roger le paumer, Henry
                        the clerk, Gilbert fitz-Thomas, John de Sirebume, Robert <pb n="164"/>
                        Folenfant, Walter fitz-Gilbert, William de Chiselford, Richard de Totham,
                        clerk. <date><supplied>c. 1240–50.</supplied></date> Pointed oval seal,
                        broken, <hi rend="smallcap">’S’ · CRIST … BART’·’</hi>; an ornament. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 54</bibl> Ivo fitz-Gilbert grants to Richard de
                        Withermundeford for his homage and service, all the land which he held from
                        Bartholomew the cook in T. Rent: 6<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> to the heirs of
                        B. the c. and scutage 1½<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> For this Richard gave 8/-.
                        Witnesses: Bartholomew de la more, Philip de Bovile, Robert Folenfant,
                        William de Musters, Hugh the forester, Gilbert of Totham, John of Syreburne,
                        Walter the janitor, Amald of Colne, clerk. <date><supplied>c.
                                1250–60.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 55</bibl> Simon de Barnaville grants to the same,
                        for his homage and service and a mark of silver, a piece of land in Great
                        Totham, between the land late of Bartholomew de la more, and that of Amicia
                        de Shereburne, abutting on the road which stretches from John Ballard’s
                        house to that of B. de le M. Rent: 1<hi rend="italic">d.,</hi> scutage, ½<hi
                            rend="italic">d.</hi> Witnesses: Sewal de Mora, John de Seymtawayn,
                        Robert Folenfant, John de Shereburne, John Alard, Philip de Bovile, Robert
                        de (Gibecralse?), Roger Anketil, Peter le paumer. <date><supplied>c.
                                1260–70.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div></div>
            </div>

            <div type="org">
                <head type="heading">Abbey of Tewkesbury (Gloucs.)<lb/>M. 56–71.</head>

                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 56</bibl> William fitz-Gerald sells to Henry
                        fitz-Robert, for 10/-, John son of Gilbert the small of Nortone, his
                        villein, with all his issue and chattels. Witnesses: Gilbert fitz-Martin,
                        Elyas de Drays, Roger fitz-Richard, John de Baiocis, Richard Frankel[eyn],
                        William de Helydene, William vicar of Thorneberge, clerk. <date><supplied>c.
                                1240–50.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 57</bibl> Licence to Tewkesbury, because Gilbert
                        de Clare, earl of Gloucester and Hertford, the king’s nephew, was buried
                        there, to appropriate the churches of Thornbury and Fayreford. Portion of
                        great seal attached by cords of red and green silk. <date>20 Nov.
                                <supplied>1314.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 58</bibl> Letters patent of Walter, bp. of
                        Worcester, relating the many causes of the poverty of Theokesbury, and
                        giving licence to appropriate the church of Thornbury, having due regard to
                        the rights of the then rector, master Roger called the Marshal, and
                        assessing the church at 26 marks a year. Given at London. <date><supplied>11
                                Feb.</supplied> 1314.</date> Portion of Walter’s seal attached by
                        cord of pink silk. </p>
                </div>
                <pb n="165"/>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 58a</bibl> Another copy. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 59</bibl> Inspeximus of M. 58 by Walter, abp. of
                        Canterbury. Given at Lambeth. <date><supplied>5 May.</supplied> 1315.</date>
                        Seal attached by cord of pink silk. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 60</bibl> Walter, bishop of Worcester, assigns to
                        the vicarage of Thornbury, which is worth 18 marks 10 shillings, the house
                        once held by Zalibroun, as a vicarage house. The value to be made up to 25
                        marks in money or wax. The vicar is to pay for books, vestments, and other
                        necessary ornaments, synodal fees to the Archdeacon, and 4 marks a year to
                        the bishop, but is not to be responsible for the repair of the chancel.
                                <date><supplied>12 Aug. 1315.</supplied></date> Seals of bishop
                        Walter, the abbot of T., and the convent of T. Endorsed with references to
                        cases in chancery, A.D. 1750 and 1813. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 61</bibl> Confirmation by the prior and chapter
                        of Worcester of M. 60. <date><supplied>5 Oct. 1315.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 62</bibl> Inspeximus by the prior and chapter of
                        Christ Church, Canterbury of <date><supplied>16 Jan.</supplied> 1317.</date>
                        <list>
                            <item>(i) M. 58.</item>
                            <item>(ii) Inspeximus of M. 58 by the prior and chapter of Worcester,
                                dated 10 Kal, April 1314.)</item>
                            <item>(iii) Inspeximus of both (i) and (ii) by Walter, abp. of
                                Canterbury, dated at Lambeth 5 Non, May, 1316. (The original of this
                                is Gloucs. ch. 28).</item>
                        </list> Fragment of seal of the chapter, attached by cords of green and
                        brown silk. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 63</bibl> Inspeximus of M. 57, by Edward II.
                        Given at Newcastle-on-Tyne. By writ of P.S. <date>15 June
                                <supplied>1315.</supplied></date> The great seal, broken, attached
                        by cords of red and green silk. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 64</bibl> Confirmation of the church of
                        Thornbury, by Simon, bp. of Worcester, consequent upon a visitation. Given
                        at Hertleburi. <date><supplied>4 Feb.</supplied> 1336.</date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 65</bibl> Indenture by which Richard, abbot of
                        Tewkesbury leases to William Warde, lately of Everton (Gloucs.), Margery his
                        wife, and <pb n="166"/> William and Thomas their sons, the manor of Little
                        Compton, with certain lands called Byllandis, and a close called Taylershay,
                        from the feast of the Annunciation last past for 40 years, if any of them
                        shall live as long. Rent: £5/6/8. They are bound to the abbot in a bond of
                        £20, of the same date, to keep the agreement. Given at Tewkesbury, in the
                        chapter-house. <date>19 Sept. <supplied>1438.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 66</bibl> Letters of John, bp. of Worcester
                        permitting John, abbot of Tewkesbury, to appropriate the church of Little
                        Compton, paying ¾ to the bishop, and ¾ to the archdeacon of Gloucester,
                        yearly. Given in his castle at Hertlebury. <date>26 May 1472.</date>
                        Confirmation of this by Robert, prior, and the chapter of Worcester. Given
                        in the chapter-house. <date>29 May.</date> Confirmation by John Seggden,
                        S.T.P., archdeacon of Gloucester. Given at Bristol. <date>16 June.</date>
                        Fragments of their seals. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 67</bibl> Indenture by which John Abbot of T.,
                        leases to Richard Bolde of Little Compton, and Margery his wife, the manor
                        of Little Compton for 24 years from this date. Rent: £5/6/8.
                                <date><supplied>28 Sept. 1477.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 68</bibl> Indenture by which Richard, abbot of
                        T., leases to master Thomas With, vicar of the church of Thornbury, John
                        Pichare of the same, and Thomas and William his sons, and John Payne lately
                        of Morton in the parish of Thornbury, the site of the rectory and all tithes
                        &amp;c. for 40 years, if they live as long. Rent: £40/2/,<note type="foot"
                            n="1">This has been inserted over an erasure. The rent is elsewhere
                            mentioned as £44.</note> and 2/-. If the rent is four weeks overdue they
                        shall lose their rights. Given at T., in the chapter-house. <date>16 June
                                <supplied>1482.</supplied></date> Endorsed: as no. M. 60. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 69</bibl> Letters patent of William Grevell,
                        sergeant at law, and Walter Rowdone, reciting a licence of Henry VII dated
                        the 12 March ’anno regni sui decimo’ [nono] to themselves, and a certain …
                        [M]ordaunt, kt., and granting the advowson of the church of Wottone under
                        Egge (Gloucs.) to Tewkesbury. <date>12 July
                            <supplied>1505.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 70</bibl> Confirmation of their possessions in
                        the diocese of Worcester to T., by the bishop of Worcester. <date>20 Sept.
                            1520.</date> The (i) parish church of T., with the chapels of
                        Northampton, <pb n="167"/> Byshleye, Estchurch, Oxyndey, Tredyntone, Abbot’s
                        Wasseborne, (ii) church of St. James, Bristol, with the chapels of
                        Stapultone, Mangodesfelde, (iii) parish church of Marsfelde, (iv) parish
                        churches of Ampney Sancte Crucis, of Thombury, of Fayrford, (v) church of
                        Stanweye, with the chapels of Lemyngton, Stanley, (vi) priory of Derehurst,
                        (vii) parish church of Estlache S. Andrew’s, (viii) parish church of Wotton
                        under Egge, (ix) parish church of Preston upon Sture, (xi) parish church of
                        Little Compton, (xi) all tithes of Fayrford, (xii) 2 parts of the tithes of
                        Aldertone and Ayelesdone, (xiii) and of Lower Swale, (xiv) ½ tithes of the
                        lordship of Whyghtfeld in the parish of Derehurst, (xv) all tithes of the
                        lordship late of Frederick of Hodynton in the same, (xvi) tithes of one hide
                        in Gretton in the parish of Winchcombe, (xvii) the greater tithes late of
                        William Hersfeld in the parish of H. <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(xviii) from the church of St. [not given] Bristol,
                                    11/-</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(xix) ” ” ” ” Holy Trinity, Bristol, 10/-</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(xx) ” ” ” ” St. John ” 10/-</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(xxi) ” ” ” ” SS. Philip and James, Bristol, 13/4</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(xxii) ” ” ” ” S. Michael, Bristol, 4/-</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>S. Andrew, Bristol, 1 lb. of wax,</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(xxiii) ” ” ” ” Estleche S. Andrew, 30/-</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(xxiv) ” ” ” ” Shenyndone, 13/4</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(xxv) ” ” ” ” A. . . creston, 4/-</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(xxvi) ” ” ” ” Welleford, 20/-</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 71</bibl> Parchment roll (4 <hi rend="italic"
                            >ms.</hi>) containing: m. 1. The rector’s court at Thornbury, 5 Jan.
                        1418. 1d. <hi rend="italic">Blank</hi> 2. Court held 19 April, 1407. 2d. ” ”
                        22 June, 1411. 3 and 3d. Court held 12 May, 1419. 4. Rental of Thombury made
                        12 May, 1419, including Thornbury (total) 61/- Townhulle 48/- Schypwardende
                        4/- 4d. <hi rend="italic">Blank.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Leigh</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Kent</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 72</bibl> Roger de Frendesbery, rector of Leghe,
                        grants to John Simon of Osprenge two crofts of land which he had of the gift
                        of Henry de Shiptone late rector of Leghe; east, to the land of the prior of
                            <pb n="168"/> Tonebregge; south, to a lane leading to the highroad which
                        runs between the church and the bridge called Bittebregge, at the land of
                        William de Kamkerst; west, to the land of Roger Connegod and that of
                        Geoffrey le Tailur; north, to the highroad running from the church to a
                        place called Hildenne. Given at la Leghe. Witnesses: Thomas Chaini, John de
                        Heghlonde, John de Polle, Thomas de Mordenne, William de Dorkynghole, John
                        de Dorkynghole, Geoffrey le Tailour. <date>22 Jan.
                                <supplied>1349.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Speldhurst</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Kent</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 73</bibl> Richard Farnhame of Speldhurst grants
                        to Richard atte Twyzthe and Cristina his wife, heir of the said Richard, a
                        piece of land called Westland at Farnhamme in the parish of Speldhurst
                        (boundaries). Witnesses: John Rolfe, Thomas Tidyman, John Farnham, Laurence
                        Giffrey, Adam Giffrey, Thomas Sandr’, Thomas Lambkyn. Given at Speldhurst.
                                <date><supplied>2 Feb. 1374.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Strode and Frindsbury</hi> [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Kent</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 74</bibl> Thomas Boydyn of Strode grants to Simon
                        Boydyn of the same and John Cok of Frendesbury all his lands in the parishes
                        of Strode and Frendesbury and elsewhere in the county of Kent. Witnesses:
                        John de Scha · ele, Henry Munde, Richard Skodyntone, Roger Abbot, Roger
                        Danyel. <date>4 Sept. <supplied>1420.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Lincoln.</hi></p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 75</bibl> A seventeenth-century transcript of an
                        agreement between Boniface archbishop of Canterbury and the dean and canons
                        of Lincoln, witnessing that when the see of Lincoln falls vacant the canons
                        are to name three or four of their number and notify the abp., who will
                        choose one of them, and arranging for the maintenance of privileges and
                        distribution of income during a vacancy. At Lambeth. Witnesses: Stephen,
                        archdeacon of Canterbury, Hugh de Mortemer, Peter de Assona, official of
                        Canterbury, Peter de Lemonicis, subdean and chaplain, Pontius de Sablera,
                        canon of Valence, Hugh de Mota, Michael, dean of arches, master Henry de
                        Sandwich, archdeacon of Oxford, David of St. Frideswide archdeacon of Derby,
                        Robert de Kas … archdeacon of Worcester, and masters John de Maidenestone,
                        Roger de Cana, canons of Lincoln, Ralph de Streafflard, and Adam de Kyles. .
                        . . . <date><supplied>22 May.</supplied> 1261.</date>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">London.</hi></p>
                </div>
                <pb n="169"/>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 76</bibl> Richard, abbot &amp;c. of Nottleley
                        (Bucks.) lease to John Longlond of Northe Wynchyndon, yeoman, a tenement in
                        Friday Street, London, called ’the abbot of Nottleley is lodgyng’, in which
                        Richard Fytthette dwelt, from Michaelmas next for 61 years. Rent: 20/-.
                            <date>27 Sept. <supplied>1538.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                    <p>[<hi rend="italic">Middlesex.</hi>]</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 77</bibl> Richard Moryson esq., grants to William
                        Elistone, merchant tailor of London, for £180, his manor of Bromley Hall,
                        late of the priory of Christ Church, London, and which he had of the King’s
                        gift (29 Aug. 1544). <date>10 Sept. <supplied>1545.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Whittlebury</hi> [<hi rend="italic">N’hants.</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 78</bibl> John Portnale of Grafton, Richard Halle
                        of Wyttylbury, William Halle of the same, and Richard, dean of Towcester,
                        grant to John Colyer of Neuportpaynelle (Bucks.) and Juliana relict of
                        William Maydeford of Wyttylbury, a meadow called Blodehangyrmede in W., all
                        the lands which William Lynell of Maydeford holds from them at will, 16<hi
                            rend="italic">d.</hi> rent which they receive from Thomas Warde in
                        Adstone, 4<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> rent from John Farman in Adstone, 5/-
                        rent from Geoffrey Hay in W., and 30<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> rent from
                        Simon Carter in W., and from [blank] Cony 2/- in Sylstone in W. for the life
                        of Juliana. Witnesses: John Frayne, John Howman, Simon Carter, Robert
                        Fyssher, John Sulbury. Given at W. <date>26 Oct.
                            <supplied>1460.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Ardley</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Oxon.</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 79</bibl> William fitz-Gerard grants to Godfrey
                        de Belefosse for his homage and service two crofts in Ardlega called
                        Wdecrofte. Rent: 12<hi rend="italic">d.,</hi> scutage 3<hi rend="italic"
                            >d.</hi> Witnesses: Ralph Martel, William Martel, Simon fitz-Mercian,
                        John fitz-Ralph, Richard fitz-Gilbert, William the clerk, Arnold de Wica,
                        William Malore, Roger de Belefosse, Warin de Belefosse, Stephen de
                        Belefosse. <date><supplied>c. 1200.</supplied></date>
                        <hi rend="italic">Endorsed</hi> to the effect that William Frost of Ardleye
                        now (8 R. II.) holds the crofts. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Barton</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Oxon.</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 80</bibl> Wimera, relict of Thomas Norton,
                        quit-claims to John Spere and Alice his wife all his right in a messuage and
                        a virgate of land with adjacent meadow, in Great Barton and Midelbarton.
                        Given at Great Barton. <date><supplied>19 March 1402.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Bradwell</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Oxon.</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <pb n="170"/>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 81</bibl> John Turgray of Anescote grants to John
                        Gibbes of Westwelle a messuage with curtilage, croft, and ½ a virgate of
                        arable land in Halewelle, in the parish of Bradewelle. Witnesses: Thomas
                        Zorne, William Inge, Thomas Spicer, Henry Coteler, Reginald Cras, John
                        Westone, William Eggard. Given at Haliwelle. <date><supplied>9 April
                                1409.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 82</bibl> Thomas Dye of Bureforde in Oxfordshire
                        quit-claims to John Chapman of Alnescote (Oxon.) all his right in a messuage
                        with curtilage, croft, and ½ a virgate of arable land in Halewelle in the
                        parish of Bradewelle, which Thomas had of the gift of John Gybbes of
                        Westwelle. Witnesses: William Cotillare of Bureford, John Punter’, John
                        Moyser’, John Bounde, Thomas Chalkeleghe, William Turfray. Given at
                        Bureford. <date><supplied>21 Dec. 1443.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 83</bibl> John Chepman de Alnescote (Oxfordshire)
                        grants to John Hopere vicar of Buckelond, John Cockle of Cayndone
                        (Wiltshire), and Thomas Smyth of Alnescote a messuage with curtilage, and
                        croft, and ½ a virgate of arable land in Halewelle in the parish of
                        Bradewelle (Oxon.), which he had of the gift of Thomas Dye of Bureford.
                        Witnesses: William Cottelere of Bureforde, John Puntar’, John Mosyar’, John
                        Boonde, Thomas Chalkeleghe, William Turfrar’. Given at Bureford.
                                <date><supplied>21 Dec. 1443.</supplied></date> Rounded oval seal,
                        1”, red wax. <gap/> The Virgin (standing) and child, a figure kneeling in
                        adoration. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Enstone</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Oxon.</hi>].</p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 84</bibl> Richard Ancelme, abbot &amp;c. of
                        Winchelcombe lease to Walter Walshe of Elmeley (Wyssetur) Esq., the
                        parsonage of Enston with all lands &amp;c. as Busby Marten Arden and William
                        Rugely had it, for 70 years, after the term of Elinor Rugely who is now in
                        possession. Rents: £18/13/4; £10, as is customary, to the vicar; 13/4, 2
                        quarters of wheat and 2 quarters of barley to the dean; 6/8 to the
                        archdeacon of Oxford. Hospitality to the abbot for a day and night once a
                        year. W. W. paid for this grant £30. <date>20 Aug.
                                <supplied>1537.</supplied></date> Endorsement that this lease was
                        surrendered to Ch. Ch. 24 July 1605. Convent seal attached, with
                        counter-seal of the abbot. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 84A</bibl> Transcript of M. 84.
                                <date><supplied>Early 17 C.</supplied></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="org">
                <pb n="171"/>
                <head type="heading">Abbey of Eynsham (Oxon.) </head>


                <div type="parish">
                    <head type="heading">South Stoke.</head>

                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 85</bibl> Transcript of no. 290 in <hi
                                rend="italic">Eynsham Cartulary,</hi> vol. i. Endorsed: Mr. Palmer’s
                            deed for common of pasture in S. Woods at Stoke. <date>37 Hen.
                                III.</date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 86</bibl> Letters patent confirming to the
                            abbey of Eynsham the advowsons of Abbots’ Stoke, Newenton, Sewel, and
                            Combe (Oxon.), for 100 marks paid into the hanaper, and a new altar in
                            memory of the late queen. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Eynsham Cartulary,</hi>
                            nos. 733–7. <date>12 Dec. <supplied>1397.</supplied></date> Great seal
                            attached by cords of purple and green silk. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 87</bibl> Chancery copy of no. 791 in <hi
                                rend="italic">Eynsham Cartulary,</hi> vol. ii. <date>20 Dec.
                                    <supplied>1535.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 88</bibl> Quit-claim by Eynsham to John Rede,
                            Esq., for the lands which his father, Wm. Rede, held of them in South
                            Stoke, and about which there had been disputes; 20 a. called the
                            Bameclose, 10 a. in a close called the Bay, 6 a. in a close called the
                            Nethircourt, and 12 strips (= 6 a.) in the common field called
                            Hungrehill. Rent: 9/-. <date>1 May <supplied>1538.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 89</bibl>
                            <hi rend="italic">‘A note of certain freeholds in South Stoke’</hi>: <hi
                                rend="italic">‘Ahoue hylle’</hi>: Rychard Wylde £3/1/8, Mr. John
                            Berwyk 22/-, Mr. Rychard Wyntersalle 22/-, Sir Francys Ingerfilde 12/-
                                <hi rend="italic">‘Beneth hylle’</hi>: Anthony Paslow 9/-, Alys
                            Bowlez 10/-, Wylliam Hawelle 4/-, with memoranda. <date><supplied>16th
                                    cent.</supplied></date>
                            <table>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Account Rolls.</hi></head>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>M. 90.</cell>
                                    <cell>Stoke Abbot [i.e. South Stoke].</cell>
                                    <cell>John Hetherend, reeve,</cell>
                                    <cell>29 Ed. III.</cell>
                                    <cell>4 <hi rend="italic">ms.</hi></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>M. 91.</cell>
                                    <cell>” ”</cell>
                                    <cell>Thomas Schortte, reeve.</cell>
                                    <cell>SS. Simon &amp; Jude 30 Ed, III–Mich, 31 Ed, III.</cell>
                                    <cell>3 <hi rend="italic">ms.</hi></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>M. 92.</cell>
                                    <cell>” ”</cell>
                                    <cell>John Vyncent, reeve,</cell>
                                    <cell>47 Ed. III.</cell>
                                    <cell>3 <hi rend="italic">ms.</hi></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>M. 93.</cell>
                                    <cell>” ”</cell>
                                    <cell>John Damycele, reeve,</cell>
                                    <cell>21 Ric. II.</cell>
                                    <cell>2 <hi rend="italic">ms.</hi></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>M. 94.</cell>
                                    <cell>” ”</cell>
                                    <cell>Giles Smith, farmer,</cell>
                                    <cell>4 Hen. VI.</cell>
                                    <cell>2 <hi rend="italic">ms.</hi></cell>
                                </row>
                            </table> For the other Eynsham accounts, about 150 in number, see <hi
                                rend="italic">Eynsham Cartulary,</hi> ed. Salter, ii, p. vii et
                            seqq. </p>

                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Headington [Oxon.].</head>
                    <pb n="172"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 95</bibl> Indenture by which Robert James,
                            esq., Edward Rede, and John Feynelle, senior, grant to John Walker of
                            Oxford, baker, Michael Nortone, Gilbert Burton, and William Frankleyn, a
                            toft and a virgate of land in Hedyndone, which they had of the gift of
                            John Dulberd, clerk, Richard Bruns, and John Hore. The grantees shall
                            have seisin in return for 27½ marks, at Easter. Witnesses: John Hye,
                            Henry Hert, John Hay, John Bryan, John Chaplayn. Given at Hedyngdon.
                                    <date><supplied>20 May 1420.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 96</bibl> Henry Waffey of Hedyngdon, cousin
                            and heir of the late William Waffey, of Barton, grants to John Brobu and
                            John Wynterburn a messuage, a virgate and a quarter, called Huchons,
                            formerly called Harkedelle, in H. Thomas Sporer and William Wedowe are
                            his attorneys to deliver seisin. Witnesses: Robert Harecourt, Richard
                            Harecourt, Edmund Rede, knights, Richard Quartermayns, John Hor’, Roger
                            Penr’, Esq., William Attkyns, Richard … Given at H. <date>14 June
                                    <supplied>1468.</supplied></date>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Hensington [Oxon.].</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 97</bibl> Sybil, late the wife of Robert
                            called le Forester of Hensyntone, grants to Robert son of Thomas de
                            Wodestok le chapman and Alice his wife a messuage with curtilage and
                            garden and 4 acres of arable land in Hensyntone [boundaries]. For this
                            the grantees gave 12/-. Witnesses: Edmund le parker of Wodestok, Adam
                            Beneyth, Richard le harpur, Robert Seynt, James Man, Adam Shylfol,
                            Robert le parker, John le … Given at Wodestok. [<hi rend="italic"
                                >Mutilated.</hi>] <date><supplied>25 April 1296.</supplied></date>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Ilbury [Oxon.].</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 98</bibl> Indenture (in English) by which
                            John lord Zouche sells to John Bustard his lands in Ilbury, for £48.
                                <date>9 January <supplied>1529.</supplied></date>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Littlemore [Oxon.].</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 99</bibl> Licence to the priory of Littlemore
                            to acquire land in mortmain to the value of 8 marks a year. Given at
                            Westminster. By writ of P.S. <date>8 May
                                <supplied>1397.</supplied></date> Endorsed: ‘Memorandum quod 12 die
                            … 5 Hen. IV,’ the priory acquired lands to the value of 40/- a year. </p>

                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Oxford.</hi></head>
                    <pb n="173"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 100</bibl> Indenture by which Adam son of
                            Laurence Bernard grants to William de Lecchelade of Oxford, and Rose his
                            wife, a rent of 4/- from a tenement which Thomas de Orlyens holds in St.
                            Michael’s, south, near le Schelvyngstole, lying between the prior of St.
                            F.’s tenement on the east, and that of Peter son of John on the west,
                            for which they may distrain, and if they cannot distrain upon the said
                            tenement, they may enter Adam’s house, which is between the tenement
                            late of Geoffrey le orfevere, on the north, and Trillemille stream on
                            the south. Witnesses: Henry Oweyn, mayor, William de Wodestone and
                            Andrew Culvert, bailiffs, Philip de Ow, John de Ow, Ralph le Plomer,
                            Richard de Mertone. Given at Oxford. <date><supplied>9 Aug.
                                    1292.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 101</bibl> Christina Pille, widow, grants to
                            Robert de Brackele and Agnes his wife (the grantor’s daughter) for their
                            service, a messuage and 6 cottages with two butts and two acres of
                            arable land. The messuage lies between the prior of St. F.’s land and
                            the land late of Robert le Chapeler, in St. Peter’s-in-the-East, without
                            the East Gate. The cottages and butts are in St. Clements’ beyond the
                            Petit Pont, between the land of Walter le teler and that of Henry le
                            tannur. One acre of land lies between the preceptor of Couele’s land and
                            that of the Abbot of Oseney. The other acre, called Havedlond, lies
                            between the prior of St. F.’s land and the bank called Charewelle. Rent:
                            30/- during the grantor’s life, or else a house for her to live in,
                            worth 30/- (yearly): after her death a clove gillyflower to her heirs,
                            at Easter. Witnesses: Nicholas de Kingestone, mayor, Thomas de Sowy,
                            Richard le plumer, baillifs, Guy de Stocwelle, John the marshal, Walter
                            the dyer, Thomas Thurstayn bailiff of the hundred of Bolendene, Henry
                            Oweyn, Henry le tannur, Walter le teler. <date><supplied>1281
                                    0-1283.</supplied></date> Pointed oval seal, in green wax. A
                            crescent moon, with a star. <hi rend="smallcap">S’ CRISTIANE ·
                                PILLE.</hi><note type="foot">The terms of this grant seem to imply
                                that Christina Pille had granted all her property to Robert de
                                Brackele and to her daughter. Most of it descended to Thomas de
                                Brackele and later to the Hospital of St. John the Baptist. This
                                deed falls before no. 44 in the Cartulary of the Hospital (vol. i,
                                p. 46.).</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div type="org">
                <pb n="174"/>
                <head type="heading">Abbey of Thame (Oxon.)<lb/>
                </head>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head type="heading">Chalgrove.</head>

                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 102</bibl> Letters patent of Edward I
                            granting the advowson of Chalgrove to the abbey of Thame, for the
                            support of the 6 monks there, and that they may pray daily for the soul
                            of Piers Gaveston, Earl of Cornwall, who died in the abbey. Given at
                            Wodestok. By writ of P.S. <date>29 June
                                <supplied>1317.</supplied></date></p>
                        <p>Portion of great seal attached by cords of red and green silk. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 103</bibl> Letters patent of Walter,
                            archbishop of Canterbury, inspecting letters of <date><supplied>23
                                    April</supplied> 1320.</date>
                            <list>
                                <item>(i) John, late bishop of Lincoln, confirming to the Abbot of
                                    Thame the church of Chalgrove. Given at Bukedene. [1]May
                                    1319.</item>
                                <item>(ii) Henry, the dean, and chapter of Lincoln, inspecting (i).
                                    Given at Lincoln. [30] May 1319. Given at Lambeth.</item>
                            </list> Seal of the archbishop in green wax, attached by cords of green
                            and brown silk. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 104</bibl> Confirmation by Walter, abp. of
                            Canterbury, of a sentence pronounced by Master Richard de Hunsingore,
                            official of the archdeacon of Oxford, and dated 5 Kal. April, 1320,
                            against Ralph, rector of Fletmerston at the suit of Thame Abbey
                            concerning tithes coming from the lands of Sir John Neyrunt, kt., and
                            Robert Verney, in Fletmerston, as well as from the lands of Sir William
                            Blount, kt., in the same, all pertaining to the church of Chalgrove.
                            Walter had authorized the official to proceed against Ralph de Stretle,
                            then rector, by letters dated at Selby 2 Kal. March 1309. Given at
                            Lamebeth. <date><supplied>29 June</supplied> 1321.</date> Fragments of
                            Walter’s seal attached by cords of red and green silk. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 105</bibl> Inspeximus of an Inspeximus (dated
                            at Nottingham, 31 August 1 Ed. III, ‘sub sigillo quo tunc utebamur’) of
                            M. 102. <date>12 Feb. <supplied>1328.</supplied></date> Great seal
                            attached by cords of red and green silk. </p>

                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Westwell [Oxon.].</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 106</bibl> John Lecche of Southrope
                            quit-claims to Robert Murdac of Lomhulle all his right in all the lands
                            and tenements which <pb n="175"/> Robert atte Mulle of Southrope held in
                            Westwelle. Given at Westwelle. <date>16 April 1345.</date> Circular
                            seal, in red wax, ⅔″, a shield of arms, <hi rend="smallcap">S’
                                ROB’TI</hi> … </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 107</bibl> John de St. Philibert, knight,
                            grants to William de Edyndone, bishop of Winchester (i) the manor of
                            Westwelle in Oxfordshire, with knights’ fees and park in Etone, and (ii)
                            the manor of Thormartone in Gloucestershire, with the advowson of the
                            church of Thormartone and knights’ fees. Witnesses: John Landels, Walter
                            de Haywode, Thomas de Colshulle, Philip le Parker, John Crooke. Given at
                            Suthwerk. <date><supplied>29 May 1351.</supplied></date> Circular seal,
                            in red wax, I″, a shield of arms, <hi rend="smallcap">SIGILL’ · JOH’IS ·
                                DE · S’TO · PHIL’BERTO.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 108</bibl> Thomas de Aspale quit-claims to
                            William de Edyndon, bp. of Winchester, all his right in the manors of
                            Westwelle and Thormorton. Witnesses; John Golafre, kt., John de
                            Aluetone, William de Chiltenham, John Laundels, Robert Palet. Given at
                            Southwerke. <date><supplied>8 Feb. 1352.</supplied></date> Circular
                            seal, ¾″, in red wax: a shield of arms, 3 chevrons, <hi rend="smallcap"
                                >SIGILLVM · THOME · DE · ASPALE.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 109</bibl> Margaret, widow of John de St.
                            Philbert, kt., quit-claims to the same, her right in the same.
                            Witnesses: Sirs Edward de St. John, Bernard Brokas, John de Podenhale,
                            kts., Walter de Haywode, John atte More, Edward Baynard, John Helewys.
                            Given at Basyngg’. <date>7 April <supplied>1359.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 110</bibl> John atte Mulle of Southrope,
                            rector of the church of Broughton, grants to John … and Alice his wife,
                            of Westwelle, that tenement … and 13 acres of arable land (Boundaries)
                            in the same, which he had of the gift of Matilda Gras, sister of Robert
                            Murdak. Given at Westwelle. Witnesses: John Grosson, Thomas Stowe,
                            Thomas Bacyn, Thomas Torefray, John Bruer. <date>6 April
                                    <supplied>1369.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div type="org">
                <head type="heading">Priory of Bolton-in-Craven (Yorks.)</head>

                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 111</bibl> Sentence of William, archbishop of
                        York, confirming to the priory of Boulton-in-Craven the churches of Preston,
                        Kyldewyk, and Skipton-in-Cravene (with the chapel of Carletone). Pronounced
                        at Cawode. <date>29 May 1310.</date> Broken seal of the archbishop, in red
                        wax. </p>
                </div>
                <pb n="176"/>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 112</bibl> Master Robert of Rypplingham,
                        chancellor of the church of York, has received the church of
                        Preston-in-Craven from Boulton for 3 years from Midsummer, 1317, for a
                        certain sum of money. He has granted it for the same term to William de
                        Geyregrave, vicar of Kyldewyk, Henry de Herdeslawe, vicar of Skypton, and
                        John vicar of Carletone, for 360 marks. The monks have constituted
                        themselves principal debtors for this sum, of which he has received 100
                        marks, owed them 50 marks, has pardoned 120 marks, and is to receive 80
                        marks. Given at York. <date><supplied>3 Nov.</supplied> 1319.</date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="charter">
                    <p>
                        <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 113</bibl> William Felter, Doctor of Decrees, of
                        the church of York, testifies after examination consequent upon an
                        archiepiscopal visitation that Boulton ought to hold the churches of
                        Kildewyk, Preston, Horwode, and Skypton, with the chapel of Carletone, to
                        their own use. <date>26 Nov. 1441.</date>
                    </p>

                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Broughton.</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 114</bibl> Walter, archbishop of York, at the
                            presentation of the prior &amp;c. of Boulton-in-Craven, has instituted
                            Richard de Wautringham as vicar of Brocton. Witnesses: Master W. de
                            Bodeham, archdeacon of Nottingham, Richard of Cornwall, master Michael
                            of Wautringham, and Nicholas Martel, Richard de Bereford, Walter de
                            Chaaluns, William de Vescy, Roger de Weston and Odo de Richemunde.
                                    <date><supplied>19 Nov. 1272.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 115</bibl> License to John Thwaites, for 26
                            marks paid into the Hanaper, to grant the church of Broughton, which is
                            worth 18 marks a year, to Boulton. Given at Westminster. By writ of P.S.
                                <date>12 June <supplied>1442.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 116</bibl> The rectors of Bolton in Lowland
                            and Marton in Craven have, on the receipt of letters from John
                            archbishop of York (given at his manor of Ripon, 21 Aug. 1442),
                            ascertained by inquisition in the church of Skipton (27 Aug. 1442) that
                            the church of Broughton which John Thewayt Esq. wished to give to the
                            priory of B., is worth, in land, 40/-, and in tithes &amp;c. £13/6/4:
                            that it should pay to the archbishop 14/2, to the King for a tenth 20/6,
                            and that there are many burdens which they cannot estimate. [Items
                            composing the tithes &amp;c. are specified.] Names of the jurors:
                            Richard More, vicar of Preston in Craven, Robert Newall, vicar of Otlay,
                            Thomas Ben’, vicar of Carlton in Craven, John Kirkby, Richard <pb
                                n="177"/> Pacok, William Welle’, chaplains; William Garegrave,
                            Richard Pudsay, Henry Young, John Alcok, John Calio’, William Ben’,
                            laymen. Given at Skipton. <date><supplied>27 Aug.
                                1442.</supplied></date> Of the jurors’ seals two have been used
                            thrice each, and two twice each. The four types of seal are all round
                            and approximately the same size, ⅔″. One represents a bird, the three
                            others have initial letters. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 117</bibl> John Thwaytes, Esq., quit-claims
                            to the prior &amp;c. of Boulton his right in the advowson of the church
                            of Broughton. An endorsement notes that it will be found amongst the
                            Recognisances for Easter 31 Hen. VI, on the K.R. Mem. Roll. <date>6
                                Sept. <supplied>1442.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 118</bibl> Transcripts (on paper) of an
                            Inspeximus by William, dean, and chapter of York, of a charter of John
                            abp. of York to Boulton, dated in the palace at York, 7 October, 1442,
                            confirming to them the church of Broughton. They are to pay 4/- to the
                            abp. and 2/8 to the dean and chapter: 10 marks to the vicar, and 3/4 in
                            Lent, yearly, to the poor of the parish. <date>7 Dec. c. 1443.</date>
                            Endorsed: ‘Ex Registro Domini Johannis Kemp quondam Eboracensis
                            Archiepiscopi, folio 454.’ </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 119</bibl> Indenture by which Thomas, prior
                            of Boulton, grants to John Thwaites and Isabella his wife the manor of
                            Hille, on condition that if they are ejected from the rectory of
                            Broughton they shall have again the manor of Hille. Given in the
                            chapter-house. <date>20 July <supplied>1452.</supplied></date>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Carlton.</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 120</bibl> Peter fitz-Grent gives the
                            advowson of Karelton, with two bovates of land in K., and two bovates of
                            land in Lotheriesdene with tofts (tochtis) and with common rights (‘et
                            cum communitate ville’) in wood and plain, to S. Mary’s Bochelton, in
                            free, for the soul of Everard his grandfather, &amp;c. Witnesses: Robert
                            the chaplain of Skipton, Mauger de Gisleburn, Adam the clerk of K., and
                            Alexander the parson of K., and Everard his heir, and William his
                            brother, and Aufras his brother, and Walter his brother, and Henry his
                            brother, and Hugh de Suttune, and William Favel, Helte de Estbi.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1160–c. 1180.</supplied></date><note
                                type="foot" n="1">The hand cannot be much later, and Peter occurs in
                                the <hi rend="italic">Cartae</hi> of 1166 (<hi rend="italic">Red
                                    Book of the Exchequer,</hi> i. 425–6).</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="178"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 121</bibl> Everard fitz-Peter Grent, lord of
                            Carletone, quit-claims to Boulton Abbey all his right in the advowson of
                            C. and the lands appurtenant, according to his father’s charter. The
                            prior &amp;c. will mention him in their prayers. Witnesses: John de
                            Estone, William de Hebbedene, William de Farenhile, William
                            fitz-Eduuard, Richard the chaplain, William de Somervil, Roger the
                            clerk. <date><supplied>c. 1230–c. 1250.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 122</bibl> Thomas de Alta Ripa, son and heir
                            of John de Alta Ripa quitclaims to Boulton Abbey all his right in the
                            advowson &amp;c. of C. Witnesses: Sirs Robert de Plumpton, Roberg de
                            Steveton, John Gilot, Henry de Kighelay, knights, John de Farnhil,
                            William de Cesterhunt, Richard Tempest, William of York, Everard Fauuel.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1290.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 123</bibl> Seventeenth century transcript of
                            letters of William, abp. of York, endowing the chapel of Carleton which
                            is assessed at 12 marks a year, with a vicarage house, small tithes, and
                            one mark a year. Given at Cawode. <date><supplied>30 June</supplied>
                                1311.</date>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Kildewyk.</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 124</bibl> Inspeximus by William, abp. of
                            York, of a charter of John de Lund, prior of Boulton in Craven,
                            assigning to the church of Kyldewyk all portions touching the vicarage
                            except tithes of corn, wool, lambs, and of the mill, dated [9] Feb. 1376
                            [rectius 1276], and given at Otteley. Given at York. <date>18 March
                                1321.</date> A portion of the Archbishop’s seal remains. </p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Preston.</hi></p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 125</bibl> William archbishop of York
                            announces that the vicarage of Preston was instituted by his
                            predecessor, Thomas, and that another assignment was made by the dean
                            and chapter <hi rend="italic">sede vacante</hi> (by letters dated at
                            Cawod, [20] Oct. 1307). He inspects letters of (i) John de Londa, prior
                            of Boulton (who with Richard de Ottley, one of the canons, was made
                            proctor of the monastery in this matter, 8 Feb. 1321); (ii) Robert de
                            Spaldyngton, perpetual vicar of Preston. They have submitted their
                            dispute to his decision and he has assigned the following to the vicar:
                                    <date><supplied>10 Feb. 1321.</supplied></date> all tithes
                            except (i) those coming from the plough, (ii) the tithe of wool, (iii)
                            the tithe of hay from 6½ oxgangs of glebe land, (iv) the <pb n="179"/>
                            tithe of hay from Raynor de Knoll of Helghfeld’s manor; a capital manse
                            in which the rector used to live, with a garden, common rights,
                            housebote and heybote; 9 oxgangs of land and 9 tofts. The vicar is to
                            bear all ordinary charges; in extraordinary charges the monastery is to
                            pay two parts and the vicar the third. Written by Richard de Snowhulle,
                            notary public. Given at York. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 126</bibl> Public instrument witnessing that
                            in the Cathedral church of York, Thomas Salby, vicar of
                            Preston-in-Craven gave power of attorney to Master William Malster,
                            Doctor of Decrees, canon of York, John Worseley, Bachelor of Laws,
                            William Brandon, John Gysburne and John Haymer, clerks, in a case before
                            the archbishop concerning his vicarage. <date>10 May 1455.</date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="org">
                <head type="heading">Priory of Holy Trinity, York<lb/></head>


                <div type="parish">
                    <head type="heading">Leeds.</head>

                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 127</bibl> The Dean and Chapter of S.
                            Peter’s, York, confirm to the monastery of Holy Trinity, York,
                            everything that Jordan Paganel, his sons William and Jordan, and their
                            men, may have granted, particularly the church of Leeds.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1170–90.</supplied></date> Seal, 3″ × 2⅛″, on
                            a tongue, brown wax, <hi rend="smallcap">SIGILLVM · CAPITOLI · [SAN]CTI
                                · PETRI · EBORACENS[IS].</hi> A figure of the prior, standing. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 128</bibl> Alan the clerk of Thornton, vicar
                            of the church of Adel, is bound to the prior of Holy Trinity, York, in
                            10 marks a year, and if any controversy is moved against them by A.
                            fitz-Hugh de Wit’, or by Hugh himself, by reason of a charter which the
                            prior &amp;c. asserts they sought (‘inpetraverunt’) from them in the
                            lifetime of A. the archdeacon and rector of Adel, to have the church on
                            the rector’s death, Alan will undertake the action at his own cost.
                            Witnesses: H. treasurer of York, master W. archdeacon of Nottingham,
                            master G. canon of York, master Alan de Claxton, master Martin de Semar,
                            master John de Hamerton, Hugh de Botend’, John fitz-Wido, Henry Bustard,
                            Robert de Essai, Herbert the janitor, Peter de Ardene, Henry de Tikil,
                            William Fit’. <date><supplied>1204–14.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 129</bibl> R[ichard] abbot of Selby, H.
                            treasurer, and L. canon of York, at the command of Pope Innocent III
                            ([9] Dec. [1204]) have passed judgment in a dispute between the priory
                            and the Abbey of <pb n="180"/> Kirkstall over an agreement by which the
                            Abbey was to pay 20/- for the tithes of 4 carucates of land in West
                            Hadinglai, ½ ploughland in East Hadinglai, 2 carucates in West Allerton,
                            and 1 bovate in East Allerton, and to pay tithe for any further land
                            acquired in that parish (Leeds).
                                <date><supplied>1204–5.</supplied></date> The Abbey, accused of
                            withdrawing the 2 ploughlands in East Allerton, objected that they had
                            received the tithes and paid the rent for 50 years with right unshaken.
                            It is now decreed that the Priory shall grant to the Abbey the tithes of
                            grain and vegetables from the 2 ploughlands in East Allerton, in
                            exchange for the tithes of 2 ploughlands of land in West Allerton, and
                            that the Abbey shall pay 3/- more, and shall remit the tithes of 18
                            acres and one oxgang in East Allerton.. Three seals, in green wax, left
                            to right: (i) seal of the abbot of Selby, 1<num type="fraction"
                                >11/16</num>″ × 2⅜″, the abbot enthroned, <hi rend="smallcap">RIC .
                                . . . . . GERMANI · DE · SELEBI.</hi> (ii) From a (?) Greek gem. A
                            discus-thrower and a recumbent athlete. Pointed oval, 1⅞″ × 1¼″, (iii)
                            Pointed oval, 1″ × 1⅜″, possibly a bird. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="org">
                <head type="heading">The Hospital of S. Wulfstan’s, Worcester</head>

                <p>For other deeds of this Hospital see the <hi rend="italic">Calendar of Charters
                        and Rolls in the Bodleian Library,</hi> pp. 590–600.</p>

                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Chaddleswick (Worcs.).</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 130</bibl> Indenture by which John Burton,
                            clerk, master of the Hospital of S. Wulfstan’s, Worcester, outside
                            Sudburyegate, leases to John Lynchalle of Alt church (Worc.) the manor
                            of Chaddewyche in the parish of Bromesgrove. For 69 years. Rent: 13/4.
                                    <date><supplied>29 Sept.</supplied> 1496.</date>
                        </p>

                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="parish">
                    <head>Hendulph (Worcs.).</head>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 131</bibl> Roger son of Adam Walensis of
                            Alechreton grants to William fitz-Galien for his homage and service,
                            that hide in A. of the manor of Hindlepe. Rent: 2/-. For this grant
                            William gave 27 marks. Witnesses: Sir Henry Lunet, Walter le Poiher,
                            Richard de Ambresseg’, Osbert de Abbetot, and Alexander his son, William
                            de Cokesie, Henry fitz-William, Gregory de Crombe, Roger de Mortone,
                            Simon de Mortone, Ralph Haket, and Thomas his son, Richard de Acle.
                                    <date><supplied>c. 1230.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="181"/>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 132</bibl> William Galien grants to Roger [de
                                Oyli?]<note type="foot" n="1">Or Roger fitz-Michael as in M. 133.
                                Roger de Oyli is mentioned in the charter, and the grantee’s name
                                was certainly Roger.</note> one hide … Rent: 1½<hi rend="italic"
                                >d.</hi> to W. G. and 2/- to the lords of the fee. Witnesses: Hugh
                            le Poher, sheriff of Worcester, Eudo de Beauchamp, Osbert de Albetot,
                            John de Albetot, Adam fitz-Philip, William Sebrond, Peter Dalle, Michael
                            Porter, William his son, William of Worcester, clerk. [<hi rend="italic"
                                >Torn.</hi>] <date><supplied>1236.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 133</bibl> Roger fitz-[Michael<note
                                type="foot" n="2">Taken from an endorsement.</note>] grants to Peter
                            Pichard … 2 acres … Rent . . . . 2/-. For this grant Peter gave 36
                            marks. Witnesses: Sir Walter de Beauchamp, Sir Hugh le Poiher, … Eudo de
                            Beauchamp, Peter de saltimarisco, Osbert de …, … William de Malveme,
                            Thomas the clerk, and Adam fitz-Philip, … Simon de St. John. [<hi
                                rend="italic">Partly obliterated.</hi>] <date><supplied>c.
                                    1240–50.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="charter">
                        <p>
                            <bibl type="shelfmark">MS. D. D. Ch. Ch. M. 134</bibl> Grant by Alexander Abetot, son of
                            John Abetot, to … Attested by Eudo de Beauchamp and the sheriff of
                            Worcester. <date><supplied>c. 1260–70.</supplied></date>
                        </p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">Fragment.</hi>]</p>
                    </div>
                </div>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
